<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[CX Social Dev Blog]]></title>
    <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-05T09:02:25+00:00</updated>
    <id>/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to edit a commit message]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/04/03/how-to-edit-commit-description"/>
            <updated>2017-04-03T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/04/03/how-to-edit-commit-description</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We use GitHub for hosting the code, and issue tracker behind CX Social. As you may already know, you can close issues automatically by adding <code>Closes #issue</code> to a commit message and merging it in the master branch. This is great because I always forget to close the fixed issue (it's also great for cross-linking between issues and commits).</p>

<p>But what if you forgot to add <code>Closes #issue</code> to your commit? Let me teach you a trick to edit a commit message.</p>

<p>Let's make a new directory to test it.</p>

<pre><code class="sh">$ mkdir demo-git-edit
$ cd demo-git-edit
$ git init
Initialized empty Git repository in /Users/hansott/Code/demo-git-edit/.git/
</code></pre>

<p>Okay great. We've got our repository ready. Let's add a file.</p>

<pre><code class="sh">$ touch app.js
</code></pre>

<p>Then add the following contents:</p>

<pre><code class="js">throw new Error('This is a bug!');
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="sh">$ git add app.js
$ git commit -m "Add bug"
[master (root-commit) 308c96d] Add bug
 1 file changed, 1 insertion(+)
 create mode 100644 app.js
</code></pre>

<p>Let's fix the bug by removing it.</p>

<pre><code class="sh">$ echo &gt; app.js
$ git diff
diff --git a/app.js b/app.js
index 128b630..8b13789 100644
--- a/app.js
+++ b/app.js
@@ -1 +1 @@
-throw new Error('This is a bug!');
+
$ git add app.js
$ git commit -m "Fixed bug"
$ git log
* 83ac3a3 Fixed bug
* 308c96d Add bug
</code></pre>

<p>There you go. We forgot <code>Closes #issue</code>. What can we do about it? It's important that you don't push (otherwise you'll have to use <code>--force</code> and you should <strong>never</strong> do that).</p>

<p>If you want to edit your last commit you can use:</p>

<pre><code class="sh">$ git commit --amend -m "Fixed bug" -m "Closes #issue"
[master f27a1ca] Fixed bug
 Date: Wed Feb 1 12:31:29 2017 +0100
 1 file changed, 1 insertion(+), 1 deletion(-)
</code></pre>

<p>You should consider committing with <code>$ git commit --amend</code>. It opens a proper text editor (like <a href="http://vim.sourceforge.net/">vim</a>) to write a comprehensive message (instead of using <code>-m "message"</code>). Did you notice I used <code>-m</code> twice? You can read about it in <a href="/blog/2017/01/24/some-tips-for-a-better-git-history/">Some tips for a better Git history</a>.</p>

<pre><code class="sh">$ git show f27a1ca
ommit f27a1caac3ee33ac3b0ef81040cd2c2f877f13f4
Author: Hans Ott &lt;hans.ott@clarabridge.be&gt;
Date:   Wed Feb 1 12:31:29 2017 +0100

    Fixed bug

    Closes #issue

diff --git a/app.js b/app.js
index 128b630..8b13789 100644
--- a/app.js
+++ b/app.js
@@ -1 +1 @@
-throw new Error('This is a bug!');
+
</code></pre>

<p>Hooray! We did it. What if we added other commits before we realised we forgot? <a href="https://git-scm.com/book/tr/v2/Customizing-Git-Git-Configuration">I'll assume you got a decent text editor configured for git</a>.</p>

<pre><code class="sh">$ git log
* 889da98 Add leftpad
* b1b364c Add library
* 05e664c Fixed bug
* 308c96d Add bug
</code></pre>

<p>We added 2 commits after our bug fix commit. Since <code>$ git commit --amend</code> can only change the last commit, we can't use it. Luckily, we know the secret behind the curtain: it's doing a git rebase of the last commit. Let's use git rebase for great good! Again, be careful, this won't work if you already pushed your work (you can inspect with <code>$ git log --decorate</code>).</p>

<pre><code class="sh">$ git rebase -i 308c96d  # use the commit JUST before the bug fix commit
</code></pre>

<pre><code>.g/r/git-rebase-todo
pick 05e664c Fixed bug
pick b1b364c Add library
pick 889da98 Add leftpad

# Rebase 308c96d..889da98 onto 308c96d (3 commands)
#
# Commands:
# p, pick = use commit
# r, reword = use commit, but edit the commit message
# e, edit = use commit, but stop for amending
# s, squash = use commit, but meld into previous commit
# f, fixup = like "squash", but discard this commit's log message
# x, exec = run command (the rest of the line) using shell
# d, drop = remove commit
#
# These lines can be re-ordered; they are executed from top to  bottom.
#
# If you remove a line here THAT COMMIT WILL BE LOST.
#
# However, if you remove everything, the rebase will be aborted.
#
# Note that empty commits are commented out
</code></pre>

<p>You'll have to replace <code>pick</code> before <code>05e664c Fixed bug</code> with <code>reword</code> and save it. Git will show the commit(s) you selected so you can edit it and save it.</p>

<pre><code>.g/COMMIT_EDITMSG
Fixed bug

Closes #issue
# Please enter the commit message for your changes. Lines starting
# with '#' will be ignored, and an empty message aborts the commit.
#
# Date: Wed Feb 1 12:31:29 2017 +0100
#
# interactive rebase in progress; onto 308c96d
# Last command done (1 command done):
#    reword 05e664c Fixed bug
# Next commands to do (2 remaining commands):
#    pick b1b364c Add library
#    pick 889da98 Add leftpad
# You are currently editing a commit while rebasing branch 'master' on '308c96d'.
#
# Changes to be committed:
#       modified:   app.js
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="sh">$ git rebase -i 308c96d
[detached HEAD 4225a9a] Fixed bug
 Date: Wed Feb 1 12:31:29 2017 +0100
 1 file changed, 1 insertion(+), 1 deletion(-)
Successfully rebased and updated refs/heads/master.
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="sh">$ git show 308c96d
commit 4225a9a3eb74b42772297a2f4b67b58696e11410
Author: Hans Ott &lt;hans.ott@clarabridge.be&gt;
Date:   Wed Feb 1 12:31:29 2017 +0100

    Fixed bug

    Closes #issue

diff --git a/app.js b/app.js
index 128b630..8b13789 100644
--- a/app.js
+++ b/app.js
@@ -1 +1 @@
-throw new Error('This is a bug!');
+
</code></pre>

<p>Hooray! We did it again. Now pat yourself on the back.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vim As A PHP IDE - Quality Control]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/03/15/vim-ide-quality-control"/>
            <updated>2017-03-15T09:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/03/15/vim-ide-quality-control</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>This blogpost is part of the "Vim As A PHP IDE" series, which starts <a href="/blog/2017/01/01/vim-ide-setting-up">here</a>.</strong></p>

<p>So it seems that people find it really handy that their IDEs tell them when things are going wrong, and I can't really disagree with that. So let's see how we can get pretty much the same thing in Vim, for PHP.</p>

<ul>
<li>I need to be warned of syntax errors.</li>
<li>I need to be warned of unused variables, methods, fields, etc.</li>
<li>Every language has their own rules for indenting and tabs vs. spaces, and maybe even every project.</li>
<li>What about coding standards like PSR-2?</li>
</ul>

<p>Basically I do two things here:</p>

<ol>
<li>I make sure that my editor is configured correctly for the language and the project, using a simple default configuration in my <code>.vimrc</code> which I overwrite on a project basis using <a href="http://editorconfig.org/">EditorConfig</a>.</li>
<li>I use some static analysis tools for the other parts.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="1.-basic-setup">1. Basic setup</h2>

<h3 id="filetype-plugin">Filetype plugin</h3>

<p>Depending on your taste, you might want to update your PHP filetype plugin in Vim, with a more modern version, for instance if you'd like <code>@param</code> highlighted differently in your PHPDoc blocks. You can find a more up-to-date plugin <a href="https://github.com/StanAngeloff/php.vim">here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="editor-config">Editor Config</h3>

<p>To properly configure my editor, I use the simple snippet in my <code>~/.vim/ftplugin/php.vim</code> that I also posted in the first episode of this blog series:</p>

<pre><code class="vim">" Some basic PSR code style rules
set tabstop=4           " Tab width
set softtabstop=4       " Soft tab width
set shiftwidth=4        " Shift width
set expandtab           " Use spaces instead of tabs
</code></pre>

<p>I override this with project settings, using <a href="http://editorconfig.org/">EditorConfig</a>. It's as easy as installing the <a href="https://github.com/editorconfig/editorconfig-vim">EditorConfig plugin</a> for Vim.</p>

<p>In my projects I then have a <code>.editorconfig</code> file that might look like this:</p>

<pre><code class="editorconfig">; This file is for unifying the coding style for different editors and IDEs.
; More information at http://editorconfig.org

root = true

[**.{php,js,scss,html}]
charset = utf-8
indent_size = 4
indent_style = space
end_of_line = lf
insert_final_newline = true
trim_trailing_whitespace = true
</code></pre>

<h2 id="2.-static-analysis">2. Static Analysis</h2>

<p>On to more interesting stuff, for the rest of our list: syntax errors, coding guideline violations, unused variables, and the like. The cool part of this, is that many of these things are covered by great PHP tools:</p>

<ul>
<li>syntax errors: <code>php -l</code></li>
<li>coding guideline violations: <a href="https://pear.php.net/package/PHP_CodeSniffer/">PHP Code Sniffer</a></li>
<li>unused variables and other possible issues with code: <a href="https://phpmd.org/">PHP Mess Detector</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Even greater is that there's a great Vim plugin that combines all of these quality control tools into one great automated package: <a href="https://github.com/vim-syntastic/syntastic">Syntastic</a>, and it's fantastically easy to install. Use your Vim package manager, and put some lines into your <code>.vimrc</code> to configure it:</p>

<pre><code class="vim">" Syntastic configuration
let g:syntastic_always_populate_loc_list = 1
let g:syntastic_auto_loc_list = 1
let g:syntastic_check_on_open = 1
let g:syntastic_check_on_wq = 0
</code></pre>

<p>Now to configure the PHP specific tools, that I mentioned above, I do it like this:</p>

<pre><code class="vim">" Syntastic configuration for PHP
let g:syntastic_php_checkers = ['php', 'phpcs', 'phpmd']
let g:syntastic_php_phpcs_exec = './bin/phpcs'
let g:syntastic_php_phpcs_args = '--standard=psr2'
let g:syntastic_php_phpmd_exec = './bin/phpmd'
let g:syntastic_php_phpmd_post_args = 'cleancode,codesize,controversial,design,unusedcode'
</code></pre>

<p>This works because the <code>phpcs</code> and <code>phpmd</code> binaries live in a <code>bin/</code> directory inside my project's directory (I installed them using composer). If you have global installs of these tools, you can just leave out these config lines, Syntastic knows where to find them. As we now have the <code>php -l</code> linter as a Syntastic checker, we can remove the <code>autocmd</code> from our <code>.vimrc</code>.</p>

<p>Some screenshots for the visually minded people:</p>

<p><img src="/images/2017-03-15-vim-ide-quality-control/syntax-error.png" alt="Syntax error detection with php -l" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/2017-03-15-vim-ide-quality-control/psr-violation.png" alt="PSR-2 violation" /></p>

<h2 id="wrapping-up">Wrapping up</h2>

<p>Now I get live feedback about the quality of my code! Great! On to the next episode.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bug Fixing: Creating Synergy Between Dev and Support]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/03/01/batman-chatman"/>
            <updated>2017-03-01T09:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/03/01/batman-chatman</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is about bugs. About bug-tracking software. About prioritising what issues to fix first. About client-developer communication. About Service Level Agreements. And about hotfixes.</p>

<p><center><img src="/images/2017-03-01-batman-chatman/oh-f.gif" alt="Oh, f*ck" /></center></p>

<p>If that didn't scare you away, well hello there!</p>

<h2 id="first-line-support">First Line Support</h2>

<p>CX Social is software that allows companies to respond to their incoming social data (Twitter mentions, Facebook wall posts, etc.) as fast and as efficiently as possible. The customer care agents of companies like Telenet, De Lijn, NMBS (in Belgium), and Lufthansa, Turkish Airlines, T-Mobile (worldwide) use CX Social day-in day-out. They've set-up highly customized workflows within our tool, including automated actions, advanced filtering and real-time communication.<br />
This makes CX Social a business-critical tool for our clients to serve their customers. To help with set-up, or if clients have discovered a bug in our system, there is direct in-app access to a live chat that puts them in contact with one of our support agents.<br />
These support agents handle several chats and incoming emails per hour. We use Olark for in-app live chat, and use Salesforce Desk as the tool to handle incoming emails.</p>

<p><center><img src="/images/2017-03-01-batman-chatman/olark-chat.png" alt="CX Social in-app Live Chat via Olark" /></center></p>

<h2 id="an-empowered-support-agent-means-less-bugs">An Empowered Support Agent Means Less Bugs</h2>

<p>The support agents are the people in our company that know our tool best. In several cases even better than us developers who wrote the code for it. We involve our support agents in testing new features we build. By making support part of the Q&amp;A-process, we assure they have used new features before clients put their hands on it, but also that the product team keeps solving <em>real</em> problems that our clients are having every day.<br />
Apart from that, we actively maintain FAQ documents that help support agents identify problems, and collect the correct information to reproduce issues. We - try to - regularly organise trainings that go deep into certain aspects of our application. The customer support agents for CX Social know the basics of html, can interpret some - if not most - of our monitoring dashboards and know about <code>oAuth</code> or <code>API's</code> and find their way around the Chrome Developer Tools.<br />
All with one goal: to be able to solve our clients' problems as fast as possible. (Read: With as little help from a developer as possible 😏 )</p>

<h2 id="a-direct-line-to-development">A Direct Line To Development</h2>

<p>For those cases where the help of a developer is wanted, our support team has a direct line open to development, and that's the internal Slack channel <code>#supdev</code> that all support agents have joined. The main goal of this channel is to discuss whether a certain <em>symptom</em> is in fact an issue. We've seen it work best if all these discussions happen through a single and public channel so that multiple people can jump in to help. This encourages learning from each other's questions and answers, and also helps to hand-over problems to teams in other timezones.
On the other hand, on active days, the constant flow of messages in the <code>#supdev</code> channel often get in the way of focus. That's why the people in our development team are taking turns in answering support questions in this channel, and by doing that allowing others to preserve their focus. The whole development team (all full stack developers) takes part in this schedule we nicknamed the 'chatman', in periods of one week.</p>

<p>The result of this direct line is;</p>

<ol>
<li>Less bugs:

<ul>
<li>Because some configuration errors might be spotted earlier;</li>
<li>Because multiple reports by clients get bundled into a single bug report;</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Better bug reports:

<ul>
<li>More detailed steps to reproduce;</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>

<h2 id="github-as-bug-repository">GitHub as Bug Repository</h2>

<p>We use GitHub Issues as our main bug tracker. Not that it matters that much, but here's some of the reasons we appreciate GitHub:</p>

<ul>
<li>Integration with the git repository;

<ul>
<li>Closing issues from your commit message via <code>closes #issueno</code>;</li>
<li>The automatic referencing between issues, pull requests and commits;</li>
</ul></li>
<li>It's simple and easy to use interface; and at the same time flexible enough due to its labeling system.</li>
<li>Its simple and extensive REST API.</li>
</ul>

<p>We have set-up an <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/creating-an-issue-template-for-your-repository/">issue template</a> to guide our support agents to provide as much of the relevant context as possible. This issue template makes sure we always know the User ID and Account ID of the person having/reporting the problem.</p>

<p>We have several types of issues; "critical", "minor" and "major", which we indicate with <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/creating-and-editing-labels-for-issues-and-pull-requests/">issue labels</a>. Most issues are classified as "minor", and the "major"/"critical" labels are reserved for those "drop everything and fix this"-type of problems.</p>

<p>Whenever a Desk case (= client report) results in a GitHub issue (= actual bugreport), we make sure to save the connection between the Desk case and GitHub issue in our own database. <em>(The why is explained later.)</em></p>

<p>In a typical week at CX Social around 10 bugs are reported, and while most of them take about 2 to 3 hours to fix, some take days.</p>

<h2 id="batman-will-fix-it">Batman Will Fix It</h2>

<p>Similar to how we have a dedicated person answering questions from our support team, the person(s) responsible for fixing bugs is also a rotated role. Each week different people are assigned the Batman role, and spend their week digging into the reported and confirmed issues, trying to find a solution for them.</p>

<p>This separation of bug fixing work from standard product development <em>(i.e. new features, or reworked features)</em> has the following advantages for us:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Everyone in the team will at some point be involved in fixing bugs, including bugs in parts of the code he/she doesn't know yet. Of course, everyone's free to go ask other people's advice, but it's definitely an efficient way of preventing knowledge silos. This contributes to everyone's knowledge of the code base, and also to how much care is given to writing clean &amp; well documented code.</p></li>
<li><p>In weeks a developer isn't assigned the Batman role, he/she can fully focus on the product development project; making it easier to stay focused and work towards target dates. Before we used a system like this, it was often much harder to make progress on product development, because there's always a certain bug that got more priority.</p></li>
<li><p>By separating these duties it also becomes more measurable how much effort is spent - team-wide - on each type of job, and how we should distribute our resources.</p></li>
</ul>

<p><center><img src="/images/2017-03-01-batman-chatman/scars.jpg" alt="Do you want to know how I got these scars?" /></center></p>

<p>At the same time, a system like this creates a few problems as well:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Probably the person trying to find the cause of a bug is not the person who originally wrote the code, and thus it might take more time than somebody who knows the ins and outs of what he/she wrote.</p></li>
<li><p>Bugs that aren't fixed by the end of the week, will of course not go away by itself, and a handover to the next batman is needed.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>The solution for this is simple: allow to deviate from the guidelines. In emergency situations, more people are working on bugs than just the Batman. And if you are close to a fix on Friday evening and fixing it will only take another half a day; of course that's what we do. And have regular in-person <code>#supdev</code>-meetings with the support team, and this and next week's Batman and Chatman.<br />
The agenda for these meetings is:</p>

<ul>
<li>What are the most important issues still needing a fix, from a support point of view?</li>
<li>What are blocking problems, from a dev point of view?</li>
<li>Passing on information to the next batman, both from support and from batman.</li>
</ul>

<p>We use this system in a tech team of 11 people, of which 7 people are involved in this Batman/Chatman schedule. The rest of the team is either designer, data scientist or ops people. While it works for us now, we realise it might become hard if the team grows.</p>

<p>On top of the GitHub API we built several dashboards that plot the trend in amount of open bugs and that show our average resolution time. These are the prime indicators we take into account when planning extra resources for this role. Our Slack bot will also notify us when issues stay open for too long, or are unassigned, or miss labels, etc.</p>

<p><center><img src="/images/2017-03-01-batman-chatman/issue-stats.png" alt="Amount of open issues over time" /></center></p>

<p>When an issue is closed but without a resolution (it's a duplicate, we were unable to reproduce it, it's a limitation of the external services we use, etc.) we indicate this with a resolution label. And similarly we tag all bugs with a label indicating which CX Social feature group it's related to. These two types of labels help us assess the quality of both our bug reports as identify problem areas with the application.</p>

<h2 id="prioritising-issues">Prioritising Issues</h2>

<p>The nature of a bug typically entails its priority; if something is a problem with a core feature of CX Social, for multiple accounts at once, it's labeled as "major", and thus has higher priority over bugs classified as "minor". Luckily, the amount of "major" bugs is limited. So, most of the time we spent fixing "minor" bugs. Typically we have between 10 and 30 of these bugs open, and from this to-do list for the Batman it's important we focus on those issues that have the most impact, for whatever reason. It's our support team that decides which of these to work on, since they know a bug's impact on customers best.</p>

<p><center><img src="/images/2017-03-01-batman-chatman/github-screenshot.png" alt="Some open issues" /></center></p>

<h2 id="what-didn%27t-work">What Didn't Work</h2>

<p>We didn't always work this way. Over the course of the last 5 years, we've had a whole bunch of different approaches.</p>

<p>In our first iterations Batman also did the duties of who we now refer to as Chatman. But complex bugs often require a lot of focus (and we found out: more so than for standard product development work), so this combined role, resulted in a lower bug closing efficiency. And that's of course the main target for a system like this.</p>

<p>Not having a Chatman at all, is even worse. The fact that a developer can add his/her perspective to a bug report, greatly enriches the quality of a bug report. The fact that this communication with the Chatman happens over chat, avoids a slow ping-pong of "needs more information" comments on GitHub issues.</p>

<p>While it's sometimes tempting to skip a weekly <code>#supdev</code>-meetings, we've found that not having a regular in-person meeting between development and support creates an invisible "hostility" where it feels like one party is fighting against the other: fixing bugs versus reporting bugs. While what really happens is two teams working together to fix customer issues. Talking in person can cause breakthroughs because ideas get validated or ping-ponged.</p>

<h2 id="deploying-fixes-%26-reaching-out-to-the-customer">Deploying Fixes &amp; Reaching Out to the Customer</h2>

<p>When a developer has fixed a bug, it's pushed to a separate branch which is then opened up for peer review via <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/about-pull-requests/">GitHub's Pull Requests</a> and the Support Agents involved in the bug report are notified. At this moment it's also possible to fire up a staging environment with the bug fix to verify by support.</p>

<p>Approved bug fixes are typically pushed out to production the same day. And by requiring issues to be closed via GitHub's <code>closes #issueno</code> commits, our continuous integration agent Jenkins also knows what fixes he is deploying to production. We have configured Jenkins so that it leaves a comment on the actual GitHub issue with the build number and exact time of when a fix for that issue went live. Jenkins will also make sure to post any bug fixes that are deployed to a few of the relevant Slack channels.</p>

<p><center><img src="/images/2017-03-01-batman-chatman/fixed-comment.png" alt="It's fixed" /></center></p>

<p>This Jenkins-comment on the GitHub issue will also trigger the reopening of any Desk cases associated with the GitHub issue, so that our support team immediately has the relevant cases reopened. By closing the loop back to the customer we make sure that customer immediately knows about a fix, and that we have confirmation of the fix as soon as possible.</p>

<p>What strategies have worked for you to speed up the bug fixing process and ensure positive communication between those encountering the bugs, reporting the bugs and fixing the bugs?</p>

<p><center><img src="/images/2017-03-01-batman-chatman/fixed-slack.png" alt="It's fixed" /></center></p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vim As A PHP IDE - Exploring Code]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/02/15/vim-ide-exploring-code"/>
            <updated>2017-02-15T09:30:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/02/15/vim-ide-exploring-code</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>This blogpost is part of the "Vim As A PHP IDE" series, which starts <a href="/blog/2017/01/01/vim-ide-setting-up">here</a>.</strong></p>

<p>As it turns out, finding things in a huge project is one of the main reasons people use an IDE. The most frequently used functionality seems to be</p>

<ul>
<li>searching for a file by its name;</li>
<li>searching within the current file;</li>
<li>searching for something arbitrary in the current project;</li>
<li>searching for methods or classes;</li>
<li>"jumping" to implementations of interfaces, child classes, definitions of methods;</li>
<li>finding usages of a method;</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finding-files-by-their-names">Finding files by their names</h2>

<p>Finding files is something I'm very bad at. I mostly remember only part of the name, or nothing at all. That's why I want to search for files in a "fuzzy" way, if at all. For fuzzy file search, a feature found in most text editors and IDEs these days, I use <a href="https://github.com/kien/ctrlp.vim">CtrlP</a>, which does that just fine. It also has some nice extra commands that let you fuzzily find files in your open buffers, tags (more on that later), and bookmarks.</p>

<p>Some people like to use <a href="https://github.com/scrooloose/nerdtree">NerdTree</a> to have a nice directory listing to the left of the screen, like in Sublime Text or similar editors. You can use it, and I sometimes do for its <code>:NERDTreeFind</code> command, but for most of your needs, the default file browser in Vim is great. You can open it like you open any file, just open a directory instead e.g. <code>:e src/</code>.</p>

<h2 id="searching-within-the-current-file">Searching within the current file</h2>

<p>To find something in the current file, Vim provides a huge number of options. There's the default forward search command, <code>/</code>, which can be pimped a bit to behave in a more "natural" way. In <code>.vimrc</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="vim">set incsearch           " search as characters are entered
set hlsearch            " highlight matches
</code></pre>

<p>And you can search backwards in exactly the same way by using <code>?</code>. Jump to next and previous hits with <code>n</code> and <code>N</code>. And of course you can use regex.</p>

<p>Then there are some more "special" ways of searching in the current file:</p>

<ul>
<li>Hop to the next occurence of the word under cursor <code>*</code></li>
<li>Hop to the previous occurence of the word under cursor <code>#</code></li>
<li>Hop to the next method <code>]]</code></li>
<li>Hop to the previous method <code>[[</code></li>
<li>Hop to the definition of a variable under cursor <code>gd</code> (goto definition)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="searching-for-arbitrary-text-in-the-current-project">Searching for arbitrary text in the current project</h2>

<p>I use <code>ag</code> as my main code search engine. It's a great command line tool to search codebases really fast. I use it on the command line, as well as in Vim, to replace <code>:vimgrep</code> with something faster. It's also the basis for some more interesting stuff, which I'll talk about later.</p>

<p>You'll need to have the <code>ag</code> binary for your operating system installed, using e.g. <code>brew install ag</code>. Check if it works by searching your codebase for a class, e.g. <code>ag HttpKernelInterface</code>.</p>

<p>Install the <code>Ack.vim</code> plugin, that you can find <a href="https://github.com/mileszs/ack.vim">here</a>. Then set the default search engine for the plugin to <code>ag</code> in your <code>.vimrc</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="vim">" Ack -&gt; Ag
if executable('ag')
    let g:ackprg = 'ag --vimgrep'
endif
</code></pre>

<p>Open Vim in your codebase's working directory and try it there, e.g. <code>:Ack HttpKernelInterface</code>. This should jump straight to the first match found.</p>

<p>The problem with this is that you don't have a visual representation of what else was found. Luckily, and much like <code>:vimgrep</code>, <code>:Ack</code> fills the quickfix list with matches, so you can use <code>:cwindow</code> to show matches (and see also <code>:cnext</code>, <code>:cprev</code>, <code>:cclose</code>). If you want your quicklist to open automatically if anything was found you can add this to your <code>.vimrc</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="vim">" Automatically open &amp; close quickfix window
autocmd QuickFixCmdPost [^l]* nested cwindow
</code></pre>

<h2 id="searching-for-methods-or-classes">Searching for methods or classes</h2>

<p>Now this is where it gets interesting, and where people somewhat underestimate Vim. Using an external application to generate an index of your project's "tags" (classes, interfaces, methods, variables, etc), which Vim can interpret, it provides jumping to all these things and back! This is great. How to set it up?</p>

<p>You'll need to have the <code>ctags</code> binary for your operating system installed, using e.g. <code>brew install ctags</code>. Check if it works by issueing this command <code>ctags --version</code>. I created a config file for it in my <code>$HOME</code> directory, called <code>.ctags</code> with this in it:</p>

<pre><code class="ctags">--recurse=yes
--tag-relative=yes
--exclude=.git
--exclude=composer.phar
--exclude=*.js
--exclude=*.vim
--langmap=php:.engine.inc.module.theme.install.php
--PHP-kinds=+cfi-vj
</code></pre>

<p>The line with <code>--PHP-kinds</code> tells <code>ctags</code> to index classes, functions, interfaces, but not variables or javascript functions. You can tune this to your likings.</p>

<p>If you now use <code>ctags</code> from the command line to generate the tags file for your project, using <code>ctags -R .</code>, a file that Vim can interpret, called <code>tags</code> will be created.</p>

<ul>
<li>You can now open Vim on a tag like so <code>vim -t HttpKernelInterface</code></li>
<li>Or search for that tag from within Vim <code>:tag HttpKernelInterface</code></li>
<li>Or jump to the tag under the cursor: <code>&lt;C-]&gt;</code> or <code>&lt;C-$&gt;</code> depending on keyboard layout</li>
<li>if you jumped to some tags and you want to jump back, use <code>&lt;C-t&gt;</code></li>
</ul>

<p>Of course there are <a href="https://github.com/ludovicchabant/vim-gutentags">plugins</a> to manage your <code>tags</code> files for you.</p>

<h2 id="finding-implementations-of-interfaces%2C-child-classes">Finding implementations of interfaces, child classes</h2>

<p>So this is where the aforementioned <code>Ack</code> magic comes in handy, as it's not default Vim functionality, and I didn't find a plugin to do these things either. I basically just created some functions that find PHP implementations of an interface, and PHP subclassses of a class. I just put them in my <code>.vimrc</code>, but I'm planning on creating a very simple plugin for them.</p>

<pre><code class="vim">" PHP Find Implementations
function! PhpImplementations(word)
    exe 'Ack "implements.*' . a:word . ' *($|{)"'
endfunction

" PHP Find Subclasses
function! PhpSubclasses(word)
    exe 'Ack "extends.*' . a:word . ' *($|{)"'
endfunction

noremap &lt;Leader&gt;fi :call PhpImplementations('&lt;cword&gt;')&lt;CR&gt;
noremap &lt;Leader&gt;fe :call PhpSubclasses('&lt;cword&gt;')&lt;CR&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, I added mappings to execute them for the word under cursor (<code>&lt;cword&gt;</code>). These key mappings should probably be done inside the PHP <code>augroup</code> we created in the previous post.</p>

<h2 id="finding-usages-of-a-method">Finding usages of a method</h2>

<p>Pretty much in the same spirit of the Vim functions I wrote to find implementations of an interface, I also wrote such a function to find usages of a method, which I also just added to my <code>.vimrc</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="vim">" PHP Find Usage
function! PhpUsage(word)
    exe 'Ack "::' . a:word . '\(|&gt;' . a:word . '\("'
endfunction

noremap &lt;Leader&gt;fu :call PhpUsage('&lt;cword&gt;')&lt;CR&gt;
</code></pre>

<h2 id="wrapping-up">Wrapping up</h2>

<p>So that is basically how I move around in our codebase, from within Vim. It's not all perfect, but it works perfectly fine for me and I find what I need, when I need it. Up to the next episode!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some tips for a better Git history]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/01/24/some-tips-for-a-better-git-history"/>
            <updated>2017-01-24T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/01/24/some-tips-for-a-better-git-history</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We're all heavy Git users in the CX Social development team. Honestly, we couldn't survive without it, as some of us are located across the planet, and we also use GitHub as our primary source of information, even when talking to other teams like the "Customer Support" team. Here's some small tips we learned along the way, when it comes to keeping your Git history clean.</p>

<h2 id="%60git-log%60-like-a-boss"><code>git log</code> like a boss</h2>

<p>I personally like to see everything there is to see about my git history. That's why I have an alias for <code>git log</code> that upgrades it with two default flags:</p>

<pre><code class="sh">git log --decorate --name-status
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>--decorate</code> flag shows ref names next to commits, meaning that you can see where <code>HEAD</code> points, and where your current (and remote) branches are pointing.</p>

<p>The <code>--name-status</code> flag activates the functionality to display which files were changed in that commit, below your commit message. This is great to see what changed in a commit, at first glance.</p>

<h2 id="writing-proper-commit-messages">Writing proper commit messages</h2>

<p>Another great tip, and maybe the best thing you'll take away from this blog post, actually comes from <a href="http://chris.beams.io/posts/git-commit/">another blogpost</a> which talks about writing great <code>git commit</code> messages. If you haven't read that post, go read it now, it's awesome. The main things I took away from it are these:</p>

<ul>
<li>use a proper text editor (like Vim) for writing your commit messages</li>
<li>write a commit subject as the first line, which complete this sentence:
<code>if applied, this commit will...</code></li>
<li>keep a blank line between the subject and what follows</li>
<li><strong>always</strong> write a commit body with <strong>what</strong> changed, and <strong>why</strong> you changed it.</li>
</ul>

<p>If you're too stubborn to write your commit messages using a decent text editor, here's a trick for you: you can use the <code>-m</code> flag on your command line more than once, to create paragraphs, e.g.:</p>

<pre><code class="sh">git commit \
-m "Add a second Hyperdrive as a backup" \
-m "When being followed by an imperial fighter, we want to be able to jump to hyperspace even though our first drive fails." \
-m "We're afraid this might cause some more radiation than expected."
</code></pre>

<p>But still, really consider using a text editor.</p>

<h2 id="distributed-versioning">Distributed versioning</h2>

<p>Git is a distributed versioning system, which means that it's designed to work offline, without a connection to the remote. We might as well exploit that to have great git history.</p>

<ul>
<li><code>git checkout</code> your own feature branch to work on something</li>
<li>don't <code>push</code> or <code>pull</code> while working on your feature. This gives you the advantage that you can <code>amend</code> your commit messages if you made a mistake, or that you can even <code>rebase</code> or <code>squash</code> your commits for clarity.</li>
<li>when you're done, push your branch. If you're working alone on your feature branch, this will work fine and you're done. If there are other people working on the same branch, don't panic and proceed to the next step</li>
<li><code>git pull --rebase origin {branch-name}</code> and then push</li>
</ul>

<p>As I mentioned before, <strong>not</strong> pushing or pulling, and still being able to work is a great feature of git. It means that you can work offline and do everything as if you were the only developer working on a project. You can undo mistakes you made in git, say, you forgot to include a file in a commit. Just <code>git commit --amend</code> it to your liking. Just don't go around and change parts of history that were already pushed.</p>

<p>Now the <code>--rebase</code> part in the <code>git pull</code> step is where it gets interesting. What this does, is undo everything you did since the last time you pulled the branch. Then it pulls from the remote, so that it's a fast-forward without conflicts with 100% certainty. And then it will apply your commits to that. This means that if you changed something, and someone else changed the same thing, you will have a rebase conflict. Which is great! You can now just fix your own conflict, and the history will still be linear! This also means that you will have to fix your own conflicts from now, instead of fixing other people's conflicts. Go on and push your branch when your done.</p>

<h2 id="merging-master-in-your-feature-branch">Merging master in your feature branch</h2>

<p>In analogy with what I said before, you can look at your feature branch as an "isolated" place where you can work on your feature in separation of everything that happens in other branches. Just do what you wanted to do, and never merge any branch into it, or at least minimize the amount of times you merge in case you really really have to.</p>

<p>The advantage this gives you, is great linear history in your feature branch, which <strong>only</strong> applies to that feature, which makes it easy to review or merge into other branches. This is even more true if you use the <code>git pull --rebase</code> feature from the previous tip.</p>

<p>Now, when your feature is ready and there are merge conflicts between your feature branch, and the branch you want to merge it into, e.g. <code>master</code>, you can solve that easily. Merge master in your branch once, and fix your own conflicts. Then merge your branch into master. There are some rebase tricks you can do here to keep linear history too, but I prefer to still merge branches when a feature is done.</p>

<h2 id="further-reading">Further Reading</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://chris.beams.io/posts/git-commit/">How to Write a Git Commit Message</a></li>
<li><a href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Distributed-Git-Distributed-Workflows">GitBook chapter on Distributed Workflows</a></li>
<li><a href="http://nvie.com/posts/a-successful-git-branching-model/">A successful Git branching model</a></li>
</ul>

<p>That's it! Enjoy your clean git logs!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Distributed Processing via RabbitMQ]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/01/07/distributed-processing-via-rabbit-mq"/>
            <updated>2017-01-07T08:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/01/07/distributed-processing-via-rabbit-mq</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Looking at <a href="https://stackshare.io/clarabridge-cx-social/web-application-stack">the tech stack of our CX Social product</a>, there's tens of components involved, and this post will go into detail about one of the most central components of our system: our RabbitMQ service.</p>

<p>RabbitMQ, or at least the concept of "Message Brokers" it implements, is central to the way we capture and digest the hundreds of social media messages we track each second, but also in how we throw around workload and tasks. Actually, it's so central we often take it for granted. So, let's take a step back and see why we use it ...</p>

<h2 id="what-is-a-queueing-system%3F">What is a Queueing System?</h2>

<p>Almost too simple to explain, a queueing system is a service where you can pile up a bunch of things to do (tasks) or messages to process (social media tweets etc. in our case). Different processes put messages on the queue (publish) while multiple other processes (consumers), possibly on other servers, read from these queues to e.g. execute a certain process.</p>

<p><center><img src="/images/2017-01-07-distributed-processing-via-rabbit-mq/queue.png" alt="What Is A Queue?" /></center></p>

<p>At Clarabridge CX Social, we use <a href="https://www.rabbitmq.com/">RabbitMQ</a>, but there's also <a href="https://kafka.apache.org/">Apache Kafka</a> or <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/sqs/">Amazon SQS</a> as often used alternatives.</p>

<p>Below is a screenshot of our RabbitMQ dashboard, showing a.o. about 3000 messages per second being processed.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2017-01-07-distributed-processing-via-rabbit-mq/rabbitmq-dashboard.png" alt="RabbitMQ Dashboard" /></p>

<h2 id="so%2C-what%27s-cool-about-queues%3F">So, What's Cool About Queues?</h2>

<h3 id="1.-do-stuff-async-and-handle-peaks">1. Do Stuff Async and Handle Peaks</h3>

<p>If at any point in our code we can procrastinate, we try to do so. If it's not super important to execute a certain function immediately, we push a message onto one of our RabbitMQ queues containing enough information to execute the function later, potentially by someone else. Easy. And lazy.</p>

<p>An example where we do this, is in the processing of webhooks for Facebook. For every like or comment that happens on one of the Facebook Pages that our CX Social clients own, Facebook sends us a real-time update containing who commented/liked which post. This information needs to be added to our clients' inboxes as soon as possible, but it's not vital that that's done in the same webhook-request that Facebook sends us. So, this page just pushes whatever information it gets from Facebook onto a queue. And an army of consumers for this queue turns these messages in e.g. comment objects to add to our data cluster.<br />
Whenever a Facebook post we monitor turns out to be hugely popular, and hundreds of post interactions per second is no exception, this queue serves both as a buffer (so we can handle these peak moments) and as a distributor (so multiple processes can massage and index the data).</p>

<p>Other common use cases include emailing or notifying several people. Say you have an online shop, and you want to notify a whole bunch of subscribers as soon as you add a new item to the inventory. Instead of sending these notifications in the same web request that the admin adds a product in, you push the notification-job on a queue, and let a different process send the actual emails or push notifications. Your initial request ("Add product x") stays fast, while all necessary emails are sent in the background.</p>

<h3 id="2.-split-up-complex-problems">2. Split up Complex Problems</h3>

<p>Queues are also particularly handy to split up heavy tasks into smaller, more manageable chunks of work. By using queues as the glue between these steps, you create more visibility into this chain of events.</p>

<p>One such chain that is vital to CX Social is the processing of a new incoming message (a tweet, an Instagram photo, etc.). Whenever a new messages is capture by our data crawling systems, there's several steps we need to do to get it to our clients, including:</p>

<ol>
<li>Checking which of our clients are interested in the message by matching it to the set-up of their accounts.<br />
(E.g. does it contain any of the keywords they're monitoring? Is it from a social profile they own?)</li>
<li>Resolving any of the urls in the post, as to get more details about the linked sites.</li>
<li>Computing the language the post's text is in.</li>
<li>Making an estimated guess of what the sentiment of the post could be.</li>
<li>Predict any labels that the client uses often for this particular post.</li>
<li>Indexing it to our main data cluster (ElasticSearch).</li>
<li>Predicting a possible reply for the post, if actionable.</li>
<li>Sending a notification to logged in users to their interfaces update with the new data.</li>
</ol>

<p>Each step of this process involves different services, of which some might be external, or slow, or down. By splitting this big chunk of work into smaller steps that are executed in sequence (each step generates an event that the next step listens to), we have better control over the execution of these steps. In addition, each step is simpler to monitor and thus debug (both in resource usage as speed).</p>

<h3 id="3.-give-certain-jobs-priorities">3. Give Certain Jobs Priorities</h3>

<p>By using different queues for different types of tasks, and by playing around with the amount of consumer-processes you have running for a certain queue, you have control over the priority of the tasks you push to this service, and different queues and types of tasks don't affect each other.</p>

<h3 id="4.-cross-service-communication">4. Cross-Service Communication</h3>

<p>We also use RabbitMQ in case different services need to talk to each other. At Clarabridge CX Social we have a service for real-time communication to a user's browser using websockets (via node.js/Socket.io). Every other service in our cluster can just send their messages there via RabbitMQ.
If a certain php process needs to send a real-time notification to a certain logged in user, the php process publishes an event to a RabbitMQ queue. A node.js server will then consume the event, and passes it on the client via socket.io.<br />
Using RabbitMQ as the intermediate we allow services written in a multitude of different languages to talk to each other.</p>

<h3 id="5.-monitoring-made-easy">5. Monitoring Made Easy</h3>

<p>A benefit of architecting your application this way, is that your Message Broker becomes an important and easy service to monitor, giving early indications when problems arise. As soon as a certain queue is growing beyond its expected volume, it's often an indication of a process that is slower than expected, or fully down.</p>

<p>If you monitor ...</p>

<ul>
<li>the amount of messages on a queue at any time;</li>
<li>the age of the oldest messages on a queue;</li>
<li>the rate of publishing to a queue;</li>
<li>the rate of consuming from a queue;</li>
</ul>

<p>... you have a very good indication of the health and performance of your application.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2017-01-07-distributed-processing-via-rabbit-mq/serverdensity-dashboard.png" alt="ServerDensity Dashboard" /></p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vim As A PHP IDE - Setting Up]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/01/01/vim-ide-setting-up"/>
            <updated>2017-01-01T08:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/01/01/vim-ide-setting-up</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I always get a lot of critique and disbelief when I mention that I use Vim to do my daily work in our PHP codebase. Most people in PHP have become avid users of <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/">PhpStorm</a>, a great PHP IDE made by JetBrains. I'm unsure about my own reasons to use Vim over PhpStorm but I guess these are some factors:</p>

<ul>
<li>I do not only write PHP</li>
<li>I love the fact that using Vim is like speaking a language</li>
<li>I live in my terminal</li>
</ul>

<p>I'm hereby starting a blog series about how I use Vim as my IDE of choice for PHP development. This is not a Vim tutorial, I'm assuming that you can look up the basics <a href="http://vimcasts.org/">anywhere else</a> and that you know about <code>:h :h</code>. However, I'll show you how I manage to do my work in Vim, how you can accomplish the same thing, and that I don't have a lot of missing features compared to users of other IDEs. This will be a blog series, and I'll list up episodes below as they come out. Let's start with setting up for a really basic PHP oriented workflow.</p>

<h2 id="basic-%60.vimrc%60-setup">Basic <code>.vimrc</code> setup</h2>

<p>First of all, never put things in your <code>.vimrc</code> that you don't understand. There's a huge amount of documentation in Vim's built-in help pages, which you can access like this: <code>:h &lt;keyword&gt;</code>. These are some simple things that I put in my <code>.vimrc</code> that I want at all times:</p>

<pre><code class="vim">filetype plugin indent on " use the file type plugins
syntax on                 " Syntax highlighting
set number nu             " Line numbers
set cursorline            " Color the cursorline
set autoindent            " Auto indenting
set smartindent           " Smart indenting
</code></pre>

<h2 id="basic-packages-i-use-all-the-time">Basic Packages I Use All The Time</h2>

<h3 id="package-manager">Package Manager</h3>

<p>To be able to easily install Vim plugins, I use <a href="https://github.com/tpope/vim-pathogen">Pathogen</a> or another Vim package manager, they make it so much easier to install the other packages.</p>

<h3 id="multiple-cursors">Multiple Cursors</h3>

<p>Even though it's really not Vim-like to use this, sometimes it comes in handy to have multiple cursors, even though we all know it can be done using find-and-replace or using Vim's macros. There are multiple packages for this, I use <a href="https://github.com/terryma/vim-multiple-cursors">this one</a>.</p>

<h3 id="surroundings">Surroundings</h3>

<p>Adding, removing and editing brackets around all Vim objects like "words", "paragraphs", "HTML-tags", etc has been made super easy with <a href="https://github.com/tpope/vim-surround">surround.vim</a>, which makes all these actions feel like they were in Vim all along.</p>

<h3 id="sessions">Sessions</h3>

<p>To manage my sessions, I usually don't use any plugins, since Vim has basic session management built in. You can save your current session using <code>:mksession! &lt;name&gt;</code>. Vim will save a file with the <code>&lt;name&gt;</code> you specified. If you then close vim, you can come back to the same session by starting vim like this: <code>vim -S &lt;name&gt;</code>.</p>

<p>If you go with the aforementionned approach, your sessions won't be saved automatically. If you want to get more out of your sessions, you might want to try the <a href="https://github.com/tpope/vim-obsession">vim obsession</a> plugin.</p>

<h3 id="snippets">Snippets</h3>

<p>As a last general purpose plugin, I'll recommend some snippet managers. I myself don't use any of them, just because I started out with a very basic Vim setup and I didn't yet feel the need for one of them. But if you'd like one, check out <a href="https://github.com/sirver/UltiSnips">UltiSnips</a> or <a href="https://github.com/msanders/snipmate.vim">SnipMate</a>.</p>

<h2 id="php-specific-things-for-your-%60.vimrc%60">PHP Specific things for your <code>.vimrc</code></h2>

<p>Let's start looking at some PHP specific configurations. I created a specific <code>augroup</code> section in my <code>.vimrc</code>, to be able to define <code>autocmd</code>s that can be overwritten if I reload my <code>.vimrc</code>. I'll reference this <code>augroup</code> in the following episodes of this series, too. Let's use it to run the <code>php -l</code> linter after we save a PHP file. Here we go:</p>

<pre><code class="vim">augroup PHP
  autocmd! " Clear all autocmd's in this group before running them again

  " Check for PHP syntax errors after saving a file
  autocmd BufWritePost {*.php} echom system("php -l ".expand('%'))

augroup END
</code></pre>

<p>Let's set some basic configuration for all PHP files that we'll open. Create a file called <code>~/.vim/ftplugin/php.vim</code> and put this in it:</p>

<pre><code class="vim">" Some basic PSR code style rules
set tabstop=4           " Tab width
set softtabstop=4       " Soft tab width
set shiftwidth=4        " Shift width
set expandtab           " Use spaces instead of tabs
</code></pre>

<h2 id="what%27s-next%3F">What's next?</h2>

<p>When I talk to people about their IDE of choice, which I don't do often, these are some topics which seem to be important:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="/blog/2017/02/15/vim-ide-exploring-code">exploring the codebase</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/2017/03/15/vim-ide-quality-control">quality control</a></li>
<li>git integration</li>
<li>testing integration</li>
<li>refactoring</li>
</ul>

<p>In the upcoming posts, I'll talk about those in more detail!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>