<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[CX Social Dev Blog]]></title>
    <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
    <updated>2018-11-28T10:26:38+00:00</updated>
    <id>/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lambda To The Rescue: Syntax]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2018/11/28/lambda-syntax"/>
            <updated>2018-11-28T11:30:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2018/11/28/lambda-syntax</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>This is the fifth post in a series about using Functional Programming concepts to make your Object Oriented code more comprehensible. Start <a href="/blog/2018/03/02/lambda-lists-to-wrap-failure">here</a> if you want to read the whole thing.</strong></p>

<h2 id="%E2%9C%A8-syntactic-sugar">✨ Syntactic Sugar</h2>

<p>When I was first reading <a href="http://learnyouahaskell.com/">Learn You A Haskell For Great Good</a>, I came across the term <em>Syntactic Sugar</em> and I was confused... My background in OOP languages made me cringe a little when I read about how you can create your own syntax in Haskell using infix operators and DSLs. It even goes so far that some functional languages have almost no syntax at all! Let's look at an example of "sugar":</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">map reverse
    (filter (\x -&gt; length x &lt; 5)
            ["foo", "bar", "baz", "qux", "ramsam"])
</code></pre>

<p>We're taking the list <code>["foo", "bar", "baz", "qux", "ramsam"]</code>, filtering out items that are 5 characters or longer, and reversing them all, one by one. The result is <code>["oof", "rab", "zab", "xuq"]</code>.</p>

<p>We can make this a little bit more readable by using Haskell's <code>$</code> infix operator, which allows us to remove some of the parentheses by evaluating the expression on its righthand side first:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">map reverse $ filter (\x -&gt; length x &lt; 5) $ ["foo", "bar", "baz", "qux", "ramsam"]
</code></pre>

<p>Although the parentheses are gone, we still have to read from right to left if we want to know what exactly the result of this will be. We basically pipe the result of the expression on the right of the <code>$</code> to the expression on the left side of it. Some languages like F# have the <code>|&gt;</code> operator which allows you to pipe from left to right, so the exact opposite of the <code>$</code> operator. It's not idiomatic Haskell, but in some cases we might want to use it to create some clarity.</p>

<p>Since we know <code>|&gt;</code> is the exact opposite of <code>$</code>, let's just try to write it ourselves. In Haskell, infix operators are just normal functions with two parameters. Here's an example:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">*repl &gt; 2 + 3
5

*repl &gt; (+) 2 3
5
</code></pre>

<p>The function <code>(+)</code> can be used as a normal Haskell function, writing the function first and its arguments after it, or as an infix operator, without the parentheses. So we know <code>($)</code> is a function taking two parameters, and we have <code>flip</code> which takes a function with two parameters, and flips the order of them!</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">(|&gt;) = flip ($)
</code></pre>

<p>Easy! Let's now write the original example using <code>(|&gt;)</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">["foo", "bar", "baz", "qux", "ramsam"]
  |&gt; filter (\x -&gt; length x &lt; 5)
  |&gt; map reverse
</code></pre>

<p>We created our own syntactic sugar! We can now read this left to right, or top to bottom as you will. The result of the first expression you read will be "piped" to the next as last parameter! We get the exact same result <code>["oof", "rab", "zab", "xuq"]</code>.</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%92%AC-domain-language">💬 Domain Language</h2>

<p>As you saw in the last example, we can create our own infix functions in Haskell. This can be very useful to create more readable code, using the language of the domain. Let's see a typical example of a function that doesn't do that:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">changeAddress :: Client -&gt; Address -&gt; Client
</code></pre>

<p>Now when we use this function in the classical way, it looks like this:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">let abbeyRoad3 = "3 Abbey Road, London NW8 9AY, UK"
let updatedClient = changeAddress client abbeyRoad3
</code></pre>

<p>which doesn't read very well... What if we could use an infix here?</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">let updatedClient = client `changesAddressTo` abbeyRoad3
</code></pre>

<p>Using backticks we can use a function as an infix operator. The only thing we needed to change was the name of the function, and now this looks like a sentence!</p>

<p><code>client changedAddressTo abbeyRoad3</code></p>

<p>This is now the function type:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">changedAddressTo :: Client -&gt; Address -&gt; Client
</code></pre>

<p>So a simple changed lead to a better understanding of the code.</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%93%89-the-absolute-minimum">📉 The Absolute Minimum</h2>

<p>In the previous examples, you could see how we can mold the existing syntax to our likings, and use that to create very understandable code. Now let's see what happens when you take a language that has almost no syntax at all, like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scheme_(programming_language)">scheme</a>. Literally, the only syntax in scheme is <code>(</code> and <code>)</code>. The rest are functions. Let's check out some code:</p>

<pre><code class="scheme">(define sum
  (lambda (list)
    (cond
      ((null? list) 0)
      (else (+ (car list) (sum (cdr list)))))))
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, there are lots of <code>(</code>s and <code>)</code>s. Basically, every <code>()</code> combo is a function call.</p>

<ul>
<li><code>(define name body)</code> defines a variable. In this case, it's called <code>sum</code>.</li>
<li><code>(lambda (arguments) body)</code> defines a function. In this case, it has an argument called <code>list</code>.</li>
<li><code>(cond (condition result1) (else result2))</code> creates a conditional. If the <code>condition</code> is <code>#t</code> (true), we return <code>result1</code>, else <code>result2</code>.</li>
<li><code>(null? list)</code> checks if a list is empty.</li>
<li><code>(+ a b)</code> returns the sum of two numbers.</li>
<li><code>(car list)</code> returns the first item of a list (the <code>head</code> of the list).</li>
<li><code>(sum list)</code> is the recursive call to our own defined function.</li>
<li><code>(cdr list)</code> returns a list without its <code>head</code> (the <code>tail</code> of the list).</li>
</ul>

<p>Almost all of the above functions can be defined in <code>scheme</code> itself. That's why you'll find a lot of <code>scheme</code> parser or environments written in <code>scheme</code>. Even the datatype of a list can be written as a function! And it doesn't end there! Scheme has support for macro's which will let you manipulate your own code!</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%A4%B7%E2%80%8D%E2%99%82%EF%B8%8F-what%27s-the-point%3F">🤷‍♂️ What's the point?</h2>

<p>My point isn't that you should try to minimize the amount of syntax to have a good language, but I'm always looking for better ways to write stuff. This means that languages where you can create your own syntax have a high appeal to me. I love to read code that tells a story, so that my brain can try and understand the problem &amp; the solution at hand, instead of the code. I think a lot of functional programming languages have strong support for writing code like this, compared to most OOP languages.</p>

<p>That doesn't mean we can't apply a lot of this in our day-to-day OOP codebases. See what you can do for expressiveness. Can you give your classes, functions and variables better names? How can you lower the cognitive overhead needed to understand the code? How can we bring developer time down? Experimenting with this is something we can do in all languages, but it gets easier if we try and look around to the other languages and ecosystems around us! Don't get stuck in the idioms of the language you're spending the most time with, try stuff, look around, conquer the world!</p>

<p>It's also worth mentioning that there are whole communities around "designing software according to the domain" and "using the language of the domain". If you want to learn more, check out <a href="http://dddcommunity.org/book/evans_2003/">Domain Driven Design</a>! I've been going to the <a href="https://dddeurope.com/">DDD Europe Conference</a> and <a href="https://www.meetup.com/dddbelgium/">DDD Belgium meetups</a> for a few years now, and I must say, a lof of DDD people are trying functional languages!</p>

<p>That concludes this post. I hope you try some of this stuff soon! Happy programming y'aλλ! 🖖</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lambda To The Rescue: Monoids]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2018/10/08/lambda-monoids"/>
            <updated>2018-10-08T10:30:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2018/10/08/lambda-monoids</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>This is the fourth post in a series about using Functional Programming concepts to make your Object Oriented code more comprehensible. Start <a href="/blog/2018/03/02/lambda-lists-to-wrap-failure">here</a> if you want to read the whole thing.</strong></p>

<h2 id="%E2%98%95%EF%B8%8F-ordering-some-coffees">☕️ Ordering some coffees</h2>

<p>In the previous posts, you already came across a few functional programming concepts. Let's explore one more. Let's say we went to a coffee bar and we want to calculate the total price of an order of coffees:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">- Lungo           € 2.50
- Lungo           € 2.50
- Cappuccino      € 2.90
- Double Espresso € 2.10
- Iced Coffee     € 4.50
</code></pre>

<p>If you want to quickly do this from the top of your head, it makes sense to calculate it like this:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">2.50 + 2.50 + 2.90 + 2.10 + 4.50
= (2.50 + 2.50) + (2.90 + 2.10) + 4.50
= 5             + 5             + 4.50
= 10                            + 4.50
= 14.50
</code></pre>

<p>instead of</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">2.50 + 2.50 + 2.90 + 2.10 + 4.50
= 2.50 + (2.50 + 2.90) + (2.10 + 4.50)
= 2.50 + 5.40          + 6.60
= 7.90                 + 6.60
= 14.50
</code></pre>

<p>As you already knew, these two approaches yield the same results. We say the location of the <code>(</code> and <code>)</code> when doing <code>+</code> isn't important, or <code>+</code> is <em>associative</em>.</p>

<p>Usually the receipt has a line "service" with some service costs of the order as well. In this case, since we ordered more than 4 coffees, we get service for free. The actual receipt looked like this:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">- Lungo           € 2.50
- Lungo           € 2.50
- Cappuccino      € 2.90
- Double Espresso € 2.10
- Iced Coffee     € 4.50

- service         € 0
</code></pre>

<p>Does this change our calculation?</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">(2.50 + 2.50) + (2.90 + 2.10) + 4.50 + 0
= 5           + 5             + 4.50 + 0
= 10                          + 4.50 + 0
= 14.50                              + 0
= 14.50
</code></pre>

<p>Not at all! We conclude that 0 is "neutral" in that it doesn't change our calculations when using <code>+</code>. We call this <code>0</code> value <em>identity</em>.</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%A7%90-monoids">🧐 Monoids</h2>

<p>Now, when we find these two properties (associativity and neutral element) for a function and its data, we found a <em>Monoid</em>. Cool! Let's see if we can find some other Monoids!</p>

<p>Let's see if a list of integers, and the operation <code>++</code> (append) form a Monoid:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">$ ([1, 2] ++ [3, 4]) ++ [5, 6]
[1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6]

$ [1, 2] ++ ([3, 4] ++ [5, 6])
[1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6]
</code></pre>

<p>Ok, we have associativity, let's check if we can find a neutral element. How about the empty list?</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">$ [1, 2] ++ []
[1, 2]
</code></pre>

<p>Nice! We found another Monoid!</p>

<p>How about this:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">data DiskUsage = DiskUsage { server :: String
                           , consumed :: Int
                           } deriving (Eq, Show)

data ServerStats = ServerStats { totalInGB :: Int
                               , perServer :: [DiskUsage]
                               } deriving (Eq, Show)

mergeServerStats :: ServerStats -&gt; ServerStats -&gt; ServerStats
mergeServerStats a b = ServerStats { totalInGB = totalInGB a + totalInGB b
                                   , perServer = perServer a ++ perServer b
                                   }
</code></pre>

<p>A program we could use to measure disk usage in our fictional data center's server racks returns <code>ServerStats</code> per rack. For every server in the rack, there's a <code>DiskUsage</code> entry in the <code>perServer</code> list. To easily calculate the total disk usage in our fictional data center, we just use <code>mergeServerStats</code> to sum it all, <em>et voilà</em> we get one <code>ServerStats</code> with a total amount of GB used, and a list of all servers with their <code>DiskUsage</code>. (Note that the <code>totalInGB</code> can be totally wrong in this example. In a real world application you would just calculate that from the <code>perServer</code> value at all times. It's there because of convenience: you can immedately see how much disk usage is for a given rack.)</p>

<p>The question is, is this a <strong>Monoid</strong>? 🤔</p>

<p>To talk about a Monoid, we know we need a datatype. In this case we have <code>ServerStats</code>. Good. We also need a binary operation. We have <code>mergeServerStats</code>. Nice! We're halfway there. Let's see if we have the other stuff we need:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>associativity:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">$ foo = DiskUsage { server = "foo", consumed = 42 }
$ bar = DiskUsage { server = "bar", consumed = 99 }
$ baz = DiskUsage { server = "baz", consumed = 1 }
$ qux = DiskUsage { server = "qux", consumed = 0 }
$
$ rack1 = ServerStats { totalInGB = 42, perServer = [foo] }
$ rack2 = ServerStats { totalInGB = 100, perServer = [bar, baz] }
$ rack3 = ServerStats { totalInGB = 0, perServer = [qux] }
$
$ result1 = mergeServerStats (mergeServerStats rack1 rack2) rack3
$ result2 = mergeServerStats rack1 (mergeServerStats rack2 rack3)
$
$ result1 == result2
True
</code></pre>

<p>Applying <code>mergeServerStats</code> first to <code>rack1</code> and <code>rack2</code>, and then applying the same function to the result of the first calculation and <code>rack3</code> had the same result as first applying <code>mergeServerStats</code> to <code>rack1</code> and the result of applying that same function to <code>rack2</code> and <code>rack3</code>. We have associativity!</p></li>
<li><p>neutral element:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">$ foo = DiskUsage { server = "foo", consumed = 42 }
$
$ rack1 = ServerStats { totalInGB = 42, perServer = [foo] }
$ neutral = ServerStats { totalInGB = 0, perServer = [] }
$
$ result = mergeServerStats rack1 neutral
$
$ result == rack1
True
</code></pre>

<p>We were able to find a <code>ServerStats</code> value <code>neutral</code> that, when appended to another value <code>rack1</code> using <code>mergeServerStats</code> resulted in the same value as <code>rack1</code> again! This means we have a neutral element!</p></li>
</ul>

<p>We can conclude that <code>ServerStats</code> forms a Monoid with its operation <code>mergeServerStats</code>.</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%92%B0-usefulness">💰 Usefulness</h2>

<p>Now why is this such a big deal? Why do we keep rambling on about this? Let's evaluate this next question from our fictional operations engineers:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Our datacenter grew quickly and we now have 10 racks with 10 servers each. We have a script that produces a <code>ServerStats</code> entry per rack. We want to know the total disk usage across all racks. Can we do this?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We quickly head back to <a href="/blog/2018/06/27/lambda-recursion/#recognizing-a-pattern">last "Lambda To The Rescue" episode</a> and check out the paragraph about <code>fold</code>. Let's see if folds can help us!</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">$ foldr mergeServerStats neutral [ rack1, rack2, rack3, ... ]
ServerStats { totalInGB = 142
            , perServer = [ DiskUsage {server = "foo", consumed = 42}
                          , DiskUsage {server = "bar", consumed = 99}
                          , DiskUsage {server = "baz", consumed = 1}
                          , DiskUsage {server = "qux", consumed = 0}
                          , ...
                          ]
            }
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, we used all aspects of the Monoid in this example. We used the <em>neutral element</em> to have a starting value for our <code>foldl</code> invocation. We gave <code>foldl</code> the <code>mergeServerStats</code> binary operation over our datatype, and didn't worry about order of evaluation, which is where the <code>associativity</code> was helpful (we don't have to worry about implementation of <code>foldl</code>).</p>

<p>So, when we find out we're working with a Monoid, we immediately know we can <code>fold</code> easily over lists of that datatype!</p>

<p>In fact, if you're acquainted with <em>MapReduce</em>, a strategy for processing lots of data, you'll see that having a list of data allows you to <code>map</code> over it, and finding a Monoid between the datatype inside that list and the operation you want to do will allow you to <code>reduce</code> (or <code>fold</code>) easily over the list. Now you know what to look for!</p>

<p>Aside from "knowing what we can do with it", there's another benefit to understanding <code>Monoid</code>s, and that is <em>familiarity</em>. If you're checking out a codebase, and you find a Monoid instance, you'll feel right at home, and you'll understand the operations done on that particular datatype much easier than before. Which leads me to "formalizing".</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%A4%AF-formalizing">🤯 Formalizing</h2>

<p>You can even go further with this: in Haskell, there's a datatype <code>Monoid</code> which formalizes these properties in a typeclass:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">class Monoid m where
  mempty :: m
  mappend :: m -&gt; m -&gt; m
  mconcat :: [m] -&gt; m
  mconcat = foldr mappend mempty
</code></pre>

<p>This means that you can formalize that your datatype &amp; operation combo is a <code>Monoid</code> instance, because it has a neutral element <code>mempty</code> and a binary operation <code>mappend</code>. You then get <code>mconcat</code> for free, which is the same as doing the <code>foldr</code> of the last example. Let's do this for our <code>ServerStats</code> type:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">instance Monoid ServerStats where
  mempty = ServerStats { totalInGB = 0, perServer = [] }
  mappend = mergeServerStats
</code></pre>

<p>We can now do this:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">$ mconcat [rack1, rack2, rack3]
ServerStats { totalInGB = 142
            , perServer = [ DiskUsage {server = "foo", consumed = 42}
                          , DiskUsage {server = "bar", consumed = 99}
                          , DiskUsage {server = "baz", consumed = 1}
                          , DiskUsage {server = "qux", consumed = 0}
                          ]
            }
</code></pre>

<p>This <code>mconcat</code> function thus comes for free and will work on any <code>Monoid</code>! You can mostly guess the behaviour of this function whenever you see it!</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%98%85-back-to-oop">😅 Back to OOP</h2>

<p>What to do with this knowledge in the Object Oriented world? We use lists to work with objects of the same type constantly, and do operations on objects in those lists to gather new information. Most of the time I see this, it's done using <code>foreach</code> or something like it. However, as far as I'm concerned there's no difference to the Functional Programming world here. If you already embrace <code>map</code>, <code>filter</code> and <code>reduce</code>, you should also be thinking about the datastructure inside the list: is it a <em>Monoid</em>? You'll then understand better how it will behave when doing operations on it and you'll immediately know which the best reducer functions are!</p>

<p>That concludes this post. I hope you try it out soon! Happy programming y'aλλ! 🖖</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[👾 Anthony and Jasper at Nordic.js 2018]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2018/09/28/anthony-and-jasper-went-to-nordic"/>
            <updated>2018-09-28T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2018/09/28/anthony-and-jasper-went-to-nordic</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><center>
<img src="/images/2018-09-10-anthony-and-jasper-went-to-nordic.js-2018/nordicjs.png" alt="Nordic.js cover" />
</center></p>

<p>Our colleague Anthony was so impressed by <a href="https://engagor.github.io/blog/2017/09/15/nordicjs/">last year's edition</a> that he decided to return this year.
He even convinced me to go with him to this cool web conference.</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-permalink="https://www.instagram.com/p/BnbWhy8FtVJ/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_medium=loading" data-instgrm-version="12" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:540px; min-width:326px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:16px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BnbWhy8FtVJ/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_medium=loading" style=" background:#FFFFFF; line-height:0; padding:0 0; text-align:center; text-decoration:none; width:100%;" target="_blank"> <div style=" display: flex; flex-direction: row; align-items: center;"> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 40px; margin-right: 14px; width: 40px;"></div> <div style="display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center;"> <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 100px;"></div> <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 60px;"></div></div></div><div style="padding: 19% 0;"></div><div style="display:block; height:50px; margin:0 auto 12px; width:50px;"><svg width="50px" height="50px" viewBox="0 0 60 60" version="1.1" xmlns="https://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="https://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><g stroke="none" stroke-width="1" fill="none" fill-rule="evenodd"><g transform="translate(-511.000000, -20.000000)" fill="#000000"><g><path d="M556.869,30.41 C554.814,30.41 553.148,32.076 553.148,34.131 C553.148,36.186 554.814,37.852 556.869,37.852 C558.924,37.852 560.59,36.186 560.59,34.131 C560.59,32.076 558.924,30.41 556.869,30.41 M541,60.657 C535.114,60.657 530.342,55.887 530.342,50 C530.342,44.114 535.114,39.342 541,39.342 C546.887,39.342 551.658,44.114 551.658,50 C551.658,55.887 546.887,60.657 541,60.657 M541,33.886 C532.1,33.886 524.886,41.1 524.886,50 C524.886,58.899 532.1,66.113 541,66.113 C549.9,66.113 557.115,58.899 557.115,50 C557.115,41.1 549.9,33.886 541,33.886 M565.378,62.101 C565.244,65.022 564.756,66.606 564.346,67.663 C563.803,69.06 563.154,70.057 562.106,71.106 C561.058,72.155 560.06,72.803 558.662,73.347 C557.607,73.757 556.021,74.244 553.102,74.378 C549.944,74.521 548.997,74.552 541,74.552 C533.003,74.552 532.056,74.521 528.898,74.378 C525.979,74.244 524.393,73.757 523.338,73.347 C521.94,72.803 520.942,72.155 519.894,71.106 C518.846,70.057 518.197,69.06 517.654,67.663 C517.244,66.606 516.755,65.022 516.623,62.101 C516.479,58.943 516.448,57.996 516.448,50 C516.448,42.003 516.479,41.056 516.623,37.899 C516.755,34.978 517.244,33.391 517.654,32.338 C518.197,30.938 518.846,29.942 519.894,28.894 C520.942,27.846 521.94,27.196 523.338,26.654 C524.393,26.244 525.979,25.756 528.898,25.623 C532.057,25.479 533.004,25.448 541,25.448 C548.997,25.448 549.943,25.479 553.102,25.623 C556.021,25.756 557.607,26.244 558.662,26.654 C560.06,27.196 561.058,27.846 562.106,28.894 C563.154,29.942 563.803,30.938 564.346,32.338 C564.756,33.391 565.244,34.978 565.378,37.899 C565.522,41.056 565.552,42.003 565.552,50 C565.552,57.996 565.522,58.943 565.378,62.101 M570.82,37.631 C570.674,34.438 570.167,32.258 569.425,30.349 C568.659,28.377 567.633,26.702 565.965,25.035 C564.297,23.368 562.623,22.342 560.652,21.575 C558.743,20.834 556.562,20.326 553.369,20.18 C550.169,20.033 549.148,20 541,20 C532.853,20 531.831,20.033 528.631,20.18 C525.438,20.326 523.257,20.834 521.349,21.575 C519.376,22.342 517.703,23.368 516.035,25.035 C514.368,26.702 513.342,28.377 512.574,30.349 C511.834,32.258 511.326,34.438 511.181,37.631 C511.035,40.831 511,41.851 511,50 C511,58.147 511.035,59.17 511.181,62.369 C511.326,65.562 511.834,67.743 512.574,69.651 C513.342,71.625 514.368,73.296 516.035,74.965 C517.703,76.634 519.376,77.658 521.349,78.425 C523.257,79.167 525.438,79.673 528.631,79.82 C531.831,79.965 532.853,80.001 541,80.001 C549.148,80.001 550.169,79.965 553.369,79.82 C556.562,79.673 558.743,79.167 560.652,78.425 C562.623,77.658 564.297,76.634 565.965,74.965 C567.633,73.296 568.659,71.625 569.425,69.651 C570.167,67.743 570.674,65.562 570.82,62.369 C570.966,59.17 571,58.147 571,50 C571,41.851 570.966,40.831 570.82,37.631"></path></g></g></g></svg></div><div style="padding-top: 8px;"> <div style=" color:#3897f0; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:550; line-height:18px;"> Dit bericht bekijken op Instagram</div></div><div style="padding: 12.5% 0;"></div> <div style="display: flex; flex-direction: row; margin-bottom: 14px; align-items: center;"><div> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(0px) translateY(7px);"></div> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; height: 12.5px; transform: rotate(-45deg) translateX(3px) translateY(1px); width: 12.5px; flex-grow: 0; margin-right: 14px; margin-left: 2px;"></div> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(9px) translateY(-18px);"></div></div><div style="margin-left: 8px;"> <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 20px; width: 20px;"></div> <div style=" width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 2px solid transparent; border-left: 6px solid #f4f4f4; border-bottom: 2px solid transparent; transform: translateX(16px) translateY(-4px) rotate(30deg)"></div></div><div style="margin-left: auto;"> <div style=" width: 0px; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-right: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(16px);"></div> <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; flex-grow: 0; height: 12px; width: 16px; transform: translateY(-4px);"></div> <div style=" width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-left: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(-4px) translateX(8px);"></div></div></div></a> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BnbWhy8FtVJ/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_medium=loading" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">FIKA!!💖💖 #nordicjs</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">Een bericht gedeeld door <a href="https://www.instagram.com/nordicjs/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_medium=loading" style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px;" target="_blank"> Nordic.js</a> (@nordicjs) op <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2018-09-07T13:56:58+00:00">7 Sep 2018 om 6:56 (PDT)</time></p></div></blockquote>

<h2 id="hosts-%F0%9F%91%A9%E2%80%8D%F0%9F%9A%80%F0%9F%91%A8%E2%80%8D%F0%9F%9A%80">Hosts 👩‍🚀👨‍🚀</h2>

<p>First of all, we had two very funny hosts: <a href="https://twitter.com/unnderbar">Unn</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/mpjme">MPJ</a>.</p>

<p>They asked every speaker for three words that they would creatively use when introducing the next speaker to the audience. This resulted in some weird introductions when the speakers picked completely random words to see what our hosts could come up with. They also provided some entertainment between speakers.</p>

<p>Check out this clip of the "Fight Scene Karaoke" they did on stage:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">starting the second day for <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nordicjs?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#nordicjs</a> <a href="https://t.co/xJo8UcOMhq">pic.twitter.com/xJo8UcOMhq</a></p>&mdash; Alejandro Oviedo (@a0viedo) <a href="https://twitter.com/a0viedo/status/1037969613080997890?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">7 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<p>MPJ has his own YouTube channel <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCO1cgjhGzsSYb1rsB4bFe4Q">Fun Fun Functions</a> where you can find some development discussions with some of the speakers.</p>

<h2 id="talks-%F0%9F%92%AC">Talks 💬</h2>

<p><em>At the time of writing no videos are online but they will be soonish. Check the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/nordicjs">Nordic.js youtube channel</a> for updates.</em></p>

<p>Also this year it was a single track conference. They had a good variety of light talks like "hey I have a good story/practice for you" and some very code rich "let's take a closer look" talks.</p>

<p>All talks were about Javascript, frontend development in general and the Javascript community. Below is a small list of my favourites.</p>

<h3 id="building-foundations-of-the-node.js-community"><a href="http://nordicjs.com/speakers#tierney-cyren">Building Foundations of the Node.js Community</a></h3>

<p>by <a href="https://twitter.com/bitandbang">Tierney Cyren</a></p>

<p>Tierney is a Co-chair of the Node.js Community Committee, and a member of the Node.js Evangelism Working Group.
Tierney kicked off the conference with a motivating and inspiring keynote about Node.js and why it has such a great ecosystem behind it.
Main thought: Everything is about community and everybody can be part of it.</p>

<h3 id="fast-but-not-furious%3A-debugging-user-interaction-performance-issues"><a href="http://nordicjs.com/speakers#anna-migas">Fast but not furious: debugging user interaction performance issues</a></h3>

<p>by <a href="https://twitter.com/szynszyliszys">Anna Migas</a></p>

<p>Anna explained a bit about debugging tabs in Google Chrome and Firefox.
All based on her findings while developing some css plugins like <a href="https://github.com/LunarLogic/starability">Starability</a>. She worked specifically on the rendering of animations.</p>

<p>This is a video of her giving the same talk at ScotlandJS.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/FmpNNw1Jjwk" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<h3 id="magic-tricks-with-houdini"><a href="http://nordicjs.com/speakers#sam-richard">Magic Tricks with Houdini</a></h3>

<p>by <a href="https://twitter.com/Snugug">Sam Richard</a></p>

<p>I was lucky to meet Sam at the "Dinner with new friends" (organized by NordicJS). We've been sent to an Indonesian restaurant with delicious food. It was great to have interesting company when you're having a meal abroad!
So Sam is a UI Architect at IBM and gave a talk about Houdini.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">CSS Houdini let us tap into the CSS engine, extending it with JavaScript, not only mimicking. Cool right? <a href="https://twitter.com/Snugug?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@snugug</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nordicjs?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#nordicjs</a></p>&mdash; Jonatan (@karlerikjonatan) <a href="https://twitter.com/karlerikjonatan/status/1037645299353878528?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">6 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<p>He did the same presentation at CSSConf Australia.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/FYWZrLpN5Po" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p>Side note: He's been presenting this subject for a while now. He said that he has to change his slides every time because newer versions of Houdini are so frequently released. So, the above video can possibly be outdated.</p>

<h3 id="can-you-tell-me-if-your-node-app-is-healthy%3F"><a href="http://nordicjs.com/speakers#alejandro-oviedo-garca">Can you tell me if your Node app is healthy?</a></h3>

<p>by <a href="https://twitter.com/a0viedo">Alejandro Oviedo García</a></p>

<p>Alejandro talked about monitoring for your Node app.
Such as CPU consumption or memory usage, number of requests, ...
He even explained the event loop with toy trains which was visually very nice to see!</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">🚂✨ <a href="https://twitter.com/a0viedo?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@a0viedo</a> demonstrates the relationship of event handlers + event loops and why event loop lag is bad with toy trains in his &quot;Can you tell me if your Node app is healthy?&quot; talk at <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nordicjs?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#nordicjs</a> 🚂✨ <a href="https://t.co/MgrTu9iirJ">pic.twitter.com/MgrTu9iirJ</a></p>&mdash; Jessie-BuzzFeed @ NordicJS (@buzzfeedexp) <a href="https://twitter.com/buzzfeedexp/status/1037674309391659008?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">6 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">thank you <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nordicjs?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#nordicjs</a>! check out my demo and list of resources here <a href="https://t.co/2v3PWUhjNC">https://t.co/2v3PWUhjNC</a></p>&mdash; Alejandro Oviedo (@a0viedo) <a href="https://twitter.com/a0viedo/status/1037677069067534336?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">6 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<h3 id="look-mum%2C-no-hands%21"><a href="http://nordicjs.com/speakers#charlie-gerard">Look mum, no hands!</a></h3>

<p>by <a href="https://twitter.com/devdevcharlie">Charlie Gerard</a></p>

<p>This was definitely the winner of most rants in a presentation 🤬.
Although it was very interesting and funny to watch.</p>

<p>She brought a headset and programmed it with a bunch of JS, so that it could "read" your mind.
During her presentation, she decided to give a live demo. Very brave and of course it failed in the beginning, but in the end she was able to demonstrate something.
First she selected keys on a keyboard with her eyes and after that she controlled a drone with her mind.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Here are the slides for my talk about mind control in JavaScript if anyone wants the links to resources I talked about :) <a href="https://t.co/hrHozZRUIv">https://t.co/hrHozZRUIv</a> Feel free to ask any question! 😊 <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nordicjs?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#nordicjs</a></p>&mdash; Charlie Gerard 🏳️‍🌈 (@devdevcharlie) <a href="https://twitter.com/devdevcharlie/status/1037962564297220097?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">7 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/7KhFO-qCVyg" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<h3 id="powerful-automation-with-the-chrome-devtools-protocol"><a href="http://nordicjs.com/speakers#trent-willis">Powerful Automation with the Chrome DevTools Protocol</a></h3>

<p>by <a href="https://twitter.com/trentmwillis">Trent Willis</a></p>

<p>Trent is a Senior UI Engineer at Netflix.
He actually didn't talk about his favorite Netflix show, but talked about his ChitChat app.
During his presentation he was explaining how you can use Puppeteer together with some Chrome DevTools.</p>

<p>Afterwards, he wrote this blogpost about this subject: <a href="https://pretty-okay.com/2018/09/17/static-site-api">How To Turn Your Static Site Into An API With Puppeteer</a></p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Hey <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/NordicJS?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#NordicJS</a>, the slides to my talk and links to the demos/app are up now on <a href="https://twitter.com/benotist?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@benotist</a>! Check it out and share it if you like it 😄 I can&#39;t wait to see what y&#39;all build! <a href="https://t.co/CGQbxk2mn6">https://t.co/CGQbxk2mn6</a></p>&mdash; Trent Willis (@trentmwillis) <a href="https://twitter.com/trentmwillis/status/1037996740941701120?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">7 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">This is why we can&#39;t have nice things. <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nordicjs?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#nordicjs</a>  <a href="https://twitter.com/trentmwillis?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@trentmwillis</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/nordicjs?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@nordicjs</a> <a href="https://t.co/ufGZowIpuP">pic.twitter.com/ufGZowIpuP</a></p>&mdash; 🌍 🌳 🐝 🌊 🏳️‍🌈 (@reimertz) <a href="https://twitter.com/reimertz/status/1037721767383654403?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">6 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<h3 id="accessible-by-law%21-generating-colors-with-js-and-css-custom-properties"><a href="http://nordicjs.com/speakers#ingvild-indreb">Accessible by law! Generating colors with JS and CSS Custom Properties</a></h3>

<p>by <a href="https://twitter.com/IngvildIndrebo">Ingvild Indrebø</a></p>

<p>Ingvild is from Norway and she told us that <a href="https://medium.com/confrere/its-illegal-to-have-an-inaccessible-website-in-norway-and-that-s-good-news-for-all-of-us-b59a9e929d54">it’s illegal to have an inaccessible website in Norway</a>. Yes, by law!
Lot's of big companies have nice websites, but is not accessible for everyone, so you got bad headers in newspapers and you will probably loose some visitors/clients on your website.
Her talk was more about colors and contrast in websites. The company where she's working for, has a calculation about which primary and secondary colours should fit best with each other.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Accessible by Law by <a href="https://twitter.com/IngvildIndrebo?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@IngvildIndrebo</a>  at <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nordicjs?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#nordicjs</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/nordicjs?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@nordicjs</a> as <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/sketchnotes?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#sketchnotes</a> <a href="https://t.co/773ODWBZu4">pic.twitter.com/773ODWBZu4</a></p>&mdash; Norman Wehrle (@normanwehrle) <a href="https://twitter.com/normanwehrle/status/1038017526574272512?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">7 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Interesting talk by <a href="https://twitter.com/IngvildIndrebo?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@ingvildindrebo</a> on accessibility and color contrast - required by Norwegian law! Similar to the contrast check we added when we built <a href="https://t.co/UfWMizyQuq">https://t.co/UfWMizyQuq</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/Danetag?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@Danetag</a> 👀<a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nordicjs?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#nordicjs</a> <a href="https://t.co/YvxlLDGJAt">pic.twitter.com/YvxlLDGJAt</a></p>&mdash; Majsan Auvinen (@majsanauvinen) <a href="https://twitter.com/majsanauvinen/status/1038100592311394305?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">7 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<h3 id="why-we-built-another-framework"><a href="http://nordicjs.com/speakers#tomas-della-vedova">Why we built another framework</a></h3>

<p>by <a href="https://twitter.com/delvedor">Tomas Della Vedova</a></p>

<p>Tomas is an Italian guy that works for <a href="https://twitter.com/elastic">Elastic</a>.</p>

<p>He made <a href="https://www.fastify.io/">Fastify</a>, a web framework for Node.js.
In his talk, he discussed the pros and cons of building this framework.
The focus was speed (what's in a name?), but also what a framework should have that will reduce the speed a bit.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Why we build another franework by <a href="https://twitter.com/delvedor?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@delvedor</a> at <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nordicjs?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#nordicjs</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/nordicjs?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@nordicjs</a> as <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/sketchnotes?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#sketchnotes</a> <a href="https://t.co/eQRr17ugiI">pic.twitter.com/eQRr17ugiI</a></p>&mdash; Norman Wehrle (@normanwehrle) <a href="https://twitter.com/normanwehrle/status/1038018303594319872?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">7 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<h3 id="empathy-driven-development%3A-boosting-performance-by-implementing-for-unfavorable-conditions"><a href="http://nordicjs.com/speakers#isabella-silveira-de-souza">Empathy Driven Development: Boosting performance by implementing for unfavorable conditions</a></h3>

<p>by <a href="https://twitter.com/silveira_bells">Isabella Silveira de Souza</a></p>

<p>Main thought: Develop for every screen.
She gave some tips to render specific parts of your webpage first to have a speedier feeling.
In the beginning of her talk, she referred to her hometown Rio De Janeiro where the population is a bit like the internet: some people have it all, others have to do something with what they have. Rich and poor. 60fps and 120fps.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Good practices on performance boosting:<br>1. Set a performance budget<br>2. Test on real phones and networks<br>3. Start optimizing early, keep it in your radar<a href="https://twitter.com/silveira_bells?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@silveira_bells</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nordicjs?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#nordicjs</a></p>&mdash; Nordic.js (@nordicjs) <a href="https://twitter.com/nordicjs/status/1038058859829579776?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">7 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">So excited for this talk by <a href="https://twitter.com/silveira_bells?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@silveira_bells</a>! Empathy Driven Development <a href="https://t.co/Paak3jilJF">pic.twitter.com/Paak3jilJF</a></p>&mdash; Sam Richard - 🇸🇪 Nordic.js (@Snugug) <a href="https://twitter.com/Snugug/status/1038051579608358914?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">7 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<h3 id="headers-for-hackers"><a href="http://nordicjs.com/speakers#andrew-betts">Headers for Hackers</a></h3>

<p>by <a href="https://twitter.com/triblondon">Andrew Betts</a></p>

<p>Andrew was elected to <a href="https://twitter.com/w3ctag">W3C Technical Architecture Group</a> and gave a talk about HTTP headers.</p>

<p>He gave some numbers about headers that people shouldn't use anymore, but are still represented in a lot of websites.
He also talked about some new interesting headers to check out.</p>

<p>Main thought: We have to focus more on headers, because they can prevent a lot of hacks you don't want.</p>

<p>Andrew gave the same presentation (but a bit longer) at ScaleConf.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TfDb9xdJFlA" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<h3 id="connecting-javascript-to-the-blockchain"><a href="http://nordicjs.com/speakers#meng-shang">Connecting JavaScript to the Blockchain</a></h3>

<p>by Meng Shang</p>

<p>Well euhm... this happened (with React):</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">And Meng Shang just created a blockchain contract, deployed and interacted with it in about three minutes, live, onstage 😲😲😲 <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nordicjs?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#nordicjs</a></p>&mdash; Lucas Medeiros Reis (@iamlucasmreis) <a href="https://twitter.com/iamlucasmreis/status/1038075373895012353?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">7 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">DApps DevTools with Meng Shang <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nordicjs?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#nordicjs</a> <a href="https://t.co/KcrtEvNSiR">pic.twitter.com/KcrtEvNSiR</a></p>&mdash; Mikael Forsgren (@mikaelf) <a href="https://twitter.com/mikaelf/status/1038071573692014592?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">7 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<h2 id="lightning-talks-%E2%9A%A1%EF%B8%8F">Lightning talks ⚡️</h2>

<p>It's a concept where attendees can apply to give a short presentation about something they like or want to share with the audience.
There is a limit of 5min. If they go overtime, the hosts chase the presenter off the stage with candy.</p>

<h3 id="picasso.js">Picasso.js</h3>

<p>by Alexander Kalsson</p>

<p><a href="https://picassojs.com/">Picasso.js</a> is based on <a href="https://d3js.org/">D3.js</a>, but easier to start with.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Hope you enjoyed our great lightning fast 🙌🏽⚡️<a href="https://twitter.com/nordicjs?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@nordicjs</a> Lightning Talk by <a href="https://twitter.com/mindspank?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@mindspank</a>. Alex is around today to answer any questions about <a href="https://twitter.com/picassodotjs?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@picassodotjs</a>, our awesome dev community and so much more! <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nordicjs?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#nordicjs</a> Holla! <a href="https://t.co/CmM2pRdf35">pic.twitter.com/CmM2pRdf35</a></p>&mdash; Qlik Branch (@qlikbranch) <a href="https://twitter.com/qlikbranch/status/1037651512028278785?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">6 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<h3 id="expo">Expo</h3>

<p>by <a href="https://twitter.com/reimertz">Pierre Reimertz</a></p>

<p>A guy that had too many slides and talked too fast. But it was cool, very cool!
He created CatSnap, a kind of Instagram where you can upload pictures, but if there isn't a cat in the picture, the picture is blurred.
React and React Native are perfect tools to create this app, but in the beginning, it requires some study to get started and Pierre wanted to made the app as fast as possible.
So he used <a href="https://expo.io/">Expo</a>. You can compare it a bit with <a href="https://ionicframework.com/">ionic</a>, which is also using HTML, CSS and JS to build your app.</p>

<p>It was funny to see him struggling with the hardware part of his demo.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Omg, lightning talks at <a href="https://twitter.com/nordicjs?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@nordicjs</a> is always a lot of fun! For the few ones who would like to break the app: <a href="https://t.co/2TSWRJZicd">https://t.co/2TSWRJZicd</a> <br><br>I promise to share the codez later this week. <br><br>Also, sorry <a href="https://twitter.com/Apple?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@apple</a> for the rant. You good, but kind of not either. 😢</p>&mdash; 🌍 🌳 🐝 🌊 🏳️‍🌈 (@reimertz) <a href="https://twitter.com/reimertz/status/1038059146585759744?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">7 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="nl"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Possibly the best talk at <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/NordicJS?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#NordicJS</a> so far by <a href="https://twitter.com/reimertz?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@reimertz</a> “cats are great, MacOS is not”</p>&mdash; JesperBylund (@JesperBylund) <a href="https://twitter.com/JesperBylund/status/1038045432541335552?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">7 september 2018</a></blockquote>

<h2 id="this-was-nordic.js-2018-%F0%9F%8E%A5">This was Nordic.js 2018 🎥</h2>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-permalink="https://www.instagram.com/p/Bn8zR_4FeFm/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_medium=loading" data-instgrm-version="12" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:540px; min-width:326px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:16px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/Bn8zR_4FeFm/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_medium=loading" style=" background:#FFFFFF; line-height:0; padding:0 0; text-align:center; text-decoration:none; width:100%;" target="_blank"> <div style=" display: flex; flex-direction: row; align-items: center;"> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 40px; margin-right: 14px; width: 40px;"></div> <div style="display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center;"> <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 100px;"></div> <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 60px;"></div></div></div><div style="padding: 19% 0;"></div><div style="display:block; height:50px; margin:0 auto 12px; width:50px;"><svg width="50px" height="50px" viewBox="0 0 60 60" version="1.1" xmlns="https://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="https://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><g stroke="none" stroke-width="1" fill="none" fill-rule="evenodd"><g transform="translate(-511.000000, -20.000000)" fill="#000000"><g><path d="M556.869,30.41 C554.814,30.41 553.148,32.076 553.148,34.131 C553.148,36.186 554.814,37.852 556.869,37.852 C558.924,37.852 560.59,36.186 560.59,34.131 C560.59,32.076 558.924,30.41 556.869,30.41 M541,60.657 C535.114,60.657 530.342,55.887 530.342,50 C530.342,44.114 535.114,39.342 541,39.342 C546.887,39.342 551.658,44.114 551.658,50 C551.658,55.887 546.887,60.657 541,60.657 M541,33.886 C532.1,33.886 524.886,41.1 524.886,50 C524.886,58.899 532.1,66.113 541,66.113 C549.9,66.113 557.115,58.899 557.115,50 C557.115,41.1 549.9,33.886 541,33.886 M565.378,62.101 C565.244,65.022 564.756,66.606 564.346,67.663 C563.803,69.06 563.154,70.057 562.106,71.106 C561.058,72.155 560.06,72.803 558.662,73.347 C557.607,73.757 556.021,74.244 553.102,74.378 C549.944,74.521 548.997,74.552 541,74.552 C533.003,74.552 532.056,74.521 528.898,74.378 C525.979,74.244 524.393,73.757 523.338,73.347 C521.94,72.803 520.942,72.155 519.894,71.106 C518.846,70.057 518.197,69.06 517.654,67.663 C517.244,66.606 516.755,65.022 516.623,62.101 C516.479,58.943 516.448,57.996 516.448,50 C516.448,42.003 516.479,41.056 516.623,37.899 C516.755,34.978 517.244,33.391 517.654,32.338 C518.197,30.938 518.846,29.942 519.894,28.894 C520.942,27.846 521.94,27.196 523.338,26.654 C524.393,26.244 525.979,25.756 528.898,25.623 C532.057,25.479 533.004,25.448 541,25.448 C548.997,25.448 549.943,25.479 553.102,25.623 C556.021,25.756 557.607,26.244 558.662,26.654 C560.06,27.196 561.058,27.846 562.106,28.894 C563.154,29.942 563.803,30.938 564.346,32.338 C564.756,33.391 565.244,34.978 565.378,37.899 C565.522,41.056 565.552,42.003 565.552,50 C565.552,57.996 565.522,58.943 565.378,62.101 M570.82,37.631 C570.674,34.438 570.167,32.258 569.425,30.349 C568.659,28.377 567.633,26.702 565.965,25.035 C564.297,23.368 562.623,22.342 560.652,21.575 C558.743,20.834 556.562,20.326 553.369,20.18 C550.169,20.033 549.148,20 541,20 C532.853,20 531.831,20.033 528.631,20.18 C525.438,20.326 523.257,20.834 521.349,21.575 C519.376,22.342 517.703,23.368 516.035,25.035 C514.368,26.702 513.342,28.377 512.574,30.349 C511.834,32.258 511.326,34.438 511.181,37.631 C511.035,40.831 511,41.851 511,50 C511,58.147 511.035,59.17 511.181,62.369 C511.326,65.562 511.834,67.743 512.574,69.651 C513.342,71.625 514.368,73.296 516.035,74.965 C517.703,76.634 519.376,77.658 521.349,78.425 C523.257,79.167 525.438,79.673 528.631,79.82 C531.831,79.965 532.853,80.001 541,80.001 C549.148,80.001 550.169,79.965 553.369,79.82 C556.562,79.673 558.743,79.167 560.652,78.425 C562.623,77.658 564.297,76.634 565.965,74.965 C567.633,73.296 568.659,71.625 569.425,69.651 C570.167,67.743 570.674,65.562 570.82,62.369 C570.966,59.17 571,58.147 571,50 C571,41.851 570.966,40.831 570.82,37.631"></path></g></g></g></svg></div><div style="padding-top: 8px;"> <div style=" color:#3897f0; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:550; line-height:18px;"> Dit bericht bekijken op Instagram</div></div><div style="padding: 12.5% 0;"></div> <div style="display: flex; flex-direction: row; margin-bottom: 14px; align-items: center;"><div> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(0px) translateY(7px);"></div> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; height: 12.5px; transform: rotate(-45deg) translateX(3px) translateY(1px); width: 12.5px; flex-grow: 0; margin-right: 14px; margin-left: 2px;"></div> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(9px) translateY(-18px);"></div></div><div style="margin-left: 8px;"> <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 20px; width: 20px;"></div> <div style=" width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 2px solid transparent; border-left: 6px solid #f4f4f4; border-bottom: 2px solid transparent; transform: translateX(16px) translateY(-4px) rotate(30deg)"></div></div><div style="margin-left: auto;"> <div style=" width: 0px; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-right: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(16px);"></div> <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; flex-grow: 0; height: 12px; width: 16px; transform: translateY(-4px);"></div> <div style=" width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-left: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(-4px) translateX(8px);"></div></div></div></a> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/Bn8zR_4FeFm/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_medium=loading" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Thank YOU for attending Nordic.js 2018💕 Hope you had as much fun as we did! All talks will be available on our YouTube channel soon! Stay tuned✨ Video by: Martin Ståhlberg #nordicjs</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">Een bericht gedeeld door <a href="https://www.instagram.com/nordicjs/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_medium=loading" style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px;" target="_blank"> Nordic.js</a> (@nordicjs) op <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2018-09-20T13:43:35+00:00">20 Sep 2018 om 6:43 (PDT)</time></p></div></blockquote>

<p><script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script async defer src="//www.instagram.com/embed.js"></script></p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Error: Internal Rate Limit Reached]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2018/09/11/error-internal-rate-limit-reached"/>
            <updated>2018-09-11T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2018/09/11/error-internal-rate-limit-reached</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while ago we wrote about <a href="/blog/2017/05/02/sliding-window-rate-limiter-redis">building a sliding window rate limiter with redis</a>. We needed this rate limiter for counting the amount of API calls we did to the <a href="https://www.instagram.com/developer/">Instagram API</a>. This has been working great for us. You might have heard of the deprecation of the Instagram API. Facebook introduced a <a href="https://developers.facebook.com/docs/instagram-api">new instagram API</a> as part of the Facebook graph API.</p>

<p>The new Instagram API uses the same <a href="https://developers.facebook.com/docs/graph-api/advanced/rate-limiting">rate limit measures</a> as the Facebook graph API (depends on the active users of your application). Our integration with the new Instagram API uses the same sliding window rate limiter. If our internal rate limit is reached we throw an exception: "Internal rate limit reached". This exception triggers a timeout, the timeout increases when the exception is thrown again.</p>

<p>When we deployed our integration we noticed that when an access token reached the internal rate limit, the tasks refused to do any calls to the Instagram API, even when it was allowed again, because our rate limiter was still holding them back. This resulted in data delays, not good!</p>

<p>If a combustion engine gets excessive fuel in the combustion chamber, the engine becomes flooded. You'll need to release the throttle to stop the flooding. This is exactly what's happening in our rate limiter.</p>

<p>Each time we do an API call, the following commands are sent to Redis (<a href="/blog/2017/05/02/sliding-window-rate-limiter-redis">We explained this in our previous blogpost</a>):</p>

<pre><code>&gt; MULTI
&gt; ZREMRANGEBYSCORE $accessToken 0 ($now - $slidingWindow)
&gt; ZRANGE $accessToken 0 -1
&gt; ZADD $accessToken $now $now
&gt; EXPIRE $accessToken $slidingWindow
&gt; EXEC
</code></pre>

<p>Do you see why the rate limiter gets "flooded"?</p>

<p>If you are thinking about the <code>ZADD</code> command, you're right!</p>

<p>Even when we're not allowed to do an API call we still add a timestamp. We knew this and we agreed that this was okay for our use case. However, we're using a lower rate limit (compared to the old Instagram API), which resulted in a lot of internal rate limit reached exceptions for busy Instagram accounts.</p>

<p>How can we solve this? It's important that we execute <code>ZRANGE</code> and <code>ZADD</code> in the same transaction. We want to avoid race conditions because the tasks that do these API calls are distributed. How can we check the result of <code>ZRANGE</code> before doing the <code>ZADD</code> command in the same transaction? <a href="https://github.com/itamarhaber">Itamar Haber</a> from <a href="https://redislabs.com/">Redis Labs</a> wrote a comment on our <a href="/blog/2017/05/02/sliding-window-rate-limiter-redis">previous blogpost</a> suggesting to <a href="https://gist.github.com/itamarhaber/254bac4283d1675c5a5569639b0322aa">use a Lua script</a> (Thanks, Itamar!). Using a Lua script we can execute Redis commands conditionally in an atomic way.</p>

<p>This is what we came up with:</p>

<pre><code class="lua">local token = KEYS[1]
local now = tonumber(ARGV[1])
local window = tonumber(ARGV[2])
local limit = tonumber(ARGV[3])

local clearBefore = now - window
redis.call('ZREMRANGEBYSCORE', token, 0, clearBefore)

local amount = redis.call('ZCARD', token)
if amount &lt; limit then
    redis.call('ZADD', token, now, now)
end
redis.call('EXPIRE', token, window)

return limit - amount
</code></pre>

<p>Let's break it down (Yeah, yeah 🎶):</p>

<ol>
<li>Assign the script arguments to variables.</li>
<li>Call <code>ZREMRANGEBYSCORE</code> to cleanup timestamps before the window.</li>
<li>Instead of <code>ZRANGE</code> we'll use <code>ZCARD</code> to know how many calls we already did.</li>
<li>Call <code>ZADD</code> when we've not reached the limit yet.</li>
<li>Call <code>EXPIRE</code> to make sure the sorted set, that holds the timestamps, gets cleaned up after the window has passed.</li>
</ol>

<p>In PHP we can evaluate the script using <a href="https://github.com/phpredis/phpredis">https://github.com/phpredis/phpredis</a>:</p>

<pre><code class="php">$this-&gt;redis-&gt;eval($script, [$key, $now, $window, $limit], 1);
</code></pre>

<p>This works great. Our tasks are now doing as much API calls as possible without flooding the rate limiter. 👏😎</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Skill Based Routing: Secure an Internship with us]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2018/07/03/internship-skill-based-routing"/>
            <updated>2018-07-03T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2018/07/03/internship-skill-based-routing</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-do-we-do%3F">What do we do?</h2>

<p>The Clarabridge CX Social team builds a customer care tool for social media. Our clients use our software to be able to respond to the incoming questions and complaints on their Facebook pages, Twitter accounts, Instagram profiles, a.o. These clients often have a high volume of incoming messages, on several social profiles. We try to make those people’s lives easier by offering automation tools, smart routing of messages and reply suggestions, among others.
<a href="https://developers.engagor.com/team">Read more about what we do here</a>.</p>

<p>As of September 2018, we have room for one or more enthusiastic interns to join us for (at least) a couple of weeks <em>(preferably 4 days a week, any time between September 2018 to June 2019)</em>, to work as part of the CX Social development team.</p>

<h2 id="the-project%3A-skill-based-routing%21">The Project: Skill based routing!</h2>

<p>We’re looking for someone to help us solve this problem for our clients; When a new question or complaints comes in, a customer care agent will handle that complaint; but which agent? Clarabridge CX Social offers several ways and algorithms that can help decide which questions go to which agent at a certain time, but there is still room for improvement … Ideally we want to assign the question to the agent that will be able to handle &amp; answer the question adequately in the shortest amount of time. Several factors are at play here: properties of the question, metadata about the question, metadata from who’s asking, which agents are available, skills of those agents, which mailboxes they work in, etc. We want you to look for ways how we can optimize our current algorithms and help us to implement them.</p>

<p>Here's a real-world example: a question in French about billing comes in 5 minutes before the end of the Paris team shift. Who will handle this question?</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2018-07-02-internship-skill-based-routing/routing.png" alt="Skill Based Routing" /><br />
<small>The role of skill based routing</small>
</center></p>

<p>We will provide labeled data and statistics about agent performance. It’s up to you to figure out the best approach, with our help of course.</p>

<h2 id="the-internship">The Internship</h2>

<p>As an intern you are an integral part of the R&amp;D team working on different parts of the application using technologies like PHP, React, MySQL, Redis, memcached, ElasticSearch, RabbitMQ, a.o. The other team members include a designer, front-end developer, data scientist, and several system engineers &amp; full-stack web developers.
We are looking for a student with interest and knowledge of both front-end as back-end technologies.</p>

<p>Want to hear from a previous intern what it’s like to join our team? Read about <a href="https://engagor.github.io/blog/2017/06/01/internship-gheerwijn-cx-social-developer/">Gheerwijn’s experiences</a>.</p>

<h2 id="interested%3F">Interested?</h2>

<p>We are looking for someone to join us in the Gent, Belgium office of Clarabridge, located at Grauwpoort 1, 9000 Gent.</p>

<p>Does this seem like a fun challenge for you? Please reach out to <a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#105;l&#x74;&#x6f;&#58;&#106;&#x75;&#x72;&#114;&#105;a&#x61;&#110;&#46;p&#x65;&#x72;&#115;&#121;&#x6e;&#x40;&#99;&#108;a&#x72;&#x61;&#98;&#114;&#x69;&#x64;&#103;&#101;&#x2e;&#x63;&#111;&#109;">jurriaan.persyn@clarabridge.com</a> with your details, and the requirements for your internship, and we’ll be in touch!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lambda To The Rescue: Recursion]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2018/06/27/lambda-recursion"/>
            <updated>2018-06-27T14:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2018/06/27/lambda-recursion</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>This is the third post in a series about using Functional Programming concepts to make your Object Oriented code more comprehensible. Start <a href="/blog/2018/03/02/lambda-lists-to-wrap-failure">here</a> if you want to read the whole thing.</strong></p>

<h3 id="procedural-and-declarative-styles">Procedural and Declarative styles</h3>

<p>Most programming languages have language structures to loop through lists and do interesting stuff with those lists. When you're used to programming using one of those languages, it can be pretty terrifying to have your basics taken away from you when you jump into a functional programming language like Scheme or Haskell. Let's see what the problem is that functional languages have with loops and how they solved it.</p>

<p>Let's look at a pretty standard loop in PHP that counts how many words are in a list:</p>

<pre><code class="php">function countWordsInList(array $listOfWords)
{
    $count = 0;

    foreach ($listOfWords as $word) {
        $count++;
    }

    return $count;
}
</code></pre>

<p>Of course, this is an overly simple example (and you should probably use <code>count()</code>), but you get the point. Now, things get difficult, because there are no loops like this <code>foreach</code> in a lot of functional programming languages. Why, you ask? Because most of them either don't allow you to reassign variables (which makes the loop pretty useless), and, in fact, some of them disallow side-effects altogether. Let's see how we do this in Haskell instead:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">countWordsInList :: [String] -&gt; Int
countWordsInList [] = 0
countWordsInList (x:xs) = 1 + countWordsInList xs
</code></pre>

<p>OK, stop. 🤔 What the hack is happening here?</p>

<ul>
<li>On the first line, we have the type definition of our function: It takes a list of strings <code>[String]</code> and it returns an <code>Int</code>. It's a good practice to write it (it helps you think), but Haskell's compiler can infer it most of the time.</li>
<li>Then we define a "base" case: <code>countWordsInList</code> returns <code>0</code> for an empty list <code>[]</code>.</li>
<li>Then we say that for a list with at least one word <code>x</code> and possibly other words <code>xs</code>, we'll return <code>1</code> and add the result of the recursive call to the same function, with the rest of the list of words (the whole list without the first word).</li>
</ul>

<p>As you can see, in the PHP example we told the machine what to do with the list to get to a result. In the Haskell example, we declared what the result was, and some variables just had to be filled in. You could say that no computation needed to happen, just substitution.</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">countWordsInList ["foo", "bar", "baz"] = 1 + countWordsInList ["bar", "baz"]
countWordsInList ["foo", "bar", "baz"] = 1 + 1 + countWordsInList ["baz"]
countWordsInList ["foo", "bar", "baz"] = 1 + 1 + 1 + countWordsInList []
countWordsInList ["foo", "bar", "baz"] = 1 + 1 + 1 + 0
countWordsInList ["foo", "bar", "baz"] = 3
</code></pre>

<h3 id="recognizing-a-pattern">Recognizing a Pattern</h3>

<p>Let's try and write a function to sum all numbers in a list of integers:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">sum' :: [Int] -&gt; Int
sum' [] = 0
sum' (x:xs) = x + sum' xs
</code></pre>

<p>OK, so:</p>

<ul>
<li>We'll call our function <code>sum'</code> because <code>sum</code> already exists.</li>
<li>We want <code>sum'</code> to take a list of integers <code>[Int]</code> and we'll return the sum of all those as an <code>Int</code>.</li>
<li>We'll start with the simplest case: an empty list will have the sum <code>0</code>.</li>
<li>In all other cases, we'll take the first <code>Int</code> in the list, and add it to the sum of all other items in the list.</li>
</ul>

<p>💡 Does that make you think of something?</p>

<p>You're right, this looks <strong>a lot</strong> like the previous example <code>countWordsInList</code>. And that's what other functional programmers thought when they were doing stuff like this. What if we could make an abstraction over this?</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">xxxxx [] = __value__
-- either return something for an empty list

xxxxx (x:xs) = __function__ x (xxxxx xs)
-- or take the first item of the list and combine
-- it with the recursive call with the rest of the list
</code></pre>

<p>Let's try. With the above blueprint, we can see that we need to create a function that</p>

<ol>
<li>takes a <code>__function__</code> that combines a value with the next</li>
<li>takes a <code>__value__</code> that is the default for empty lists</li>
<li>abstracts away the recursive call and returns the endresult;</li>
</ol>

<p>Let's define its type:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">fold' :: (a -&gt; b -&gt; a) -&gt; a -&gt; [b] -&gt; a
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>we'll call our function <code>fold'</code></li>
<li><code>(a -&gt; b -&gt; a)</code> first parameter is a function that takes a value of type <code>a</code> and type <code>b</code> and returns a value of type <code>a</code></li>
<li><code>-&gt; a</code> second parameter is the default value of type <code>a</code></li>
<li><code>-&gt; [b]</code> third parameter is a list of values to loop over, they all have type <code>b</code></li>
<li><code>-&gt; a</code> the return value will be of type <code>a</code></li>
</ul>

<p>Now we can start writing. We know that if the list we got is empty, we can just return the default value:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">fold' _ def [] = def
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>_</code> means "we don't care about that value". It doesn't matter what the function is; if the list is empty, we don't need it. What if the list is not empty, but contains one or more elements? Let's use the combining <code>func</code> to combine the first item of the list with the result of the recursive call to the <code>fold'</code> function with exactly the same parameters (except for the "list", we just pass everything but the first element that we already used):</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">fold' func def (x:xs) = func x (fold' func def xs)
</code></pre>

<p>We apply the <code>func</code> to the first element and the result of the recursive call to our <code>fold'</code> function with all the same parameters, except for the list. There we just pass on the rest of the list (so without the first element that we already used).</p>

<p>Combined, that is:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">fold' :: (b -&gt; a -&gt; a) -&gt; a -&gt; [b] -&gt; a
fold' _ def [] = def
fold' func def (x:xs) = func x (fold' func def xs)
</code></pre>

<p>Let's see if it works! Remember <code>countWordsInList</code>?</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">countWordsInList :: [String] -&gt; Int
countWordsInList [] = 0
countWordsInList (x:xs) = 1 + countWordsInList xs
</code></pre>

<p>We'll rewrite it using the <code>fold'</code> function:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">countWordsInList :: [String] -&gt; Int
countWordsInList list = fold' (\word count -&gt; count + 1) 0 list
</code></pre>

<p>We'll fold over the <code>list</code> with a function that takes the next <code>word</code> and the current <code>count</code>, and returns <code>count + 1</code>. The stuff that's written between parens is a lambda (anonymous function) and looks like this <code>(\params -&gt; body)</code>. The default value for our <code>fold'</code> is <code>0</code>. When we use it, it gives expected results:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">countWordsInList ["foo", "bar", "baz", "qux"]
-- 4

countWordsInList []
-- 0

countWordsInList ["foo"]
-- 1
</code></pre>

<p>How about the <code>sum</code> function that we made earlier?</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">sum' :: [Int] -&gt; Int
sum' = fold' (+) 0
</code></pre>

<p>Let's try it out:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">sum' [1, 2, 3, 4]
-- 10

sum' []
-- 0

sum' [5]
-- 5
</code></pre>

<p>That seems to work... But wait... We wrote the definition <code>sum' = fold' (+) 0</code> without a list? Isn't this function definition incomplete? Yes. In Haskell, like in math, you can omit things that happen on both sides of the equals sign. Compare it to <code>3 + 4 = 1 + 2 + 4</code>. You could just as well write <code>3 = 1 + 2</code>. It's the same thing in Haskell. <code>sum' list = fold' (+) 0 list</code> is the same as <code>sum' = fold' (+) 0</code>.</p>

<p>As an exercise, let's do one more. We'll try to write a function that finds the maximum value of a list of positive integers, and returns <code>0</code> otherwise:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">maximum' :: [Int] -&gt; Int
maximum' = fold' (\next current -&gt; if next &gt; current then next else current) 0
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="haskell">maximum' []
-- 0

maximum' [1, 2, 3, 5, 3, 2, 10, 0, 1]
-- 10

maximum' [42]
-- 42
</code></pre>

<p>If you want to use folds in Haskell, you certainly shouldn't write them yourself 😅 - they already exist. Check out <a href="https://wiki.haskell.org/Foldr_Foldl_Foldl'">the documentation</a> for <code>foldl</code>, <code>foldr</code> and <code>foldl'</code>.</p>

<h3 id="transforming-a-list-to-another-list">Transforming a list to another list</h3>

<p>Let's say we have a list of Users, and we wanted to only have a list of their ages. The above methods could help us do that, but it would be quite tedious. Let's try writing a function for it ourselves.</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">data User = User { name :: String
                 , age :: Int
                 } deriving (Show)

ages :: [User] -&gt; [Int]
ages [] = []
ages (u:us) = age u : ages us
</code></pre>

<p>Again, we make sure we got the base case of an "empty list of users" covered: we'll just return an empty list of ages. Then we really need to start thinking. We'll just get what we need for the first value of the input list, and prepend that to the result of the recursive call with the rest of the list (just like what we did with the folds). Let's see what that gives us:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">ages []
-- []

ages [ User {name="toon", age=29}, User {name="jenne", age=30} ]
-- [29,30]

ages [ User {name="toon", age=29} ]
-- [29]
</code></pre>

<p>It seems to work!</p>

<p>What if we had a list of ages, and we wanted to know how many years these people still had left to live. Let's oversimplify again, and subtract their age from <code>100</code>.</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">yearsLeft :: [Int] -&gt; [Int]
yearsLeft [] = []
yearsLeft (x:xs) = 100 - x : yearsLeft xs
</code></pre>

<p>Again, we take the first element of the list, do something with it, and recurse on the rest of the list. That looks a lot like the "age" example, doesn't it?</p>

<p>Well... there's an abstraction that can be made again. The "generic" function for doing things like this should look like so:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">xxxxx [] = []
-- an empty input list results in an empty output list

xxxxx (x:xs) = __function__ x : (xxxxx xs)
-- take the first item of the list and do something with it
-- recurse on the rest of the list and append results.
</code></pre>

<p>Let's define its type:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">map' :: (a -&gt; b) -&gt; [a] -&gt; [b]
</code></pre>

<p>Let's name our function <code>map'</code>, it takes a function from type <code>a</code> to type <code>b</code> and a list with <code>a</code>s. It then returns a list of <code>b</code>s. In the base case, it should return an empty list:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">map' _ [] = []
</code></pre>

<p>In other cases, it should take the first item of the list, apply the function to it, and append the result of the recursive call:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">map' func (x:xs) = func x : map' func xs
</code></pre>

<p>So, we get this:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">map' :: (a -&gt; b) -&gt; [a] -&gt; [b]
map' _ [] = []
map' func (x:xs) = func x : map' func xs
</code></pre>

<p>Let's try it out: we want to write a function that takes a list of <code>Int</code>s and returns the same list but with <code>1</code> added to each element.</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">plusOne :: [Int] -&gt; [Int]
plusOne = map' (+ 1)
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="haskell">plusOne []
-- []

plusOne [1, 2, 3]
-- [2,3,4]

plusOne [3]
-- [4]
</code></pre>

<p>Cool! So now we have generalizations over some of these recursive functions! There are others to be found. I'll leave that to the reader to find out about.</p>

<h3 id="back-to-oop">Back to OOP</h3>

<p>You can probably see that these abstractions have their value. E.g.: <code>map</code> lets you use a function that applies to one thing on a whole list of those things. Even better, it lets you do it in a totally declarative style. You don't need to worry about state or changing variables. You don't need to keep counter values. Nothing. It's totally transparent. For me, this results in a huge reduction of mental overhead. I know, I talk a lot about that, but it's important to me. The same thing is true for the <code>fold</code>s. It's another way of thinking about loops that works really well for me.</p>

<p>When we get back to e.g. PHP now, I see many cases where a <code>map</code> or <code>fold</code> would be great. Implementing them ourselves isn't necessary (luckily), because they already exist in practically every programming language.</p>

<p>One more thing. The above implementations -which actually work really great in functional programming languages- wouldn't work in languages like PHP. The reason is simple: we would get stack overflows pretty quickly; In functional programming languages, there are things called tail call optimizations that can be made. They make sure that you don't blow the stack, even if you recurse a thousand times. This is not really possible in PHP functions right now. Try it out! But after it, just use <code>array_map()</code> and <code>array_reduce()</code> if you want to do stuff like this 😉!</p>

<p>Happy programming y'aλλ! 🖖</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lambda To The Rescue: Pure Functions]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2018/06/04/lambda-pure-functions"/>
            <updated>2018-06-04T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2018/06/04/lambda-pure-functions</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>This is the second post in a series about using Functional Programming concepts to make your Object Oriented code more comprehensible. Start <a href="/blog/2018/03/02/lambda-lists-to-wrap-failure">here</a> if you want to read the whole thing.</strong></p>

<p>Whenever you read up on functional programming on the internet, it's common to come across words like "pure" and "transparent", and for good reason. Let's explore their meaning in the functional programming world. 🕵️‍♂️</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%92%8E-purity">💎 Purity</h2>

<p>Let's pretend we need to represent the number of cylinders in an engine <code>2</code> in our code. In a normal scenario, we would assign it to a variable and be done with it. We'll use <a href="https://www.haskell.org/">Haskell</a>, a pure functional language.</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">cylinders :: Int
cylinders = 2
</code></pre>

<p>In the example, we start with a type annotation. You can read the first line as "cylinders <strong>is an</strong> Int". Then we write our statement.</p>

<p>Now, whenever we need the number of cylinders for computation, we could just get it from the variable right? Sure! Let's try something else, since we're talking about "pure" functions. Let's try to use a function that doesn't take any input and always returns the number of cylinders, instead of a variable:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">cylinders :: Int
cylinders = 2
</code></pre>

<p>Wait? WAT? That is exactly the same?</p>

<p>Yes, in Haskell, a function without parameters is the same as a value. And that's logical right? No computation needs to happen when there's no input... right?</p>

<p>Well... Let me disappoint you:</p>

<pre><code class="php">function cylinders()
{
    echo rand();

    return 2;
}
</code></pre>

<p>In PHP, and in practically any other language, you can do things in functions that have side effects. In this case</p>

<ul>
<li>we created output on the <code>stdout</code></li>
<li>we called <code>rand()</code> which in turn tried to create a random number by reading from a randomness source</li>
</ul>

<p>Of course this can result in A LOT of unexpected behaviour. By just looking at the function, you can't always immediately see what's going to happen. And this is what the word <code>pure</code> refers to. This function has "side effects", so it's not "pure".</p>

<p>In Haskell though, if you want to do side effects within a function it will be marked with an <code>IO</code> tag. In fact, this is a type that behaves a bit like an environment. Getting a random number and echo'ing it requires <code>IO</code>, so the type can't just be <code>Int</code>, it's <code>IO Int</code>.</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">cylinders :: IO Int
</code></pre>

<p>This way, you can always clearly see, just by looking at the types, that the function has side effects, and thus is not "pure".</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%91%93-transparency">👓 Transparency</h2>

<p>While these terms are used interchangibly, in my book the word "transparency" makes this very clear: you can "look straight through" a function.</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">double :: (Num a) =&gt; a -&gt; a
double x = 2 * x
</code></pre>

<p>For every numeric value, we can calculate its <code>double</code>. You could really write this as a complete mapping from every number to its double:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">double :: (Num a) =&gt; a -&gt; a
double 0 = 0
double 1 = 2
double 2 = 4
double 3 = 6
double 4 = 8
-- ... etcetera
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, we reduced the function to (essentially) "values" again, as in the first example of this post. Calls to transparent functions could in theory be replaced by their values. In functional programming jargon this is called "referential transparancy".</p>

<p>A lot of functions can be made in an entirely transparent way, even quite complex things like parsing structured text or doing extensive computation.</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%A4%A9-consequences">🤩 Consequences</h2>

<h4 id="reduced-mental-overhead">Reduced mental overhead</h4>

<p>As you can imagine, being able to reason about functions as "values" makes things <em>much</em> easier. Otherwise you have to deal with side effects that can change the world while you just expected an Integer representing the number of cylinders in a motorcycle. The same goes for the other case, where an <code>IO Int</code> lets you know instantly that there will be stuff happening behind the curtains, and you're not getting your <code>Int</code> for free.</p>

<h4 id="in-fp-as-well-as-oop-environments">In FP as well as OOP environments</h4>

<p>Even in OOP environments I always try to see which parts of the code that I'm writing can be written as pure functions, so that they can be extracted to functions that represent values. E.g. processing incoming social media posts to a unified format of a post that our system understands is essentially a "transparent" operation. It's just a transformation of data to a certain format. The fact that this function is pure makes it very easy to reason about: we can essentially just think about the post in it's basic form (inline the function as value).</p>

<p>Now that I'm thinking about it: it would be GREAT if static analysis could detect side effects in functions... What do you think? 🤯</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Async Publishing: Making Clients Feel Like They Don’t Have To Wait]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2018/04/20/async-publishing"/>
            <updated>2018-04-20T10:30:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2018/04/20/async-publishing</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few months ago, we were asked whether it was possible to publish posts to hundreds of Facebook Pages at the same time. This use case is not something we had foreseen, the client just has <em>A LOT</em> of owned profiles; one social profile per physical location that they're in. They wanted to be able to share promotions to those locations (i.e. happy-hour promotions for participating bars).
Of course we can make that happen. It's an important part of our product. Ammm, right?</p>

<h2 id="shaking-the-walls">Shaking the walls</h2>

<p>How can we facilitate this use case, and at the same time make sure this feature is used for genuine, valuable communication?</p>

<p>Posting the exact same message a thousand times will likely trigger spam detection algorithms of certain social networks we support. And e.g. Twitter specifically changed their rules about posting, reposting and retweeting the exact messages on multiple profiles (read <a href="https://blog.twitter.com/developer/en_us/topics/tips/2018/automation-and-the-use-of-multiple-accounts.html">the blogpost</a>). Because Twitter allows you to reach out to others by @mentioning them, this behavior is certainly not desirable on their platform, and we don't allow to post the same content to several profiles at once.
For Facebook however, the re-posting is limited to owned, authorized place pages, so the use case is genuine.</p>

<h2 id="what-we-had-...">What we had ...</h2>

<p>The first thing we were worried about was: "What breaks if we would do this with our current implementation?" After a quick experiment, the answer seemed to be <em>nothing</em>; we just needed patience, a lot of patience. And as a user, the only UI feedback you got while a post got published to your 100 pages was a loading icon, for several minutes.</p>

<p>In fact, we're just looping the list of profiles.
And in that loop, we're doing API calls for each profile.</p>

<p>For 99% of our users, this was good enough and it works like a charm. But with this new use case, our UX had to improve.</p>

<h2 id="life-is-more-than-a-loading-icon">Life is more than a loading icon</h2>

<p>Asking our hamster to run a little faster was not possible. We had to think about another solution in the backend.</p>

<p>We came up with an <code>In progress</code> section in our tool. When a user wants to publish to more than 10 profiles, the post goes into this section.
What changed in the backend? We still loop all the profiles, but we create tasks for each profile and put them on a queue.
That queue will be processed asynchronously, in the background.</p>

<p>Our users can do other tasks in our tool while the post is publishing to all those profiles, and users can follow along in the section <code>In progress</code>.</p>

<p>What I really like about that new section, is that you see the publishing status of every profile.
You have 3 statuses:
- In progress
- Successful
- Failed</p>

<p><code>In progress</code> and <code>Successful</code> are quite obvious. If publishing on a single profile failed, we see the reason why it failed and there's an option to retry posting on that profile.
The <code>Retry</code> button is also a timesaver because you don't have to create the same post with only the failed profiles.</p>

<p>Every time we get a result from the API call, we update the status of the current profile. The user interface is updated in real time so from a user's standpoint, the progress is clearly visible.</p>

<p>The user knows the status of every single profile. This makes the user feel in control of all of the profile actions.
Before we did this change, the user only saw a loading icon. Now, they receive an estimation for when the publishing will be completed.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2018-04-20-async-publishing/async-posting.png" alt="In progress section in publisher" /></p>

<p>The impact that this small improvement has, really makes a big difference. It feels snappy, you can just go on with your work while your 100+ profiles are updated, you don't feel held back by the user interface.</p>

<p>Have you done something like this? Feel free to comment below!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tips For Distraction-Free Programming]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2018/04/09/some-tips-for-distraction-free-programming"/>
            <updated>2018-04-09T17:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2018/04/09/some-tips-for-distraction-free-programming</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm very easily distracted. The slightest movement or conversation in the room takes my focus right away, not to mention the endless stream of information and notifications that e.g. services like Slack (team chat) and e-mail generate. I might be working on something with a colleague or on my own, when a simple notification pops in. My brain glitches for a moment while I process the notification and get back to where I was, but it's enough to completely lose focus. When pair programming with someone that isn't easily distracted, it's mostly fixed in an instant by getting back to the conversation or repeating the last question, but it's a lot more difficult when working on a feature alone. Over time I tried to change a few things to make this kind of interruptions less frequent or pervasive. Let's check some out:</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%8F%9D-environment">🏝 Environment</h2>

<p>The room I'm working in has a huge impact on my concentration levels. People talking or walking around are direct hits, as is any movement in my surroundings, even behind me. This is mostly fixed in our case since we don't have an open floor plan, so we don't share rooms with other teams, and when it's noisy in the room next to ours, we can just close the door. To prevent people talking from disrupting my concentration and the other way around, I'll put on headphones when working alone (mostly to prevent myself from listening in on the conversation), and I'll move to another room when pair programming. I know it sounds antisocial and makes me less approachable for questions or consultation, but I try to only do this when there's noise.</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%93%B1-phone-%26-social-media">📱 Phone &amp; Social Media</h2>

<p>My phone is out of sight. When I get a message I will read it when I find the time. When someone calls me I mostly take the call. It might sound strange because we're a social media company, but I'm not logged in to any of my personal social media accounts during the day. This really helps me concentrate, because my Twitter timeline is a real timesink for me. If I'm looking at that, I'm certainly not concentrating 😏. For testing stuff, I'll aways use test accounts.</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%96%A5-full-screen-applications">🖥 Full Screen Applications</h2>

<p>Although I don't like Full Screen Applications, I started using them more and more. They hide anything that might be happening in other windows, covering unwanted distractions up until you switch to the other application. I still don't like the oversight that is taken away by using an app in Full Screen mode though. The cool thing for me specifically is that iTerm behaves a bit like a tiling window manager for me, since I do most of my development in Vim &amp; the terminal, using iTerm splits. A great tip there is that you can use <code>Cmd + Shift + Enter</code> in an iTerm split to make it appear Full Screen temporarily.</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%9B%8E-osx-notification-center">🛎 OSX Notification center</h2>

<p><img src="/images/2018-04-09-some-tips-for-distraction-free-programming/1.png" alt="do not disturb" /></p>

<p>I already hinted at it earlier on, but notifications of any kind really disturb me. They pop over any fullscreen application that might be open, and I really can't help looking at them. This is why I set the <code>DO NOT DISTURB</code> mode on during workdays. You can configure Mac OSX to enable it by default during work hours, or you can do it manually when you notice being distracted. Notifications I get are mostly from Slack, Calendar and Mail. You can also configure this on a per-application basis in your System Preferences.</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%8E%88-osx-application-badges">🎈 OSX Application Badges</h2>

<p><img src="/images/2018-04-09-some-tips-for-distraction-free-programming/2.png" alt="dock icons with badges" /></p>

<p>What's really annoying me is that Mac OS displays so-called "badges" -the red circle icons with a number in them- on applications that received notifications, and these badges are visible in the Dock and the Application Switcher (<code>Cmd + Tab</code>). When I'm switching to my browser, I don't want to see how many Slack messages I missed. I'll check those later. I just went to Notification Center in System Preferences and disabled these badges for Slack, Calendar and Mail. I believe that I can be more productive when I read these things periodically instead of during other tasks. In the screenshot above, I enabled them temporarily for Calendar to show you what I mean, but what you can't see is that I have 25+ unread messages in Slack. Don't worry, I'll read them after I get this blogpost out! 😉</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%93%A2-slack">📢 Slack</h2>

<p>Some great things to do in Slack are to Leave channels you don't use, and to use the Mute 🔇 functionality on channels that are not urgent but you can't really leave. Of course, I disabled Slack's notification sounds by default.</p>

<p>I hope these tips were helpful, they certainly help me concentrate a bit better. If you think of anything else, comment below, I want to hear it! Happy pair programming!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lambda To The Rescue: Lists to wrap failure]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2018/03/02/lambda-lists-to-wrap-failure"/>
            <updated>2018-03-02T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2018/03/02/lambda-lists-to-wrap-failure</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>This is the first post in a series about using Functional Programming concepts to make your Object Oriented code more comprehensible. Hang tight for more.</strong></p>

<h2 id="readability">Readability</h2>

<p>When we're reading code, one of the most important blocking factors is cognitive overhead. Minimize it, and your code instantly becomes easier to read and understand. Or is it the other way 'round? After some years of playing with functional programming languages in my spare time, I saw some things that functional programming does great in this field. One of them involves lists.</p>

<p>As you might know, lists are among the most important datastructures in functional programming, if not the most important. There's even a whole family of programming languages that took their name from them. Looking at you <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisp_(programming_language)">Lisp</a> 😘!</p>

<p>Let's dive in with a typical legacy PHP method discovered in the wild:</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

function words($string)
{
    if (empty($string)) {
        return false;
    }

    return explode(' ', $string);
}

var_dump(words('')); // returns false
var_dump(words('foo bar baz')); // returns ['foo', 'bar', 'baz'];
</code></pre>

<p>The reason the <code>empty</code> check is there, apparently, is that <code>explode(' ', $s)</code> with an empty string will return <code>['']</code> a list with an empty string in it, which is really strange and non-desirable. Arguably, if the <code>$string</code> variable can't be empty, we should throw an exception. But let's say we want to explore our options here. Before I look into the body of a function, I always try to understand it as a black blox.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If I pass <code>words</code> a string, it returns an <code>array</code> of words in the string. Except that for empty strings, it will return <code>false</code>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Now, the "black box" already has some mystery to it. Why does it return <code>false</code>? Let's defer the answer to it, and check out if we can write the PHP7 type annotations for it.</p>

<pre><code class="php">function words(string $string): array
{
    // ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now, this is not correct. The exception that is made for empty strings can't be written as a type. In old-skool PHP they would've written a DocBlock like this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">/**
 * @param string $string
 * @return array|false depending on failure
 */
function words($string)
{
    // ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>But that is a type signature that is unrepresentable usinig PHP7 types. What if we would represent failure using an empty array?</p>

<pre><code class="php">function words(string $string): array
{
    if (empty($string)) {
        return array();
    }

    return explode(' ', $string);
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now the type signature just works. We turned "failure" into a valid result that we can work with. For instance, all code that works with the return value of this method can now just work with arrays. The type signature now tells a story about the function too:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If I pass <code>words</code> a string, it returns an <code>array</code> of words in the string.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The base case where the string is empty is now logical: an empty string has no words, so a list of 0 words is returned.</p>

<h2 id="chaining-calls">Chaining calls</h2>

<p>Now, let's say we have a function <code>chars</code> that returns a list of chars in a string:</p>

<pre><code class="php">function chars(string $string): array
{
    if (empty($string)) {
        return array();
    }

    return str_split($string);
}
</code></pre>

<p>We're thinking we should be able to use this to list all the characters that appear within words. Would this work?</p>

<pre><code class="php">chars(words('foo bar baz'));
</code></pre>

<p>No... We get a fatal error <code>Fatal error: Uncaught TypeError: Argument 1 passed to chars() must be of the type string, array given</code>. Of course, the result of <code>words</code> is an array, which cannot be used as input to our <code>chars</code> function. Let's use <code>array_map</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="php">array_map(@chars, words('foo bar baz'));
</code></pre>

<p><em>don't worry about the <code>@</code>, it's a trick that I learned while working on <a href="https://github.com/mathiasverraes/lambdalicious/">lambdalicious</a>. <code>@</code> is PHP's error suppressing operator. In this case it allows us to write a function's name as a string, without using string notation, so that it's visually different from a string, BUT is interpreted by PHP as a string...</em></p>

<p>We get this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">[["f","o","o"],["b","a","r"],["b","a","z"]]
</code></pre>

<p>Of course, after mapping <code>chars</code> over the words, this is what we get... But actually, we wanted this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">["f","o","o","b","a","r","b","a","z"]
</code></pre>

<p>So how do we get there? We "flatten" the arrays by using <code>concat</code>, which does not exist in php. Let's write it ourselves:</p>

<pre><code class="php">function array_concat(array $arrays): array
{
    return call_user_func_array(
        @array_merge,
        array_merge(array(array()), $arrays)
    );
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now we can use it to flatten the array:</p>

<pre><code class="php">array_concat(array_map(@chars, words('foo bar baz')));
</code></pre>

<p>TADAAAA 😆 We get what we wanted!</p>

<pre><code class="php">["f","o","o","b","a","r","b","a","z"]
</code></pre>

<p>Let's call this combination of <code>array_map</code> and <code>array_concat</code> <code>array_bind</code> for now:</p>

<pre><code class="php">function array_bind(array $array, $f)
{
    return array_concat(array_map($f, $array));
}
</code></pre>

<p><code>array_bind</code> takes an array of values, and a function that operates of one of those values and returns an array. It returns a new array of values.</p>

<pre><code class="php">array_bind(array_bind(array('foo bar baz'), @words), @chars);
// returns ["f","o","o","b","a","r","b","a","z"]
</code></pre>

<p>Now that we have the <code>array_bind</code> function, we can apply functions to something in an array, and the result will always be an array! What happens if we first bind <code>words</code> and then bind <code>chars</code> to an empty string?</p>

<pre><code class="php">array_bind(array_bind(array(''), @words), @chars); // returns []
</code></pre>

<p>We get an empty array back, which is great!</p>

<p>You saw me wrap the empty string in an array, to be able to use <code>array_bind</code>. This is an act of "providing context". The array serves as a context wrapper for results of the chained functions <code>words</code> and <code>chars</code>. We'll always get our result as an array. If anywhere in the process something fails, we get an empty array, otherwise we get an array with value(s) in it.</p>

<p>I must admit, this doesn't look really great. Let's take a look at how this works in <a href="https://www.haskell.org/">Haskell</a>, a pure functional language.</p>

<p>Now, this is the equivalent of what we wrote earlier on in PHP:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">pure "" &gt;&gt;= words &gt;&gt;= chars
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="haskell">pure "foo bar baz" &gt;&gt;= words &gt;&gt;= chars
</code></pre>

<p>These return <code>[]</code> and <code>["f","o","o","b","a","r","b","a","z"]</code>, as expected, but how?</p>

<ul>
<li><code>pure</code> wraps the string in our "wrapper" list.</li>
<li><code>&gt;&gt;=</code> is the <code>bind</code> infix function; it takes the "wrapped" value on the left, and applies the function on the right to the wrapped value. It then returns a new wrapped value.</li>
<li><code>words</code> takes a <code>String</code> and returns a list of strings <code>[String]</code>, split by spaces. It's in Haskell's default module <code>Prelude</code>.</li>
<li><p><code>chars</code> is a function we made up, it takes a <code>String</code> and returns a list of strings <code>[String]</code>. By default, <code>String</code>s in Haskell are lists of <code>Char</code>s. To break up a given string in a list of strings that represent chars we need to map over the input string. The mapping function <code>(\x -&gt; [x])</code> gets a <code>Char</code> as input and returns a <code>String</code> by wrapping the given <code>Char</code> in a list; check it out:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">chars :: String -&gt; [String]
chars s = map (\x -&gt; [x]) s
</code></pre></li>
</ul>

<p>As you can see, Haskell was made for this kind of stuff... It also reads a lot better than our PHP implementation.</p>

<h2 id="expanding-on-this-concept">Expanding on this concept</h2>

<p>The reason this doesn't really work in PHP is that we don't have infix operators at our disposal. I've seen <a href="https://github.com/phunkie/phunkie">libraries</a> that do something with method calls along these lines:</p>

<pre><code class="php">pure('foo bar baz')-&gt;bind(@words)-&gt;bind(@chars);
</code></pre>

<p>which already looks a lot better than what we came up with. Failure can be encapsulated. There's a lot less boilerplate code to read. There's no checking for empty arrays or failure, while it still behaves as we wanted.</p>

<ul>
<li><code>pure()</code> wraps the value in an object.</li>
<li><code>bind()</code> is equivalent to returning a new wrapper object with the result of the applied function to the previously wrapped value. Internally it could all work using <code>arrays</code>, but it could just as well be done differently.</li>
</ul>

<p>For now, we've always worked with functions that return a number of results, but this whole concept can just as well be used with functions that are supposed to return a single result, like integer division <code>div</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="php">function div(int $divident, int $divisor): WrappedValue
{
    if ($divisor === 0) {
        return nothing();
    }

    return pure(intdiv($divident, $divisor));
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now, we created an integer division function that doesn't throw <code>DivisionByZeroError</code> exceptions, but uses this system of <code>WrappedValue</code>s to wrap it's return value on success (using <code>pure</code>, equivalent to an array with a value) or on failure (using <code>nothing</code>, equivalent to an empty array). Now, if we want to square the result of this, we can just bind <code>square</code> to the result of the previous computation.</p>

<pre><code class="php">function square(int $number): WrappedValue
{
    return pure($number * $number);
}

var_dump(div(10, 2)-&gt;bind(@square)); // [25]
var_dump(div(10, 0)-&gt;bind(@square)); // []
</code></pre>

<p>As with the previous examples, we can now just focus on the order of computation, without the need to worry about failure in the in-between steps.</p>

<p>There are also ways to make this whole thing even more interesting by providing more info like error messages in case of failure.</p>

<h2 id="day-to-day-usage">Day-to-day usage</h2>

<p>I'm not saying this is perfect for everything in OOP by any means, but we might want to think about how we handle failure in our (legacy) systems. I sometimes see trees of exception handling and boolean/null-checks on return values. This is a third option (PHP doesn't have option types by default); In lots of ways, the classic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Null_object_pattern">Null Object</a> pattern resembles this whole thing in a more Object Oriented way. In many functional programming languages this is actually the most widely used means of error handing. If you want to know more about it, I suggest reading up on <code>Functors</code>, <code>Applicatives</code>, and <code>Monads</code>. Scary names for new concepts, don't let them hold you back.</p>

<p>If you want to do the most simple and useful thing: think about how your functions behave. What goes in, what comes out? Writing the type annotations helps a lot. And of course, throwing exceptions is not a sin.</p>

<p>Happy programming y'aλλ! 👋</p>

<h2 id="what%27s-next%3F">What's next?</h2>

<p>Upcoming <em>lambda to the rescue</em> posts will be linked here:</p>

<ul>
<li>Lists to wrap failure (this post)</li>
<li><a href="/blog/2018/06/04/lambda-pure-functions">Pure Functions</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/2018/06/27/lambda-recursion">Recursion</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/2018/10/08/lambda-monoids">Monoids</a></li>
<li>...</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>