<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[CX Social Dev Blog]]></title>
    <link href="/blog/tags/Bug fixing.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-28T09:19:43+00:00</updated>
    <id>/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using decorators for debugging]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/09/22/using-decorators-for-debugging"/>
            <updated>2017-09-22T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/09/22/using-decorators-for-debugging</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When you're writing SOLID code, you probably hide some implementation details behind interfaces in many parts of your codebase. In this post, we'll talk about an HTTP client, which is hidden behind an interface. The exact implementation we use doesn't matter. It could be a simple cURL call, or we could be using a more advance package like <a href="https://github.com/guzzle/guzzle/">Guzzle</a> or <a href="https://github.com/kriswallsmith/Buzz">Buzz</a>. In any case, our application knows only about the <code>HttpClient</code> interface that it defined, like this.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace CoffeeRun;

interface HttpClient
{
    /**
     * @param Request $request An HTTP Request
     *
     * @throws ClientException if the request failed
     *
     * @return Response a response instance
     */
    public function execute(Request $request): Response;
}
</code></pre>

<p>Our code will ask the <code>HttpClient</code> implementation to <code>execute()</code> a <code>Request</code> and expects a <code>Response</code> if the call succeeded, or a <code>ClientException</code> if something unexpected happens.</p>

<p>The cool thing about this, is that our whole codebase needs to only know about this one interface, and not about the specific package that we're going to use. Plus, we can use another (fake) implementation of the <code>HttpClient</code> interface during testing.</p>

<h2 id="decorators">Decorators</h2>

<p>Now let's say that we want our application to make all HTTP calls with a certain User-Agent header. We don't want to go into our code and change every occurrence of <code>new Request</code> to also include that specific header. This is where decorators come in. We can "wrap" the <code>HttpClient</code> instance in a shell that acts as if it's the original <code>HttpClient</code>, but just takes the incoming <code>Request</code> and adds that header to it, and then passes on the call to the wrapped <code>HttpClient</code>. Like this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace CoffeeRun;

final class ClientWithUserAgent implements HttpClient
{
    private $wrappedClient;
    private $userAgentString;

    public function __construct(HttpClient $wrappedClient, $userAgentString = 'Coffee Bot 1.0')
    {
        $this-&gt;wrappedClient = $wrappedClient;
        $this-&gt;userAgentString = (string) $userAgentString;
    }

    public function execute(Request $request): Response
    {
        $request = $request-&gt;withHeader('User-Agent', $this-&gt;userAgentString);

        return $this-&gt;wrappedClient-&gt;execute($request);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Creating an instance looks something like this:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;?php

$httpClient = new ClientWithUserAgent(
    new ClientCurl(),
    'ROBOCOP'
);
</code></pre>

<p>As this Decorator also implements the same <code>HttpClient</code> interface, the application doesn't even know this is happening, because from the outside it looks and behaves exactly the same. This change essentially now is a change in the configuration file of our Dependency Injection Container, no other files needed to be changed to make this happen.</p>

<h2 id="using-decorators-for-investigation">Using decorators for investigation</h2>

<p>Now, if we want to investigate the requests and responses that we get from a service while the application is running, e.g. when an unidentified bug is happening, we could do it with a decorator. The rest of the application won't know about it and should just keep on working as usual, while we get logs of the data that we want:</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace CoffeeRun;

final class LoggingClient implements HttpClient
{
    private $wrappedClient;
    private $logger;

    public function __construct(HttpClient $wrappedClient, LoggerInterface $logger)
    {
        $this-&gt;wrappedClient = $wrappedClient;
        $this-&gt;logger = $logger;
    }

    public function execute(Request $request): Response
    {
        $this-&gt;logger-&gt;debug('request', $request);

        $response = $this-&gt;wrappedClient-&gt;execute($request);

        $this-&gt;logger-&gt;debug('response', $response);

        return $response;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The request and response are logged in our logs now, and they look good to us, but we still haven't found what we're looking for and we want to see if the requests our app is making work from the command line using <code>curl</code>. What if we made our application also log the complete curl commands? Then we could just copy paste them in our terminal to test them locally.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace CoffeeRun;

final class CurlCommandLoggingClient implements HttpClient
{
    private $wrappedClient;
    private $logger;

    public function __construct(HttpClient $wrappedClient, LoggerInterface $logger)
    {
        $this-&gt;wrappedClient = $wrappedClient;
        $this-&gt;logger = $logger;
    }

    public function execute(Request $request): Response
    {
        $method = $request-&gt;getMethod();
        $url = $request-&gt;getUrl();
        $params = $request-&gt;getParams();
        $headers = $request-&gt;getHeaders();

        $curlString = 'curl';
        $curlString .= ' --' . strtolower($method);

        foreach ($params as $key =&gt; $value) {
            $curlString .= ' --data "' . $key . '=' . $value . '"';
        }

        foreach ($headers as $key =&gt; $value) {
            $curlString .= ' --header "' . $key . '=' . $value . '"';
        }

        $curlString .= ' "' . $url . '"';

        $this-&gt;logger-&gt;debug('curl command', $curlString);

        return $this-&gt;client-&gt;execute($request);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Of course, this is an oversimplified way of building the <code>curl</code> command, but this will help you debug your HTTP calls by copy/pasting them to your terminal! Easy as that, and still no changes to the existing code. It takes one line to change it, and one line to delete and bring it back to production values.</p>

<h2 id="concerns">Concerns</h2>

<ul>
<li>Liskov Substition Principle: It's very important that our decorators still adhere to the original contract of the wrapped instance (in this case the <code>HttpClient</code> interface). If the decorator would produce another return value, or take different method parameters, it wouldn't work.</li>
<li>Applying a decorator that logs a lot of data in production might have an impact on your host. This is just an example of using your existing interfaces to create some plug &amp; play debugging solutions. If you do something like this in production, use the same caution as with other changes in production.</li>
</ul>

<p>That's it! Have fun.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bugfixing with Git Bisect]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/05/08/bugfixing-with-git-bisect"/>
            <updated>2017-05-08T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/05/08/bugfixing-with-git-bisect</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lately, we've deployed code that broke features, that were surely working in the past. Since we're quite heavy committers, things can get lost in our <code>git log</code> quite easily. That makes it harder to go back in history and find out what exactly caused the failure to happen. We simply would have to look through too many commits. That's where <code>git bisect</code> comes in!</p>

<p>The <code>git bisect</code> command provides us with a "binary search" over the commit history: we tell it when things were good for sure, and when they were bad, and bisect will jump to the commit that's in the middle between those two commits. We then test if things work as expected. If it was good at that point we know all history before that point was good, and we move on the the other half of history and apply the same process of dividing it in two and seeing if things work as expected. We do that until we arrive at a point where we know which commit broke things. That's where we need to look. The cool thing is that we can sift through a huge amount of commits in very few steps, and locate the problem quickly. Let's see how that works in practice:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Use <code>git log</code> to find out the commit hash for a commit where we know that things worked. Let's assume for now that the current <code>HEAD</code> we're at is at a point where things fail.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2017-05-08-bugfixing-with-git-bisect/1.png" alt="Screenshot of a git log history" /></p></li>
<li><p>Let's start the bisect session and tell git which points were good and bad:</p>

<pre><code class="sh">git bisect start
git bisect good {the commit hash where it was good}
git bisect bad
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, I didn't specify a commit hash for the <code>git bisect bad</code> command. Bisect assumes that we mean <code>HEAD</code> if we don't specify a commit. Since the current commit is bad, and <code>HEAD</code> always points to the currently checked out commit, we can leave this blank.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2017-05-08-bugfixing-with-git-bisect/2.png" alt="Screenshot of the first steps of a git bisect session" /></p></li>
<li><p>Now git will checkout a commit in the middle between our <code>good</code> and <code>bad</code> indications. Just do what you have to do to check if things work or not, e.g. run a unit test, or do some manual checks. Then pass that info on to git with <code>git bisect good</code> if things work, and <code>git bisect bad</code> if they don't.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2017-05-08-bugfixing-with-git-bisect/3.png" alt="Screenshot of a git bisect bad" /></p></li>
<li><p>Repeat <em>step 3</em> until git knows which commit went bad. It will indicate the process at every step. When it's done, git will show you the exact commit where things went from <code>good</code> to <code>bad</code>, using <code>git show</code> behind the scenes. You then know where to look to fix your problem.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2017-05-08-bugfixing-with-git-bisect/4.png" alt="Screenshot of the result of a bisect session: 1 commit" /></p></li>
</ol>

<p>To go back to master, do a simple <code>git bisect reset</code>. Congratulations! You've used <code>git bisect</code> to locate a problem in your commit history! Now, there are some more things to know:</p>

<h3 id="when-something-goes-wrong">When something goes wrong</h3>

<p>What if you did something wrong? You typed <code>git bisect bad</code> when everything was fine and you should've typed <code>git bisect good</code>? No worries! Bisect has a secret weapon: <code>git bisect log</code>, which lets you dump the history of this bisect session to a file. You can then remove the faulty step from the file with a text editor, and replay the entire session without that bad step.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Save your session to a file:</p>

<pre><code class="sh">git bisect log &gt; {filename}
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Remove the faulty line from the file using your favorite text editor:</p>

<pre><code class="sh">vim {filename}
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Reset your <code>bisect</code> session:</p>

<pre><code class="sh">git bisect reset
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Replay the correct steps:</p>

<pre><code class="sh">git bisect replay {filename}
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Do the rest of the bisect steps to find out where things went wrong. You can remove the replay file:</p>

<pre><code class="sh">rm {filename}
</code></pre></li>
</ol>

<h3 id="automating-the-steps-using-a-script-or-test">Automating the steps using a script or test</h3>

<p>You can automate the recursive steps of telling git that a revision is good or bad, by a simple bash script or unix command that returns a <code>0</code> status code on success, and <code>1</code> on failure. That way, if you have a testsuite, you can use that to really quickly find out where things went wrong by adding a test to it (the code is obviously not tested well or it wouldn't have happened so long ago), and using that test as the command. Let's see how that works:</p>

<pre><code class="sh">git bisect start
git bisect good {the commit hash where it was good}
git bisect bad
git bisect run {path to the script to run}
</code></pre>

<p>Don't forget to end your session with a <code>git bisect reset</code> when you found the offending commit.</p>

<h3 id="fantastic-on-fridays">Fantastic On Fridays</h3>

<p>So next time a nasty bug report comes in on a Friday -you're about to leave for a great weekend with your mates- and there were a thousand commits pushed to production that day by your team, don't dispair! Fire up <code>git bisect</code> and find where you need to be in a few minutes time, revert the commit, and enjoy your weekend!</p>

<p>Happy bughunting!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bug Fixing: Creating Synergy Between Dev and Support]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/03/01/batman-chatman"/>
            <updated>2017-03-01T09:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/03/01/batman-chatman</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is about bugs. About bug-tracking software. About prioritising what issues to fix first. About client-developer communication. About Service Level Agreements. And about hotfixes.</p>

<p><center><img src="/images/2017-03-01-batman-chatman/oh-f.gif" alt="Oh, f*ck" /></center></p>

<p>If that didn't scare you away, well hello there!</p>

<h2 id="first-line-support">First Line Support</h2>

<p>CX Social is software that allows companies to respond to their incoming social data (Twitter mentions, Facebook wall posts, etc.) as fast and as efficiently as possible. The customer care agents of companies like Telenet, De Lijn, NMBS (in Belgium), and Lufthansa, Turkish Airlines, T-Mobile (worldwide) use CX Social day-in day-out. They've set-up highly customized workflows within our tool, including automated actions, advanced filtering and real-time communication.<br />
This makes CX Social a business-critical tool for our clients to serve their customers. To help with set-up, or if clients have discovered a bug in our system, there is direct in-app access to a live chat that puts them in contact with one of our support agents.<br />
These support agents handle several chats and incoming emails per hour. We use Olark for in-app live chat, and use Salesforce Desk as the tool to handle incoming emails.</p>

<p><center><img src="/images/2017-03-01-batman-chatman/olark-chat.png" alt="CX Social in-app Live Chat via Olark" /></center></p>

<h2 id="an-empowered-support-agent-means-less-bugs">An Empowered Support Agent Means Less Bugs</h2>

<p>The support agents are the people in our company that know our tool best. In several cases even better than us developers who wrote the code for it. We involve our support agents in testing new features we build. By making support part of the Q&amp;A-process, we assure they have used new features before clients put their hands on it, but also that the product team keeps solving <em>real</em> problems that our clients are having every day.<br />
Apart from that, we actively maintain FAQ documents that help support agents identify problems, and collect the correct information to reproduce issues. We - try to - regularly organise trainings that go deep into certain aspects of our application. The customer support agents for CX Social know the basics of html, can interpret some - if not most - of our monitoring dashboards and know about <code>oAuth</code> or <code>API's</code> and find their way around the Chrome Developer Tools.<br />
All with one goal: to be able to solve our clients' problems as fast as possible. (Read: With as little help from a developer as possible 😏 )</p>

<h2 id="a-direct-line-to-development">A Direct Line To Development</h2>

<p>For those cases where the help of a developer is wanted, our support team has a direct line open to development, and that's the internal Slack channel <code>#supdev</code> that all support agents have joined. The main goal of this channel is to discuss whether a certain <em>symptom</em> is in fact an issue. We've seen it work best if all these discussions happen through a single and public channel so that multiple people can jump in to help. This encourages learning from each other's questions and answers, and also helps to hand-over problems to teams in other timezones.
On the other hand, on active days, the constant flow of messages in the <code>#supdev</code> channel often get in the way of focus. That's why the people in our development team are taking turns in answering support questions in this channel, and by doing that allowing others to preserve their focus. The whole development team (all full stack developers) takes part in this schedule we nicknamed the 'chatman', in periods of one week.</p>

<p>The result of this direct line is;</p>

<ol>
<li>Less bugs:

<ul>
<li>Because some configuration errors might be spotted earlier;</li>
<li>Because multiple reports by clients get bundled into a single bug report;</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Better bug reports:

<ul>
<li>More detailed steps to reproduce;</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>

<h2 id="github-as-bug-repository">GitHub as Bug Repository</h2>

<p>We use GitHub Issues as our main bug tracker. Not that it matters that much, but here's some of the reasons we appreciate GitHub:</p>

<ul>
<li>Integration with the git repository;

<ul>
<li>Closing issues from your commit message via <code>closes #issueno</code>;</li>
<li>The automatic referencing between issues, pull requests and commits;</li>
</ul></li>
<li>It's simple and easy to use interface; and at the same time flexible enough due to its labeling system.</li>
<li>Its simple and extensive REST API.</li>
</ul>

<p>We have set-up an <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/creating-an-issue-template-for-your-repository/">issue template</a> to guide our support agents to provide as much of the relevant context as possible. This issue template makes sure we always know the User ID and Account ID of the person having/reporting the problem.</p>

<p>We have several types of issues; "critical", "minor" and "major", which we indicate with <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/creating-and-editing-labels-for-issues-and-pull-requests/">issue labels</a>. Most issues are classified as "minor", and the "major"/"critical" labels are reserved for those "drop everything and fix this"-type of problems.</p>

<p>Whenever a Desk case (= client report) results in a GitHub issue (= actual bugreport), we make sure to save the connection between the Desk case and GitHub issue in our own database. <em>(The why is explained later.)</em></p>

<p>In a typical week at CX Social around 10 bugs are reported, and while most of them take about 2 to 3 hours to fix, some take days.</p>

<h2 id="batman-will-fix-it">Batman Will Fix It</h2>

<p>Similar to how we have a dedicated person answering questions from our support team, the person(s) responsible for fixing bugs is also a rotated role. Each week different people are assigned the Batman role, and spend their week digging into the reported and confirmed issues, trying to find a solution for them.</p>

<p>This separation of bug fixing work from standard product development <em>(i.e. new features, or reworked features)</em> has the following advantages for us:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Everyone in the team will at some point be involved in fixing bugs, including bugs in parts of the code he/she doesn't know yet. Of course, everyone's free to go ask other people's advice, but it's definitely an efficient way of preventing knowledge silos. This contributes to everyone's knowledge of the code base, and also to how much care is given to writing clean &amp; well documented code.</p></li>
<li><p>In weeks a developer isn't assigned the Batman role, he/she can fully focus on the product development project; making it easier to stay focused and work towards target dates. Before we used a system like this, it was often much harder to make progress on product development, because there's always a certain bug that got more priority.</p></li>
<li><p>By separating these duties it also becomes more measurable how much effort is spent - team-wide - on each type of job, and how we should distribute our resources.</p></li>
</ul>

<p><center><img src="/images/2017-03-01-batman-chatman/scars.jpg" alt="Do you want to know how I got these scars?" /></center></p>

<p>At the same time, a system like this creates a few problems as well:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Probably the person trying to find the cause of a bug is not the person who originally wrote the code, and thus it might take more time than somebody who knows the ins and outs of what he/she wrote.</p></li>
<li><p>Bugs that aren't fixed by the end of the week, will of course not go away by itself, and a handover to the next batman is needed.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>The solution for this is simple: allow to deviate from the guidelines. In emergency situations, more people are working on bugs than just the Batman. And if you are close to a fix on Friday evening and fixing it will only take another half a day; of course that's what we do. And have regular in-person <code>#supdev</code>-meetings with the support team, and this and next week's Batman and Chatman.<br />
The agenda for these meetings is:</p>

<ul>
<li>What are the most important issues still needing a fix, from a support point of view?</li>
<li>What are blocking problems, from a dev point of view?</li>
<li>Passing on information to the next batman, both from support and from batman.</li>
</ul>

<p>We use this system in a tech team of 11 people, of which 7 people are involved in this Batman/Chatman schedule. The rest of the team is either designer, data scientist or ops people. While it works for us now, we realise it might become hard if the team grows.</p>

<p>On top of the GitHub API we built several dashboards that plot the trend in amount of open bugs and that show our average resolution time. These are the prime indicators we take into account when planning extra resources for this role. Our Slack bot will also notify us when issues stay open for too long, or are unassigned, or miss labels, etc.</p>

<p><center><img src="/images/2017-03-01-batman-chatman/issue-stats.png" alt="Amount of open issues over time" /></center></p>

<p>When an issue is closed but without a resolution (it's a duplicate, we were unable to reproduce it, it's a limitation of the external services we use, etc.) we indicate this with a resolution label. And similarly we tag all bugs with a label indicating which CX Social feature group it's related to. These two types of labels help us assess the quality of both our bug reports as identify problem areas with the application.</p>

<h2 id="prioritising-issues">Prioritising Issues</h2>

<p>The nature of a bug typically entails its priority; if something is a problem with a core feature of CX Social, for multiple accounts at once, it's labeled as "major", and thus has higher priority over bugs classified as "minor". Luckily, the amount of "major" bugs is limited. So, most of the time we spent fixing "minor" bugs. Typically we have between 10 and 30 of these bugs open, and from this to-do list for the Batman it's important we focus on those issues that have the most impact, for whatever reason. It's our support team that decides which of these to work on, since they know a bug's impact on customers best.</p>

<p><center><img src="/images/2017-03-01-batman-chatman/github-screenshot.png" alt="Some open issues" /></center></p>

<h2 id="what-didn%27t-work">What Didn't Work</h2>

<p>We didn't always work this way. Over the course of the last 5 years, we've had a whole bunch of different approaches.</p>

<p>In our first iterations Batman also did the duties of who we now refer to as Chatman. But complex bugs often require a lot of focus (and we found out: more so than for standard product development work), so this combined role, resulted in a lower bug closing efficiency. And that's of course the main target for a system like this.</p>

<p>Not having a Chatman at all, is even worse. The fact that a developer can add his/her perspective to a bug report, greatly enriches the quality of a bug report. The fact that this communication with the Chatman happens over chat, avoids a slow ping-pong of "needs more information" comments on GitHub issues.</p>

<p>While it's sometimes tempting to skip a weekly <code>#supdev</code>-meetings, we've found that not having a regular in-person meeting between development and support creates an invisible "hostility" where it feels like one party is fighting against the other: fixing bugs versus reporting bugs. While what really happens is two teams working together to fix customer issues. Talking in person can cause breakthroughs because ideas get validated or ping-ponged.</p>

<h2 id="deploying-fixes-%26-reaching-out-to-the-customer">Deploying Fixes &amp; Reaching Out to the Customer</h2>

<p>When a developer has fixed a bug, it's pushed to a separate branch which is then opened up for peer review via <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/about-pull-requests/">GitHub's Pull Requests</a> and the Support Agents involved in the bug report are notified. At this moment it's also possible to fire up a staging environment with the bug fix to verify by support.</p>

<p>Approved bug fixes are typically pushed out to production the same day. And by requiring issues to be closed via GitHub's <code>closes #issueno</code> commits, our continuous integration agent Jenkins also knows what fixes he is deploying to production. We have configured Jenkins so that it leaves a comment on the actual GitHub issue with the build number and exact time of when a fix for that issue went live. Jenkins will also make sure to post any bug fixes that are deployed to a few of the relevant Slack channels.</p>

<p><center><img src="/images/2017-03-01-batman-chatman/fixed-comment.png" alt="It's fixed" /></center></p>

<p>This Jenkins-comment on the GitHub issue will also trigger the reopening of any Desk cases associated with the GitHub issue, so that our support team immediately has the relevant cases reopened. By closing the loop back to the customer we make sure that customer immediately knows about a fix, and that we have confirmation of the fix as soon as possible.</p>

<p>What strategies have worked for you to speed up the bug fixing process and ensure positive communication between those encountering the bugs, reporting the bugs and fixing the bugs?</p>

<p><center><img src="/images/2017-03-01-batman-chatman/fixed-slack.png" alt="It's fixed" /></center></p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>