<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[CX Social Dev Blog]]></title>
    <link href="/blog/tags/Internship.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-02T08:54:36+00:00</updated>
    <id>/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Real-Time Webhooks API: Secure an Internship with us]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/09/27/internship-webhooks-api"/>
            <updated>2017-09-27T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/09/27/internship-webhooks-api</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Are you a student looking for an internship for Spring 2018? We have a project involving real-time API's and webhooks that you might find interesting. Read on to know what we do here at CX Social and what the project is about.</p>

<h2 id="what-do-we-do%3F">What do we do?</h2>

<p>The Clarabridge CX Social team builds a customer care tool for social media. Our clients use our software to be able to respond to the incoming questions and complaints on their Facebook pages, Twitter accounts, Instagram profiles, a.o. These clients often have a high volume of messages, on several social profiles. We try to make those people’s lives easier by offering automation tools, smart routing of messages and reply suggestions, among others.
<a href="https://developers.engagor.com/team">Read more about what we do</a>.</p>

<p>As of February 2018, we have room for one or more enthusiastic interns to join us for (at least) a couple of weeks <em>(preferably 4 days a week, any time between February 2017 to June 2018)</em>, to work as part of the CX Social development team.
As an intern you are an integral part of the R&amp;D team working on different parts of the application using technologies like PHP, React, MySQL, Redis, memcached, ElasticSearch, RabbitMQ, a.o. The team consists of a designer, front-end developer, data scientist, and several system engineers &amp; full-stack web developers.
We are looking for a student with interest and knowledge of mainly back-end technologies, and some front-end knowledge.</p>

<p>Want to know more about what it’s like to do an internship here? Read about <a href="https://engagor.github.io/blog/2017/06/01/internship-gheerwijn-cx-social-developer/">Gheerwijn’s experiences</a> or the <a href="https://engagor.github.io/blog/2017/06/30/internship-achievements/">Achievements project intern Cedric is currently working on</a>.</p>

<h2 id="the-project%3A-webhooks-api">The Project: Webhooks API</h2>

<p>CX Social has an Rest (oAuth JSON) API used by several of our clients. Its documentation is publicly available on our <a href="https://developers.engagor.com">developer site</a> so have a look to see what’s possible with it.<br />
Its uses include displaying important social profile metrics on own websites, two-way syncing of data from the CX Social CRM to other (in-house or 3rd party) CRM’s (like Salesforce, a.o.). It’s also being used to display curated social mentions on own sites, or to combine data from CX Social with data from other tools on internal dashboards.</p>

<p>Today, the API is used in a <code>PULL</code> model only, where clients (periodically) request information from our API. This internship project involves a significant update to allow <code>PUSH</code> webhooks to be send to our clients.<br />
Clients have been requesting this feature, and are eager to start using it, to be notified of new data (e.g. new tweets), or updates to data (e.g. when a certain social contact’s information is filled in) in real-time.
The project would take inspiration from the <a href="https://developers.facebook.com/docs/graph-api/webhooks">Facebook Webhooks API</a>, <a href="https://dev.twitter.com/webhooks">Twitter Webhooks API</a>, or <a href="https://api.slack.com/custom-integrations/outgoing-webhooks">Slack’s Outgoing Webhooks API</a> and take into account other <a href="https://restful.io/webhooks-dos-and-dont-s-what-we-learned-after-integrating-100-apis-d567405a3671">common do's and don'ts regarding webhooks</a>.</p>

<p>It consists of the following features:</p>

<ul>
<li>Creating &amp; updating webhook-subscriptions (defining which webhooks should be delivered where). 

<ul>
<li>This should be possible via an API, as well as a web-interface;</li>
<li>Configured delivery URL’s should be checked for ownership by verification with configured handshake;</li>
<li>Configured delivery URL’s should be checked for validity of their SSL certificates;</li>
<li>Several types of subscriptions will be needed (i.e. subscribing to “account” updates, and subscribing to “user” updates);</li>
</ul></li>
<li>A robust webhook delivery system, consisting of:

<ul>
<li>Re-delivery when the delivery URL’s is unresponsive;</li>
<li>Trying to guarantee exactly-once delivery;</li>
<li>Signed webhook payloads, so receivers can verify the origin of the request;</li>
<li>Notifying the API user via email when their delivery URL continues to be unresponsive;</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Implementing the event-log that eventually triggers the webhooks:

<ul>
<li>Making sure changes in the CX Social code base trigger an event to the webhooks system;</li>
<li>Distribution of events to the right subscriptions</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Monitoring of the system to:

<ul>
<li>Be alerted when webhook delivery is running behind.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-09-27-internships-webhooks-api/slow-delivery.gif" alt="Slow Delivery" /><br />
<small>Our future clients, when their webhooks aren't delivered on time.</small>
</center></p>

<p>Together with the CX Social development team, you as an intern are responsible for choosing the right technologies &amp; architecture. For those interested in backend technologies, this will be an exciting project, that you can help shape, build and deploy to production.</p>

<h2 id="interested%3F">Interested?</h2>

<p>We are looking for someone to join us in the Gent, Belgium office of Clarabridge, located at <a href="https://www.google.be/maps/place/CX+Social/@51.0597245,3.7213322,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x47c37138e71c8617:0x314cae371e7de8a5!8m2!3d51.0597245!4d3.7235209">Grauwpoort 1, 9000 Gent</a>.
Does this seem like a fun challenge for you? Please reach out to <a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#105;l&#x74;&#x6f;&#58;&#106;&#x75;&#x72;&#114;&#105;a&#x61;&#110;&#46;p&#x65;&#x72;&#115;&#121;&#x6e;&#x40;&#99;&#108;a&#x72;&#x61;&#98;&#114;&#x69;&#x64;&#103;&#101;&#x2e;&#x63;&#111;&#109;">jurriaan.persyn@clarabridge.com</a> with your details and we can set-up an interview to see if there’s a fit.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-09-27-internships-webhooks-api/thumbs.jpg" alt="Toppie" /><br />
<small>Our future clients, when you've implemented this cool feature.</small>
</center></p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Achievement Unlocked: Secure an Internship with us]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/06/30/internship-achievements"/>
            <updated>2017-06-30T16:30:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/06/30/internship-achievements</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Are you a student looking for an internship for 2017-2018? We have a fun project for you...</p>

<h2 id="what-do-we-do%3F">What do we do?</h2>

<p>The Clarabridge CX Social team builds a customer care tool for social media. Our clients use our software to be able to respond to the incoming questions and complaints on their Facebook pages, Twitter accounts, Instagram profiles, a.o. These clients often have a high volume of messages, on several social profiles. We try to make those people’s lives easier by offering automation tools, smart routing of messages and reply suggestions, among others.<br />
<a href="https://developers.engagor.com/team">Read more about what we do</a>.</p>

<p>As of September 2017, we have room for one or more enthusiastic interns to join us for (at least) a couple of weeks <em>(preferably 4 days a week, any time between September 2017 to June 2018)</em>, to work as part of the CX Social development team. As an intern you are an integral part of the R&amp;D team working on different parts of the application using technologies like PHP, React, MySQL, Redis, memcached, Elasticsearch, RabbitMQ, a.o. The other team members include a designer, front-end developer, data scientist, and several system engineers &amp; full-stack web developers.<br />
We are looking for a student with interest and knowledge of both front-end and back-end technologies.</p>

<p>Want to hear from a previous intern what it’s like to join our team? Read about <a href="https://engagor.github.io/blog/2017/06/01/internship-gheerwijn-cx-social-developer/">Gheerwijn’s experiences</a>.</p>

<h2 id="the-project%3A-achievements%21">The Project: Achievements!</h2>

<p>A big percentage of users work in our customer care tool full time, day-in day-out. So it’s important for us to keep the user experience for them smooth and enjoyable. We want to make the experience more fun by developing an achievement based system in the web-application.</p>

<p>Apart from making CX Social more fun for agents to work in, we aim to improve team work, increase retention and let users discover new features.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-06-30-internship-achievements/notification.png" alt="NMBS Twitter Profile" /><br />
<small>An achievement notification popping up in the CX Social interface.</small>
</center></p>

<p>Some of the tasks we’re thinking of...</p>

<ul>
<li>Implementing user profiles, with a live feed of completed achievements throughout the account.</li>
<li>Help out thinking about possible ways of implementing.</li>
<li>Taking part in brainstorms.</li>
<li>Preparing for weekly status meetings, communicating about the progress of the project.</li>
<li>Having lots of fun, while trying to make this feature the best it can possibly be.</li>
</ul>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-06-30-internship-achievements/achievements.png" alt="NMBS Twitter Profile" /><br />
<small>A series of achievements for using one of CX Social's features: Canned Responses.</small>
</center></p>

<h2 id="interested%3F">Interested?</h2>

<p>We are looking for someone to join us in the Gent, Belgium office of Clarabridge, located at Grauwpoort 1, 9000 Gent.</p>

<p>Does this seem like a fun challenge for you? Please reach out to <a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#105;l&#x74;&#x6f;&#58;&#106;&#x75;&#x72;&#114;&#105;a&#x61;&#110;&#46;p&#x65;&#x72;&#115;&#121;&#x6e;&#x40;&#99;&#108;a&#x72;&#x61;&#98;&#114;&#x69;&#x64;&#103;&#101;&#x2e;&#x63;&#111;&#109;">jurriaan.persyn@clarabridge.com</a> with your details, and the requirements for your internship, and we’ll be in touch!</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-06-30-internship-achievements/profile-page.png" alt="NMBS Twitter Profile" /><br />
<small>A user profile with overview of completed achievements, personal information and live feed with account activity. </small>
</center></p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>