<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Clarabridge Engage Dev Blog]]></title>
    <link href="/blog/tags/OOP.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
    <updated>2019-09-02T14:23:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Inheritance Makes Me Cry]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2019/07/05/why-inheritance-makes-me-cry"/>
            <updated>2019-07-05T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2019/07/05/why-inheritance-makes-me-cry</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>People receiving code reviews from me on a regular basis will know this by now, but if I see inheritance happening in new code, I get moody. I look the <code>extends</code> in the eye and prepare for battle. I pick up my <em>SOLID</em> axe and start examining the principle that will allow me to slay this sub-class beast. And then I cry a little because I'll have to explain again where this centuries-old grudge comes from.</p>

<p>Now, don't get me wrong. I do understand the usefulness of inheritance in very specific cases. But most of the time when I encounter a subclassed beast during a code review I go all out offensive on it. Let's explore why:</p>

<h2 id="single-responsibility-principle">Single Responsibility Principle</h2>

<p>If you've been Object Oriented Programming for some time and you've been looking around a bit, you've definitely encountered the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SOLID">SOLID principles</a>. These are basically principles (not rules) that, when followed, will help you produce code that's easier to comprehend, change and test than when you were not following them. The first principle is the Single Responsibility Principle, which states that <em>a class should have only one responsibility</em>, or "one reason for change".</p>

<p>Let's try and use that to mitigate this case of inheritance:</p>

<pre><code class="php">interface Users
{
    public function getById(UserId $id): User;
}

class UsersDB implements Users
{
    protected $db;

    public function __construct(DB $db)
    {
        $this-&gt;db = $db;
    }

    public function getById(UserId $id): User
    {
        // ...
    }
}

class UsersCached extends UsersDB
{
    protected $cache;

    public function __construct(Cache $cache, DB $db)
    {
        parent::__construct($db);

        $this-&gt;cache = $cache;
    }

    public function getById(UserId $id): User
    {
        // get from cache?

        // if not in cache
        $user = parent::getById($id);

        // put in cache

        return $user;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Apart from all other issues that we have here, let's try to find out if the <em>Single Responsibility Principle</em> holds for this implementation. Looking at the class <code>UsersDB</code>, we can clearly see that it has just one responsibility: it represents a bunch of <code>User</code>s that are persisted to our database. It has no other reasons to change than for the purpose of representing users persisted in our database.</p>

<p>Now let's look at the <code>UsersCached</code> implementation. It represents a bunch of <code>User</code>s as well, in this case it caches them. We could think that this class has only one responsibility, until we see the <code>parent::getById()</code> call. It basically calls a method that we inherited (so it's available in our class) from the parent class. The knowledge needed to query the database is actually in our class because of the inheritance!</p>

<p>You could argue that it's still ok since it's clearly a parent class and nothing's wrong there, but let's look at it through the lense of <em>a class should have only one reason for change</em>. What if we decide that the constructor of the <code>UsersDB</code> class will now take a <code>PDO</code> instance instead of our own <code>DB</code> class? Guess what! The implementation of our <code>UsersCached</code> needs to change as well, because it needs to pass the PDO instance on to its parent. So a decision about the database made us change the caching class. And it's obvious that changing the caching mechanism would also affect the caching class. Which gives us more than one reason for change of this class.</p>

<p>This is clearly a violation of the Single Responsibility Principle.</p>

<p>We could fix this e.g. by using the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decorator_pattern">Decorator Pattern</a>:</p>

<pre><code class="php">interface Users
{
    public function getById(UserId $id): User;
}

final class UsersDB implements Users
{
    private $db;

    public function __construct(DB $db)
    {
        $this-&gt;db = $db;
    }

    public function getById(UserId $id): User
    {
        // ...
    }
}

final class UsersCached implements Users
{
    private $users;
    private $cache;

    public function __construct(Users $users, Cache $cache)
    {
        $this-&gt;users = $users;
        $this-&gt;cache = $cache;
    }

    public function getById(UserId $id): User
    {
        // get from cache?

        // if not in cache, get from nested user object
        $user = $this-&gt;users-&gt;getById($id);

        // put in cache

        return $user;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, it's only a very small change.</p>

<ul>
<li>we added <code>final</code> keywords to our classes and <code>private</code> to our variables to indicate that we don't want inheritance to happen 😏</li>
<li>we made both classes <code>implement</code> the <code>Users</code> interface</li>
<li>we injected an implementation of the <code>Users</code> interface into the constructor of the <code>UsersCached</code>, which will be called when no user is found in the cache.</li>
</ul>

<p>You could try and argue that this is no better because we still rely on the <code>Users</code> interface to stay stable. But if that interface changes, the responsibility "representing a bunch of users" changes, which is exactly the one responsibility that we have for our class. Changing the implementation of our <code>UsersDB</code> class will not affect the <code>UsersCached</code> class anymore, except when the contract of the interface is broken. Great!</p>

<h2 id="dependency-inversion-principle">Dependency Inversion Principle</h2>

<p>Let's take a short second look at the same code examples from above, now while trying to look at it from another one of the SOLID principles, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dependency_inversion_principle">Dependency Inversion Principle</a>. The principle comes down to <em>depending on abstractions instead of concretions</em>. In the case of the first example, the <code>UsersCached</code> extends <code>UsersDB</code>, which it needs when there's nothing found in the cache. We depend on a concrete class, which is a violation of the principle. In the second example, we made <code>UsersCached</code> implement the interface directly instead of extending from <code>UsersDB</code>. We then inject another implementation of <code>Users</code> in the constructor of <code>UsersCached</code>. Since we depend on the <em>interface</em> here, we don't depend on a concrete class anymore, and any implementation of the <code>Users</code> interface should work! This solution follows the principle! An added benifit of this is that our <code>UsersCached</code> instance is now much easier to test: we just need to inject a fake <code>Users</code> interface and see if it gets called when the cache doesn't have the value that we look for.</p>

<p>You could do the same with the other SOLID principles really, take e.g. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liskov_substitution_principle">Liskov Substitution Principle</a>. If a class extends from our class, it can easily overwrite a method to behave completely differently than what it was, so the principle doesn't hold. Again, it's easy to make a violation there.</p>

<h2 id="shared-dependencies">Shared Dependencies</h2>

<p>Now that we have a few SOLID reasons to say that inheritance is not a desirable solution for our problems, let's look at some other ways that I think it is misused. Consider this example:</p>

<pre><code class="php">abstract class Notification
{
    protected $id;

    public function __construct(Id $id)
    {
        $this-&gt;id = $id;
    }

    public function toUrl($relative = true): string
    {
        $path = "/notifications/{$this-&gt;id}";

        if ($relative === true) {
            return $path;
        } else {
            return "https://domain.of.application{$path}";
        }
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>I see this kind abstract classes quite often. It's a form of deduplication (people think they shouldn't repeat code), but what's problematic is the fact that you won't always know what kinds of exceptions to the rule there are going to be. Consider a class <code>AccountSpecificNotification</code> which extends from <code>Notification</code>. It wants to overwrite the <code>toUrl()</code> method, because account specific notifications are at <code>/account/{accountId}/notifications/{notificationId}</code>. Trouble is, we have to again implement the absolute and relative paths rule, and the chance of making mistakes becomes higher. Also the absolute URL of our domain is now in two classes. The knowledge about converting a notification to a URL is also in two classes. If we have a few of these exceptions, stuff gets difficult to keep track of.</p>

<p>As a solution, you could just make this class an interface and specify the <code>toUrl()</code> method on <code>Notification</code> instances. This way you always know the implementation for a certain type of <code>Notification</code> will be in the class itself. Then you'll have to live with the duplication. This is personally how I often do it. I <a href="https://medium.com/@nicolopigna/this-is-not-the-dry-you-are-looking-for-a316ed3f445f">duplicate stuff when in doubt and refactor later</a>, with the benefit of hindsight.</p>

<p>Another thing that you could do is look at the <code>toUrl()</code> method, and see that it's in fact a shared dependency between <code>Notification</code>s with another responsibility than "representing a notification". It could become another class. Let's write a separate class for it:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class NotificationToUrl
{
    public function getRelativeUrlForNotification(Notification $notification): string
    {
        $url = '/notifications/' . $notification-&gt;getId();

        if ($notification instanceof AccountSpecificNotification) {
            $url = '/account/' . $notification-&gt;getAccountId();
            $url .= '/notifications/' . $notification-&gt;getId();
        }

        return $url;
    }

    public function getFullUrlForNotification(Notification $notification): string
    {
        $path = $this-&gt;getRelativeUrlForNotification($notification);

        return "https://domain.of.application{$path}";
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Of course this is not perfect either, but it's at least a bit better from some standpoints: we get all the knowledge of converting notifications to URLs in one place, and we don't need inheritance!</p>

<h2 id="in-short">In short</h2>

<p>If you're using inheritance to fix a problem, I propose that you take a second and ask yourself why. In this post I propose a few ways of looking at inheritance that could help you come to a better solution in some cases.</p>

<ul>
<li>Are you violating one of the SOLID principles? Try and look for a solution where you can adhere to them more.</li>
<li>Are you trying to remove duplication? Try to <a href="https://medium.com/@nicolopigna/this-is-not-the-dry-you-are-looking-for-a316ed3f445f">postpone your decisions about the abstraction</a> that you're going to use to remove the duplication.</li>
<li>Do you have a shared method that multiple classes need? Try extracting it to a separate class.</li>
</ul>

<p>Since most of the time one of these methods produces a result that I find more desirable as explained in this post, I'll mostly oppose strongly against the use of inheritance when it's not strictly needed.</p>

<p>Hope that you'll be with me on slaying this beast! Until next time, happy programming! 🐲</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exceptional Exceptions]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2019/05/22/exceptional-exceptions"/>
            <updated>2019-05-22T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2019/05/22/exceptional-exceptions</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You've made it to this post thinking "Why do we still need to talk about Exceptions?". Well, they're used everywhere in OOP codebases, but sometimes they're used in a way that make debugging a bit difficult. Let's look at some ways to make debugging exceptions a bit more fun!</p>

<p>You know that feeling when you're trying to investigate an Exception that was thrown, but you can't seem to find the origin of it? You dig a bit deeper and you find that it's an exception that was caught and not rethrown, e.g.:</p>

<pre><code class="php">try {
    $this-&gt;doSomeImportantStuffWith($foo);
} catch (VeryDescriptiveException $e) {
    // do some stuff here

    throw new SomethingWentWrongException('oh no!');
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now, when you encounter this <code>SomethingWentWrongException</code>, you'll see that the trace takes you back to the 6th line of this code example. All information that was inside the <code>VeryDescriptiveException</code>, including its message, stack trace and other useful information is gone. Of course, debugging that error in <code>doSomeImportantStuffWith()</code> would be much easier if you had all that info.</p>

<pre><code class="php">Fatal error: Uncaught SomethingWentWrongException: oh no! in test.php:6
Stack trace:
#0 /Users/toon/Projects/devblog/test.php(34): Test-&gt;withoutPrevious()
#1 {main}
  thrown in /Users/toon/Projects/devblog/test.php on line 6
</code></pre>

<h2 id="prevent-information-loss-by-using-%60%24previous%60">Prevent information loss by using <code>$previous</code></h2>

<p>The obvious answer to this simplified example would be to just rethrow the <code>VeryDescriptiveException</code> instead of throwing a more general <code>SomethingWentWrongException</code>... And that would be valid, but let's say we're implementing an Interface that prescribes that we only throw <code>SomethingWentWrongException</code>s. We can't let the <code>VeryDescriptiveException</code> through or we'll break the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liskov_substitution_principle">Liskov Substitution Principle</a>. We want to throw that specific <code>SomethingWentWrongException</code>, while still somehow preserving the information of that previous exception that we caught. Let's check <a href="https://www.php.net/manual/en/exception.construct.php">the docs</a>:</p>

<p><img src="/images/2019-05-24-exceptional-exceptions/php-docs-exception-construct.png" alt="PHP Docs for the Exception Constructor" /></p>

<p>That <code>Throwable $previous = null</code> is what we're looking for! I've almost never seen this being used in the wild, but it's great for our usecase:</p>

<pre><code class="php">try {
    $this-&gt;doSomeImportantStuffWith($foo);
} catch (VeryDescriptiveException $e) {
    // do some stuff here

    throw new SomethingWentWrongException('oh no!', 0, $e);
}
</code></pre>

<p>this results in this error:</p>

<pre><code class="php">Fatal error: Uncaught VeryDescriptiveException: hello there! in test.php:15
Stack trace:
#0 /Users/toon/Projects/devblog/test.php(23): Test-&gt;doSomeImportantStuffWith('test')
#1 /Users/toon/Projects/devblog/test.php(34): Test-&gt;withPrevious()
#2 {main}

Next SomethingWentWrongException: oh no! in test.php:6
Stack trace:
#0 /Users/toon/Projects/devblog/test.php(34): Test-&gt;withPrevious()
#1 {main}
  thrown in /Users/toon/Projects/devblog/test.php on line 6
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, the stack trace of the original exception along with the one we wrapped it in are presented to us on error! We can see the message as well, and we can even add our own properties to the exception and be presented with them here if we just implement the <code>__toString()</code> method of the exception.</p>

<h2 id="custom-properties-in-exceptions">Custom properties in exceptions</h2>

<p>Let's say we've been building an API client that does some HTTP requests to an endpoint. Something can go wrong during the HTTP request, and we want to thrown an <code>ApiConnectionFailed</code> exception whenever the HTTP response code is not <code>2xx</code> or something else fails, so that the rest of our application has one single Exception it needs to prepare for. It would be very handy to debug if that exception contained our HTTP Request &amp; Response objects, e.g.:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class ApiConnectionFailed extends Exception
{
    private $request;
    private $response;

    public static function withHttpRequestAndResponse(
        $message,
        Request $request = null,
        Response $response = null,
        Throwable $previous = null
    ) {
        $exception = new static($message, 0, $previous);
        $exception-&gt;request = $request;
        $exception-&gt;response = $response;

        return $exception;
    }

    public function __toString()
    {
        $string = parent::__toString();
        $string .= "\n{$this-&gt;request}";
        $string .= "\n{$this-&gt;response}";

        return $string;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, we used a <a href="http://verraes.net/2014/06/named-constructors-in-php/">named constructor</a> <code>withHttpRequestAndResponse</code> to be able to keep the default constructor for Exceptions, but to also be able to construct it using a lot of extra relevant debugging information. This means that this Exception behaves like other exceptions and is very transparent to other developers.</p>

<p>If something fails, we'll construct the exception like this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">try {
    $response = $httpClient-&gt;execute($request);
} catch (HttpClientException $e) {
    throw ApiConnectionFailed::withHttpRequestAndResponse(
        'Http connection could not be established',
        $request,
        null,
        $e
    );
}

if ($response-&gt;getResponseCode() === 500) {
    throw ApiConnectionFailed::withHttpRequestAndResponse(
        'We got a 500 error from the host',
        $request,
        $response
    );
}
</code></pre>

<p>The exception will always contain all relevant information to be able to debug.</p>

<h2 id="recap">Recap</h2>

<p>To quickly recap, you can make your life a lot easier by</p>

<ul>
<li>providing exceptions with descriptive names</li>
<li>providing the <code>$previous</code> exception when rethrowing</li>
<li>providing all relevant data to an exception</li>
<li>providing named constructors for your exceptions to be able to add debugging info but keep the original constructor</li>
</ul>

<p>Hope that helps! Until next time, have fun coding! 🖖</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wishful Development]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2018/02/05/wishful-development"/>
            <updated>2018-02-05T14:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2018/02/05/wishful-development</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this blogpost I'm going to try and explain the main way I solve problems by delaying things that I don't want to think about at the time that I'm solving them. I use "wishful thinking" for that (hence the title of this blog post), but I guess this could also be called <em>Interface Discovery</em>. Let's look at a specific problem:
For the CoffeeRun application that we used as an example in <a href="/blog/2017/11/15/refactoring-to-collections/">previous posts</a>, we want to make a tool that compares prices of a given drink between a list of shops in our neighbourhood. What's interesting to us is the comparison logic:</p>

<ol>
<li>We ask the tool to find the cheapest {drink of a certain type}</li>
<li>The tool shows us the cheapest coffee shop in our neighbourhood where we can get a {drink of that type}</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="wishful-thinking">Wishful Thinking</h2>

<p>Let's write that in a very naïve way: I wish there was a comparison class with a method to find the cheapest drink.</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class CompareCoffeeShops
{
    public function findCheapest(Drink $drink): CoffeeShop
    {
        $cheapestShop = array_reduce(
            $this-&gt;shops,
            function($cheapestShop, $nextShop) use ($drink) {
                $cheapestPrice = $cheapestShop-&gt;getPriceFor($drink);
                $nextPrice = $nextShop-&gt;getPriceFor($drink);

                if ($nextPrice-&gt;lowerThan($cheapestPrice)) {
                    return $nextShop;
                }

                return $cheapestShop;
            },
            reset($this-&gt;shops)
        );

        return $cheapestShop;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>We just made assumptions about <em>everything</em>. Let's see.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>We assumed there was a <code>Drink</code> class. There wasn't, so let's make it happen:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class Drink
{
    private $name;

    public function __construct(string $name)
    {
        $this-&gt;name = $name;
    }
}
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>We assumed there was a list of coffee shops, oops, there was no such thing. Let's fix that by adding a constructor parameter:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class CompareCoffeeShops
{
    private $shops;

    public function __construct(array $shops)
    {
        $this-&gt;shops = $shops;
    }

    public function findCheapest(Drink $drink): CoffeeShop
    {
        // ...
    }
}
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Each <code>CoffeeShop</code> in the list seems to have a <code>getPriceFor(Drink)</code> method which returns a <code>Price</code>...</p>

<pre><code class="php">interface CoffeeShop
{
    public function getPriceFor(Drink $drink): Price;
}
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Talking about <code>Price</code>, how do prices look? They certainly seem to have a <code>lowerThan(Price)</code> method</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class Price
{
    private $price;

    public function __construct(int $price)
    {
        $this-&gt;price = $price;
    }

    public function lowerThan(Price $other): bool
    {
        return $this-&gt;price &lt; $other-&gt;price;
    }
}
</code></pre></li>
</ol>

<p>Let's write a test too:</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

use PHPUnit\Framework\TestCase;

class CompareCoffeeShopsTest extends TestCase
{
    public function test_it_finds_the_cheapest_cappuccino()
    {
        $shop1 = $this-&gt;createMock('CoffeeShop');
        $shop1-&gt;method('getPriceFor')-&gt;willReturn(new Price(200));

        $shop2 = $this-&gt;createMock('CoffeeShop');
        $shop2-&gt;method('getPriceFor')-&gt;willReturn(new Price(195));

        $shop3 = $this-&gt;createMock('CoffeeShop');
        $shop3-&gt;method('getPriceFor')-&gt;willReturn(new Price(250));

        $shops = array($shop1, $shop2, $shop3);

        $comparisons = new CompareCoffeeShops($shops);

        $cheapest = $comparisons-&gt;findCheapest(new Drink('Cappuccino'));

        $this-&gt;assertEquals($shop2, $cheapest);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Wait, what? The test passes! (I know, I know, it's not complete...)</p>

<h2 id="why-is-this-great%3F">Why is this great?</h2>

<p>We just tested and implemented most of the comparison logic through "wishful thinking" (although in a very naïve way). The details about looking up the real prices of a cappuccino in all shops in our neighbourhood were left out. We didn't need them! We actually wrote the most important thing first, how to compare drinks in multiple shops and find the cheapest place to buy our cappuccino! Nothing even hints at trying to scrape their websites (god forbid) and we can actually give up on that temporarily and implement a hardcoded list of shops and their inventories until we find the courage needed to scrape coffeeshop websites 😱!</p>

<p>In fact, look at the interface that we need to implement to get this to work:</p>

<pre><code class="php">interface CoffeeShop
{
    public function getPriceFor(Drink $drink): Price;
}
</code></pre>

<p>It's so simple! We could implement this however we want, e.g. have some shops with hardcoded inventories, others with webscrapers. None of our code needs to know about the specific implementation of the shops, it already knows about the available methods. And as a bonus, we didn't write any code we didn't need.</p>

<p>Think about it: if you can imagine it, it already works. Have fun programming! 🖖</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some insights regarding Value Objects]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2018/01/22/some-insights-regarding-value-objects"/>
            <updated>2018-01-22T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2018/01/22/some-insights-regarding-value-objects</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We've been using Value Objects more and more over the years, and although there's a lot of info out there, there are some things that we found particularly interesting to talk about in a blog post.</p>

<h2 id="what%27s-a-value-object%3F">What's a Value Object?</h2>

<p>Value Objects are simply put <em>objects that represent a value</em>, i.e. objects that don't have an identity except for the value they represent. Very frequently used examples are <code>Money</code> (if someone owes me €5 and they pay me €2 + €2 + €1 I'm happy) and <code>DateTime</code>, but there are lots of things that would qualify. For instance, combined values like a <code>TimeSlot</code> which comprises of two <code>DateTime</code> objects <code>start</code> and <code>end</code>, which is equal to another <code>TimeSlot</code> object if both <code>start</code> and <code>end</code> for both <code>TimeSlot</code> objects are equal. Or points in a 2D plane with <code>x</code> and <code>y</code> coordinates, where -you guessed it- two points are equal if both points have the same <code>x</code> and <code>y</code> coordinates.</p>

<p>A lot of people wonder why they should use Value Objects, instead of passing around primitive values. Let's take some user input in the form of a telephone number, and treat it as a <code>String</code>. We want to pass it around in our code. Somewhere in our code there's a function that expects a telephone number as a parameter. How can it be sure that we passed a telephone number? It can't... Since we're just passing around a <code>String</code>, it needs to do some checks: Does the string look like a telephone number? Does it have a valid country code? etc. The next function that takes a telephone number as a parameter needs to do these checks again. There are some rules about what makes a valid telephone number, which can't be encapsulated in the <code>String</code> representation. If we make a specialized object to represent that phone number, we we can check these rules upon creation of the object, and thus prevent invalid state before it occurs. If some part of our code now gets that <code>PhoneNumber</code> object, it can be sure that it's a valid phone number.</p>

<h2 id="yes%2C-value-objects-should-be-immutable">Yes, Value Objects should be immutable</h2>

<p>Earlier we said that <code>DateTime</code> is a Value Object. Since a <code>DateTime</code> is just a value, once it is instantiated it should represent that value. Let's check something out:</p>

<pre><code class="php">$noon1 = new DateTime('today noon');
$noon2 = new DateTime('today noon');
var_dump($noon1 == $noon2); // bool(true)

$noon3 = $noon1-&gt;modify('+ 2 hours');

var_dump($noon1 == $noon2); // bool(false)
</code></pre>

<p>What happened? I instantiated two <code>DateTime</code> objects that were equal to each other, representing "today at noon". I created a third <code>DateTime</code> object that should represent "today, two hours later than noon". After that, one of the objects that represented "noon" a second ago doesn't anymore. It's like saying: "here you have a 3", and when you start calculating with it, it changed to a 4. This essentially teleported us to another universe where 3 means 4 suddenly.</p>

<p>The reason this happened is because of the fact that the <code>-&gt;modify()</code> call mutates the <code>DateTime</code> object. If we prevent our objects from being changed (make them immutable), they will become a lot safer to work with. In this regard, you should probably always use <a href="https://secure.php.net/manual/en/class.datetimeimmutable.php"><code>DateTimeImmutable</code></a>.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-introduce-a-value-object%3F">How to introduce a Value Object?</h2>

<p>Let's say we have some code that takes a user's <a href="https://help.twitter.com/en/managing-your-account/twitter-username-rules">Twitter handle</a> to perform some operations:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class Twitter
{
    public function publicTimelineFor(string $handle)
    {
        $this-&gt;assertValidTwitterHandle($handle);

        // ... fetch &amp; return timeline
    }

    public function tweepsFollowing(string $handle)
    {
        $this-&gt;assertValidTwitterHandle($handle);

        // ... fetch &amp; return followers
    }

    /**
     * @param string $handle
     *
     * @throws InvalidArgumentException when not valid
     */
    private function assertValidTwitterHandle(string $handle)
    {
        // check the rules here, throw exception if not valid
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>assertValidTwitterHandle()</code> must happen in every call that uses the concept of a Twitter handle, but it's so easy to forget when you write a new function! Also, it's impossible to know if a given string has been approved in a previous call. If you now call <code>publicTimelineFor($handle)</code> and <code>tweepsFollowing($handle)</code> in succession for the same <code>$handle</code>, you're basically repeating yourself for no reason. Let's refactor this!</p>

<p>The first thing that you want to do is make sure you get your code under test (it should already be that way 😘). What I like to do in this case, is at least have some tests for what a "valid Twitter handle" means. Since I'll be working towards an object that can only represent a valid Twitter handle, I'll make the <code>private</code> assertion <code>public</code>, write some unit tests against the assertion, and be done with it. We'll change the test later on.</p>

<pre><code class="php">class TwitterHandleTest extends \PHPUnit_Framework_TestCase
{
    public function setUp()
    {
        $this-&gt;twitter = new Twitter();
    }

    /**
     * @expectedException InvalidArgumentException
     */
    public function test_it_throws_when_longer_than_16_chars()
    {
        $this-&gt;twitter-&gt;assertValidTwitterHandle('@VeryVeryVeryLongHandleThatShouldThrow');
    }

    // Tests for other rules go here too
    // - handle is a string and should start with '@'
    // - handle contains only uppercase chars, lowercase chars, digits and underscores
    // - make sure to provide some happy path cases as well
    // - you can of course use data providers in your tests to test multiple examples per test
}
</code></pre>

<p>Then create a very basic class for our Value Object:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class TwitterHandle
{
    private $handle;

    public function __construct(string $handle)
    {
        $this-&gt;assertValidTwitterHandle($handle);

        $this-&gt;handle = $handle;
    }

    private function assertValidTwitterHandle(string $handle)
    {
        // check the rules here, throw exception if not valid
    }

    public function __toString(): string
    {
        return $this-&gt;handle;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see I created a basic class with the Twitter handle as a string as a constructor parameter. If we use the class as a string, it will cast to the exact Twitter handle as a string that we got as input. This is a temporary measure. I then just moved the <code>assertValidTwitterHandle()</code> method from the <code>Twitter</code> class to <code>TwitterHandle</code>, and made it private. I can fix my tests by just using the constructor of the <code>TwitterHandle</code> class as entry point:</p>

<pre><code class="php">/**
 * @expectedException InvalidArgumentException
 */
public function test_it_throws_when_longer_than_16_chars()
{
    new TwitterHandle('@VeryVeryVeryLongHandleThatShouldThrow');
}
</code></pre>

<p>The code that used to work with handlers in the string form can now easily be changed to accept our object:</p>

<pre><code class="php">public function publicTimelineFor(TwitterHandle $handle)
{
    // ... fetch &amp; return timeline
}
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, we just typehint on the Value Object in the function definition, and since the <code>__toString()</code> method is defined to return the same string as we had before, everything just keeps working. With the one perk that the check for valid handles is gone from all our functions! We don't need it anymore, since it's now impossible to pass an invalid handle to them! Now you just need to handle the case of the invalid Twitter handle the moment you get it from the user.</p>

<p>As a final measure, I make sure that the output from the <code>__toString()</code> method can always be parsed back into the same Value Object again, by just giving it to the constructor. In this case that means that I need to return the complete value that the object was instantiated with (which is already the case). If you're tempted to use the <code>__toString()</code> method for other presentational purposes, <a href="http://verraes.net/2013/02/2013-02-16-casting-value_objects/#1-dont-use-_tostring-for-presentation">you're advised to create a specific function for that</a>.</p>

<h2 id="comparing-value-objects">Comparing Value Objects</h2>

<p>Let's say we want to represent points in a <code>x</code> by <code>y</code> two-dimentional plane using a <code>Point</code> Value Object. We've got something like this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class Point
{
    private $x;
    private $y;

    public function __construct(int $x, int $y)
    {
        $this-&gt;x = $x;
        $this-&gt;y = $y;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Comparing two of these <code>Point</code>s for equality is easy. We can just use PHP's built-in <code>==</code>, which will compare the objects by the values of their properties (exactly what we want for now).</p>

<pre><code class="php">$c1 = new Point(10, 20);
$c2 = new Point(10, 30);
$c3 = new Point(10, 20);

var_dump($c1 == $c2); // false
var_dump($c1 == $c3); // true
</code></pre>

<p>This gets more complicated when we want to e.g. calculate the distance between two <code>Point</code>s. Aren't those <code>x</code> and <code>y</code> properties private to the object?</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class Point
{
    private $x;
    private $y;

    public function __construct(int $x, int $y)
    {
        $this-&gt;x = $x;
        $this-&gt;y = $y;
    }

    public function distanceTo(Point $other): float
    {
        return sqrt(pow($this-&gt;x - $other-&gt;x, 2) + pow($this-&gt;y - $other-&gt;y, 2));
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Yes. But since these are two objects of the same type, they can access each other private properties! The code above just works! Be careful though, that you don't change any properties (and therefore make the objects mutable...).</p>

<h2 id="nested-value-objects">Nested Value Objects</h2>

<p>With the <code>Point</code> Value Object that we defined above, we can go a little bit further and represent other things in 2D planes, e.g. line segments, which are defined by two points A and B:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class LineSegment
{
    private $a;
    private $b;

    public function __construct(Point $a, Point $b)
    {
        $this-&gt;a = $a;
        $this-&gt;b = $b;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, we just created a Value Object that encapsulates two other Value Objects. This is great, we can successfully represent a <code>LineSegment</code> with this, but there's a problem with this:</p>

<p>The math (the domain in this case) tells us that two line segments are equal if they have the same delimiting points. In our case, we called them <code>$a</code> and <code>$b</code>, but actually, the order is not important. This means the <code>==</code> check I described above won't work like this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">$pointA = new Point(0, 0);
$pointB = new Point(5, 5);

$line1 = new LineSegment($pointA, $pointB);
$line2 = new LineSegment($pointB, $pointA);

var_dump($line1 == $line2); // false
</code></pre>

<p>We can solve that problem using an <code>equals()</code> method:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class LineSegment
{
    private $a;
    private $b;

    public function __construct(Point $a, Point $b)
    {
        $this-&gt;a = $a;
        $this-&gt;b = $b;
    }

    public function equals(LineSegment $other): bool
    {
        return ($this-&gt;a == $other-&gt;a &amp;&amp; $this-&gt;b == $other-&gt;b)
            || ($this-&gt;a == $other-&gt;b &amp;&amp; $this-&gt;b == $other-&gt;a);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>This can now be used to compare lines, but the <code>==</code> still gives wrong results. This is the point where I tell you <code>==</code> is not the best thing to use with Objects in PHP. You cannot override it, or make it work in all cases. It actually breaks encapsulation and checks private properties of objects. But we still want to make it work so that if it gets used instead of the <code>equals()</code> method, nothing breaks. We can then use a rule in our static analysis tools to check for <code>==</code> used with our object. We can make the <code>==</code> work using a fixed order in which point A and B get assigned inside <code>LineSegment</code>'s constructor:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class LineSegment
{
    // ...

    public function __construct(Point $a, Point $b)
    {
        $this-&gt;a = $a;
        $this-&gt;b = $b;

        if ($a-&gt;greaterThan($b)) {
            $this-&gt;a = $b;
            $this-&gt;b = $a;
        }
    }

    // ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>Our <code>Point</code> objects now need the <code>greaterThan()</code> method, which can be implemented a bit like this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class Point
{
    // ...

    public function greaterThan(Point $other): bool
    {
        if ($this-&gt;x == $other-&gt;x) {
            return $this-&gt;y &gt; $other-&gt;y;
        }

        return $this-&gt;x &gt; $other-&gt;x;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now we can simplify <code>LineSegment</code>'s <code>equals()</code> method, since <code>$a</code> and <code>$b</code> will be assigned in order:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class LineSegment
{
    // ...

    public function equals(LineSegment $other): bool
    {
        return $this-&gt;a == $other-&gt;a &amp;&amp; $this-&gt;b == $other-&gt;b;
    }

    // ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>Even though we don't want people to use <code>==</code> with our <code>LineSegment</code> Value Object, we made it work. Like this, we can prevent unexpected errors in our code. The final code looks like this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class Point
{
    private $x;
    private $y;

    public function __construct(int $x, int $y)
    {
        $this-&gt;x = $x;
        $this-&gt;y = $y;
    }

    public function distanceTo(Point $other): float
    {
        return sqrt(pow($this-&gt;x - $other-&gt;x, 2) + pow($this-&gt;y - $other-&gt;y, 2));
    }

    public function greaterThan(Point $other): bool
    {
        if ($this-&gt;x == $other-&gt;x) {
            return $this-&gt;y &gt; $other-&gt;y;
        }

        return $this-&gt;x &gt; $other-&gt;x;
    }
}

final class LineSegment
{
    private $a;
    private $b;

    public function __construct(Point $a, Point $b)
    {
        $this-&gt;a = $a;
        $this-&gt;b = $b;

        if ($a-&gt;greaterThan($b)) {
            $this-&gt;a = $b;
            $this-&gt;b = $a;
        }
    }

    public function equals(LineSegment $other): bool
    {
        return $this-&gt;a == $other-&gt;a &amp;&amp; $this-&gt;b == $other-&gt;b;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>If we wanted to represent the nested Value Objects as a string, e.g. to be able to save them in a field in the database, we could just make the <code>Point</code> represent itself as <code>(x, y)</code> and the <code>LineSegment</code> as <code>[(Xa, Ya), (Xb, Yb)]</code> by letting the <code>LineSegment</code>'s <code>__toString</code> method call that of the nested <code>Point</code> objects. For parsing the string representation back into a <code>LineSegment</code>, we'll need a <code>fromString()</code> <a href="http://verraes.net/2014/06/named-constructors-in-php/">alternative constructor</a> that can parse those strings and instantiate the correct objects for them, but I'll leave that as an exercise for the reader!</p>

<p>So, these were our take-aways after introducing Value Objects into our codebase. Did we forget something?</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Refactoring to Collections]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/11/15/refactoring-to-collections"/>
            <updated>2017-11-15T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/11/15/refactoring-to-collections</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How many times have you seen code like this?</p>

<pre><code class="php">public function displayCoffeeRunsOpenForOrders()
{
    $coffeeRuns = $this-&gt;coffeeRunsRepository-&gt;getAll();
    $openForOrders = array();

    foreach ($coffeeRuns as $coffeeRun) {
        if ($coffeeRun-&gt;ordersCanBeMade()) {
            $openForOrders[] = $coffeeRun;
        }
    }

    return $openForOrders;
}
</code></pre>

<p>Our office is very close to a <a href="http://simon-says.be/">great coffee bar</a>, and people are going there from time to time to get coffee for everyone in the office. Keeping track of who's going for coffee and who wants which coffee can be daunting, which is why I'm making this app. Let's take a closer look at that piece of code.</p>

<p>We're manually traversing an array of <code>CoffeeRun</code> objects that we got out of the Repository to filter out those who are open for orders. If we find one, we add it to a new array. This way we build a list of <code>CoffeeRuns</code> that are still accepting orders.</p>

<h2 id="to-iterator-or-not%2C-that%27s-the-question">To Iterator or not, that's the question</h2>

<p>Now, there's nothing very wrong with this, but it could be made a whole lot better, I think. Let's say that the Repository contains 1000 <code>CoffeeRun</code>s. We're now forcing the Repository to return an array of 1000 <code>CoffeeRun</code> objects when we call <code>getAll()</code>. That's not great. But let's think about it... The Repository already represents a list of all <code>CoffeeRun</code> objects. Why can't we just iterate over it? Something like this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">public function displayCoffeeRunsOpenForOrders()
{
    $coffeeRuns = $this-&gt;coffeeRunsRepository;
    $openForOrders = array();

    foreach ($coffeeRuns as $coffeeRun) {
        if ($coffeeRun-&gt;ordersCanBeMade()) {
            $openForOrders[] = $coffeeRun;
        }
    }

    return $openForOrders;
}
</code></pre>

<p>Having a repository we can iterate over like that would already be a first step. We could implement the <code>Iterator</code> interface within the Repository, and have this functionality immediately. But that would leave the foreach out there, and that would also present a problem for our dependency injection: the class where this <code>displayCoffeeRunsOpenForOrders</code> is a controller, and it has the Repository injected in its constructor, like this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">public function __construct(CoffeeRunsRepository $repository)
{
    $this-&gt;coffeeRunsRepository = $repository;
}
</code></pre>

<p>If we'd count on the fact that the Repository is now an <code>Iterator</code>, we should either typehint on it, but then we lose our typehint for <code>CoffeeRunsRepository</code>, which we don't want. Or we could make the <code>CoffeeRunsRepository</code> interface extend the <code>Iterator</code> interface, but then we get a really big interface we need to implement for every implementation of the Repository. Both of which are annoying to say the least.</p>

<h2 id="think-solidly-different">Think SOLIDly Different</h2>

<p>Let's try something completely different. In fact, the <code>foreach</code> in that method, is blocking progress for us right now; Let's extract that whole block to a method. This is what was in the controller before the extraction:</p>

<pre><code class="php">public function displayCoffeeRunsOpenForOrders()
{
    $coffeeRuns = $this-&gt;coffeeRunsRepository-&gt;getAll();
    $openForOrders = array();

    foreach ($coffeeRuns as $coffeeRun) {
        if ($coffeeRun-&gt;ordersCanBeMade()) {
            $openForOrders[] = $coffeeRun;
        }
    }

    return $openForOrders;
}
</code></pre>

<p>In the Repository we added a new method <code>openForOrders()</code>, and we kept the same implementation as before, which now resides in the implementation of that method:</p>

<pre><code class="php">interface CoffeeRunsRepository
{
    // ...

    /**
     * @return CoffeeRun[] A list of CoffeeRuns open for orders
     */
    public function openForOrders();

    // ...
}
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="php">final class CoffeeRunsRepositoryInMemory implements CoffeeRunsRepository
{
    // ...

    public function openForOrders()
    {
        $coffeeRuns = $this-&gt;getAll();
        $openForOrders = array();

        foreach ($coffeeRuns as $coffeeRun) {
            if ($coffeeRun-&gt;ordersCanBeMade()) {
                $openForOrders[] = $coffeeRun;
            }
        }

        return $openForOrders;
    }

    // ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>This is what's left in the controller after extraction:</p>

<pre><code class="php">public function displayCoffeeRunsOpenForOrders()
{
    return $this-&gt;coffeeRunsRepository-&gt;openForOrders();
}
</code></pre>

<p>I don't like the <code>Repository</code> word in there, while we're thinking about the Repository as just being a Collection. Let's rename the variable in our controller. Notice how well this reads:</p>

<pre><code class="php">public function displayCoffeeRunsOpenForOrders()
{
    return $this-&gt;coffeeruns-&gt;openForOrders();
}
</code></pre>

<p>"Return CoffeeRuns that are Open For Orders". I like it. What's even better, is that the filtering of the Collection is now happening in the object that worries about the Collection, namely the Repository. This means that the specific implementations can optimize for their own benifits. E.g. the database implementation of the Repository can use a specific <code>WHERE</code> query so that it doesn't need to filter <code>CoffeeRun</code>s in PHP, and as a result of that it doesn't need to load a whole list of <code>CoffeeRun</code> objects into memory.</p>

<h2 id="bump-your-head-twice">Bump your head twice</h2>

<p>What if we want a second method in our controller that displays all CoffeeRuns that are open for orders, and will happen before noon? The <code>openForOrders()</code> method won't be enough. We could use it, and then use a <code>foreach</code> as in the first example of the blog post, but then we're back to square one. We could also make it a Repository method, and that would be okay, but only if we don't have to do it too many times. Let's look for a different solution.</p>

<p>It looks like we now have two problems:</p>

<ol>
<li>We want to encapsulate the "looping over a list and picking out specific items"</li>
<li>We want to combine several of these actions on a list, or at least do them in succession</li>
</ol>

<p>The problems always come up when we're talking to the Repository. We made two changes to it, that were both half solutions. The Repository has too many responsibilities (Storage and Collection). What would happen if we'd return an object representing a list of CoffeeRun objects from the Repository, and use that to iterate over? The Repository only takes care of the storage, and the Collection object takes care of the Collection stuff.</p>

<p>What we want to do is "filter" CoffeeRuns so that we get CoffeeRuns that are open for orders, and then filter those again so that we get those open for orders that are happening before noon. In pseudo code:</p>

<pre><code class="php">coffeeRuns = repository.getAll
coffeeRuns
    .thatAre(openForOrders)
    .thatAre(happeningBeforeNoon)
</code></pre>

<p>If we can express <code>openForOrders</code> and <code>happeningBeforeNoon</code> as functions that take a <code>CoffeeRun</code> object and return a boolean (we'll call them predicates), then the <code>thatAre()</code> implementation could be very generic! Let's check it out:</p>

<pre><code class="php">$openForOrders = function (CoffeeRun $coffeeRun)
{
    return $coffeeRun-&gt;ordersCanBeMade();
};

$noon = new DateTime('today noon');
$happeningBeforeNoon = function (CoffeeRun $coffeeRun) use ($noon)
{
    return $coffeeRun-&gt;getDate() &lt; $noon;
};
</code></pre>

<p>Now we'll create the <code>CoffeeRuns</code> Collection object, with a <code>thatAre</code> method:</p>

<pre><code class="php">interface CoffeeRuns
{
    /**
     * @param callable function that takes a CoffeeRun and returns a boolean
     *
     * @return CoffeeRuns that match the predicate
     */
    public function thatAre(callable $matchingPredicate);

    /**
     * @return CoffeeRun[] An array of CoffeeRuns
     */
    public function asArray();
}
</code></pre>

<p>Let's create a naïve <code>array</code> based implementation of it:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class CoffeeRunsArray implements CoffeeRuns
{
    private $coffeeRuns;

    public function __construct(array $coffeeRuns)
    {
        $this-&gt;coffeeRuns = $coffeeRuns;
    }

    public function thatAre(callable $matchingPredicate)
    {
        return new static(
            array_filter(
                $this-&gt;coffeeRuns,
                $matchingPredicate
            )
        );
    }

    public function asArray()
    {
        $this-&gt;coffeeRuns;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Right now, we can have our <code>CoffeeRunsRepository</code> return a <code>CoffeeRuns</code> Collection object for the <code>getAll()</code> method instead of <code>CoffeeRun[]</code> (an array of CoffeeRun) objects, and remove the specific methods we created, like <code>openForOrders()</code>.</p>

<pre><code class="php">interface CoffeeRunsRepository
{
    /**
     * @return CoffeeRuns A collection of CoffeeRuns
     */
    public function getAll();
}
</code></pre>

<p>In the controller, we now get this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class CoffeeController
{
    private $coffeeRuns;
    private $openForOrders;
    private $happeningBeforeNoon;

    public function __construct(CoffeeRunsRepository $repository)
    {
        $this-&gt;coffeeRuns = $repository;

        $this-&gt;openForOrders = function (CoffeeRun $coffeeRun)
        {
            return $coffeeRun-&gt;ordersCanBeMade();
        };

        $noon = new DateTime('today noon');
        $this-&gt;happeningBeforeNoon = function (CoffeeRun $coffeeRun) use ($noon)
        {
            return $coffeeRun-&gt;getDate() &lt; $noon;
        };
    }

    public function displayCoffeeRunsOpenForOrders()
    {
        $coffeeRuns =
            $this-&gt;coffeeRuns-&gt;getAll()
            -&gt;thatAre($this-&gt;openForOrders);

        return $coffeeRuns-&gt;asArray();
    }

    public function displayCoffeeRunsOpenForOrdersAndBeforeNoon()
    {
        $coffeeRuns =
            $this-&gt;coffeeRuns-&gt;getAll()
            -&gt;thatAre($this-&gt;openForOrders)
            -&gt;thatAre($this-&gt;happeningBeforeNoon);

        return $coffeeRuns-&gt;asArray();
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, the individual methods got very readable. The operations on the Collections are encapsulated. I extracted the <code>$openForOrders</code> and <code>$happeningBeforeNoon</code> predicates to class variables, because I didn't like the duplication in both controller methods, however, I'm not satisfied with their presence in the constructor. We could create a <code>Predicate</code> interface and make the <code>thatAre()</code> method accept <code>Predicate</code> instances. As a result our controller would just do something like <code>$coffeeRuns-&gt;thatAre(new OpenForOrders());</code>. But let's leave it like this for now. I've got some critical questions coming in:</p>

<h2 id="wait-a-minute%21-you-didn%27t-solve-the-memory-problem%21">Wait a minute! You didn't solve the memory problem!</h2>

<p>Exactly. Let's do that right now.</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class CoffeeRunsWithIterator implements CoffeeRuns
{
    private $coffeeRuns;
    private $predicates;

    public function __construct(Iterator $coffeeRuns, array $predicates = array())
    {
        $this-&gt;coffeeRuns = $coffeeRuns;
        $this-&gt;predicates = $predicates;
    }

    public function thatAre(callable $matchingPredicate)
    {
        $predicates = $this-&gt;predicates;
        $predicates[] = $matchingPredicate;

        return new static(
            $this-&gt;coffeeRuns,
            $predicates
        );
    }

    public function asArray()
    {
        $collectionAsArray = array();

        foreach ($this-&gt;coffeeRuns as $coffeeRun) {
            foreach ($this-&gt;predicates as $predicate) {
                if (call_user_func($predicate, $coffeeRun) !== true) {
                    continue 2;
                }
            }

            $collectionAsArray[] = $coffeeRun;
        }

        return $collectionAsArray;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>This is an implementation of the <code>CoffeeRuns</code> Collection interface that takes an <code>Iterator</code>. Whenever the <code>thatAre()</code> method gets called with a predicate, we don't do anything, except for creating a new instance of the Collection class with the same <code>Iterator</code> in it, but with the predicate added to the list of predicates that must be matched for each element in the Collection. It's only at the last step, when we try to extract the contents of the collection, that we run the <code>Iterator</code> and check every value against the given predicates. We still need to run the predicates against the whole collection, but because they are within an <code>Iterator</code>, the <code>Iterator</code> can e.g. get them from the database one by one. That's an implementation detail of the Repository.</p>

<h2 id="what-if-we-want-to-be-able-to-use-mysql-%60where%60-statements-in-our-repositories%3F">What if we want to be able to use MySQL <code>WHERE</code> statements in our Repositories?</h2>

<p>Let's say that we want to create a MySQL implementation of the Repository. We don't really want to write a query that will get the whole list of CoffeeRuns, even though we worked with an <code>Iterator</code> before (and thus preserving memory issues), so just passing closures to the <code>thatAre()</code> method will not help us a whole lot to write efficient queries. To improve on that, we could start passing our predicates as objects instead of closures, like this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">interface CoffeeRuns
{
    /**
     * @param Predicate that CoffeeRuns need to satisfy
     *
     * @return CoffeeRuns that match the predicate
     */
    public function thatAre(Predicate $matching);

    /**
     * @return CoffeeRun[] An array of CoffeeRuns
     */
    public function asArray();
}
</code></pre>

<p>A predicate could look something like this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">interface Predicate
{
    /**
     * @param CoffeeRun the CoffeeRun we want to check
     *
     * @return bool if the Predicate is satisfied by given CoffeeRun
     */
    public function isSatisfiedBy(CoffeeRun $coffeeRun);
}
</code></pre>

<p>And to get the same functionality as before we can implement it like this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class OpenForOrders implements Predicate
{
    public function isSatisfiedBy(CoffeeRun $coffeeRun)
    {
        return $coffeeRun-&gt;ordersCanBeMade();
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>When we have this in place, implementing a repository that can translate these predicates to the correct <code>WHERE</code> statements is pretty much trivial: without doing an actual query, the Repository returns a <code>CoffeeRuns</code> collection object that can be filtered using <code>Predicate</code>s and when that is done, the query can be built by translating the Predicates to the appropriate <code>WHERE</code> statements. Now the <code>Predicate</code> object can still be used to check if a given <code>CoffeeRun</code> satisfies the rule encapsulated within it, but within the Repository, a more efficient way is used against the whole database table full of CoffeeRuns. Eric Evans calls this concept <code>Specification</code>, and you can read all about it in his great book <a href="http://dddcommunity.org/book/evans_2003/">Domain Driven Design</a>.</p>

<h2 id="doing-something-with-all-objects-in-our-collection">Doing something with all objects in our collection</h2>

<p>Let's say we want people to <code>stopOrdering()</code> for all <code>CoffeeRun</code>s that are happening before noon.</p>

<pre><code class="php">$stopOrdering = function (CoffeeRun $coffeeRun)
{
    $coffeeRun-&gt;stopOrdering();

    return $coffeeRun;
};

$coffeeRuns = $repository-&gt;getAll();
$stoppedOrderingForTheseRuns = $coffeeRuns
    -&gt;thatAre($happeningBeforeNoon)
    -&gt;updateEach($stopOrdering);
</code></pre>

<p>Let's add it to the Collection interface:</p>

<pre><code class="php">interface CoffeeRuns
{
    /**
     * @param Predicate that CoffeeRuns need to satisfy
     *
     * @return CoffeeRuns that match the predicate
     */
    public function thatAre(Predicate $matching);

    /**
     * @param callable function that takes a CoffeeRun and returns an updated one
     *
     * @return CoffeeRuns that got updated
     */
    public function updateEach(callable $update);

    /**
     * @return CoffeeRun[] An array of CoffeeRuns
     */
    public function asArray();
}
</code></pre>

<p>The implementation for the <code>CoffeeRunsArray</code> could be something like this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">final class CoffeeRunsArray implements CoffeeRuns
{
    private $coffeeRuns;

    public function __construct(array $coffeeRuns)
    {
        $this-&gt;coffeeRuns = $coffeeRuns;
    }

    public function thatAre(Predicate $predicate)
    {
        return new static(
            array_filter(
                $this-&gt;coffeeRuns,
                function (CoffeeRun $run) use ($predicate) {
                    return $predicate-&gt;isSatisfiedBy($run);
                }
            )
        );
    }

    public function updateEach(callable $update)
    {
        return new static(
            array_map(
                $update,
                $this-&gt;coffeeRuns
            )
        );
    }

    public function asArray()
    {
        $this-&gt;coffeeRuns;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, the implementation is trivial in this case, but again it provides us with a powerful abstraction. The code that operates on the Collection doesn't have to know anything about how the Collection is implemented, it just knows about the methods we provided for interacting with it. For those that are into functional programming, we just implemented <code>filter</code> and <code>map</code> here.</p>

<p>I hope you see the value in this. For pieces of code where a lot of actions need to happen on Collections of objects, this might be the way to go. Since the code doesn't have to know anything about the implementation of the Collection, you can change it at any time. For instance, when you start out, you can just use a simple <code>Array</code> implementation, and swap it out for an <code>Iterator</code> later on when you notice memory consumption going up. It can also make things pretty readable, as demonstrated above with the <code>$coffeeRuns-&gt;thatAre(new OpenForOrders());</code>.</p>

<p>You can also choose to go A LOT further, or less far into this, as you desire. Good luck on your explorations!</p>

<p>PS: I gave a talk on this subject at the <a href="http://php.gent/">PHP.GENT meetup</a>, you can find the slides <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/turanct/the-language-of-collections">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using decorators for debugging]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/09/22/using-decorators-for-debugging"/>
            <updated>2017-09-22T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/09/22/using-decorators-for-debugging</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When you're writing SOLID code, you probably hide some implementation details behind interfaces in many parts of your codebase. In this post, we'll talk about an HTTP client, which is hidden behind an interface. The exact implementation we use doesn't matter. It could be a simple cURL call, or we could be using a more advance package like <a href="https://github.com/guzzle/guzzle/">Guzzle</a> or <a href="https://github.com/kriswallsmith/Buzz">Buzz</a>. In any case, our application knows only about the <code>HttpClient</code> interface that it defined, like this.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace CoffeeRun;

interface HttpClient
{
    /**
     * @param Request $request An HTTP Request
     *
     * @throws ClientException if the request failed
     *
     * @return Response a response instance
     */
    public function execute(Request $request): Response;
}
</code></pre>

<p>Our code will ask the <code>HttpClient</code> implementation to <code>execute()</code> a <code>Request</code> and expects a <code>Response</code> if the call succeeded, or a <code>ClientException</code> if something unexpected happens.</p>

<p>The cool thing about this, is that our whole codebase needs to only know about this one interface, and not about the specific package that we're going to use. Plus, we can use another (fake) implementation of the <code>HttpClient</code> interface during testing.</p>

<h2 id="decorators">Decorators</h2>

<p>Now let's say that we want our application to make all HTTP calls with a certain User-Agent header. We don't want to go into our code and change every occurrence of <code>new Request</code> to also include that specific header. This is where decorators come in. We can "wrap" the <code>HttpClient</code> instance in a shell that acts as if it's the original <code>HttpClient</code>, but just takes the incoming <code>Request</code> and adds that header to it, and then passes on the call to the wrapped <code>HttpClient</code>. Like this:</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace CoffeeRun;

final class ClientWithUserAgent implements HttpClient
{
    private $wrappedClient;
    private $userAgentString;

    public function __construct(HttpClient $wrappedClient, $userAgentString = 'Coffee Bot 1.0')
    {
        $this-&gt;wrappedClient = $wrappedClient;
        $this-&gt;userAgentString = (string) $userAgentString;
    }

    public function execute(Request $request): Response
    {
        $request = $request-&gt;withHeader('User-Agent', $this-&gt;userAgentString);

        return $this-&gt;wrappedClient-&gt;execute($request);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Creating an instance looks something like this:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;?php

$httpClient = new ClientWithUserAgent(
    new ClientCurl(),
    'ROBOCOP'
);
</code></pre>

<p>As this Decorator also implements the same <code>HttpClient</code> interface, the application doesn't even know this is happening, because from the outside it looks and behaves exactly the same. This change essentially now is a change in the configuration file of our Dependency Injection Container, no other files needed to be changed to make this happen.</p>

<h2 id="using-decorators-for-investigation">Using decorators for investigation</h2>

<p>Now, if we want to investigate the requests and responses that we get from a service while the application is running, e.g. when an unidentified bug is happening, we could do it with a decorator. The rest of the application won't know about it and should just keep on working as usual, while we get logs of the data that we want:</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace CoffeeRun;

final class LoggingClient implements HttpClient
{
    private $wrappedClient;
    private $logger;

    public function __construct(HttpClient $wrappedClient, LoggerInterface $logger)
    {
        $this-&gt;wrappedClient = $wrappedClient;
        $this-&gt;logger = $logger;
    }

    public function execute(Request $request): Response
    {
        $this-&gt;logger-&gt;debug('request', $request);

        $response = $this-&gt;wrappedClient-&gt;execute($request);

        $this-&gt;logger-&gt;debug('response', $response);

        return $response;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The request and response are logged in our logs now, and they look good to us, but we still haven't found what we're looking for and we want to see if the requests our app is making work from the command line using <code>curl</code>. What if we made our application also log the complete curl commands? Then we could just copy paste them in our terminal to test them locally.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace CoffeeRun;

final class CurlCommandLoggingClient implements HttpClient
{
    private $wrappedClient;
    private $logger;

    public function __construct(HttpClient $wrappedClient, LoggerInterface $logger)
    {
        $this-&gt;wrappedClient = $wrappedClient;
        $this-&gt;logger = $logger;
    }

    public function execute(Request $request): Response
    {
        $method = $request-&gt;getMethod();
        $url = $request-&gt;getUrl();
        $params = $request-&gt;getParams();
        $headers = $request-&gt;getHeaders();

        $curlString = 'curl';
        $curlString .= ' --' . strtolower($method);

        foreach ($params as $key =&gt; $value) {
            $curlString .= ' --data "' . $key . '=' . $value . '"';
        }

        foreach ($headers as $key =&gt; $value) {
            $curlString .= ' --header "' . $key . '=' . $value . '"';
        }

        $curlString .= ' "' . $url . '"';

        $this-&gt;logger-&gt;debug('curl command', $curlString);

        return $this-&gt;client-&gt;execute($request);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Of course, this is an oversimplified way of building the <code>curl</code> command, but this will help you debug your HTTP calls by copy/pasting them to your terminal! Easy as that, and still no changes to the existing code. It takes one line to change it, and one line to delete and bring it back to production values.</p>

<h2 id="concerns">Concerns</h2>

<ul>
<li>Liskov Substition Principle: It's very important that our decorators still adhere to the original contract of the wrapped instance (in this case the <code>HttpClient</code> interface). If the decorator would produce another return value, or take different method parameters, it wouldn't work.</li>
<li>Applying a decorator that logs a lot of data in production might have an impact on your host. This is just an example of using your existing interfaces to create some plug &amp; play debugging solutions. If you do something like this in production, use the same caution as with other changes in production.</li>
</ul>

<p>That's it! Have fun.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>