<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[CX Social Dev Blog]]></title>
    <link href="/blog/tags/People.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-03T08:03:38+00:00</updated>
    <id>/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Skill Based Routing: Secure an Internship with us]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2018/07/02/internship-skill-based-routing"/>
            <updated>2018-07-02T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2018/07/02/internship-skill-based-routing</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-do-we-do%3F">What do we do?</h2>

<p>The Clarabridge CX Social team builds a customer care tool for social media. Our clients use our software to be able to respond to the incoming questions and complaints on their Facebook pages, Twitter accounts, Instagram profiles, a.o. These clients often have a high volume of incoming messages, on several social profiles. We try to make those people’s lives easier by offering automation tools, smart routing of messages and reply suggestions, among others.
<a href="https://developers.engagor.com/team">Read more about what we do here</a>.</p>

<p>As of September 2018, we have room for one or more enthusiastic interns to join us for (at least) a couple of weeks <em>(preferably 4 days a week, any time between September 2018 to June 2019)</em>, to work as part of the CX Social development team.</p>

<h2 id="the-project%3A-skill-based-routing%21">The Project: Skill based routing!</h2>

<p>We’re looking for someone to help us solve this problem for our clients; When a new question or complaints comes in, a customer care agent will handle that complaint; but which agent? Clarabridge CX Social offers several ways and algorithms that can help decide which questions go to which agent at a certain time, but there is still room for improvement … Ideally we want to assign the question to the agent that will be able to handle &amp; answer the question adequately in the shortest amount of time. Several factors are at play here: properties of the question, metadata about the question, metadata from who’s asking, which agents are available, skills of those agents, which mailboxes they work in, etc. We want you to look for ways how we can optimize our current algorithms and help us to implement them.</p>

<p>Here's a real-world example: a question in French about billing comes in 5 minutes before the end of the Paris team shift. Who will handle this question?</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2018-07-02-internship-skill-based-routing/routing.png" alt="Skill Based Routing" /><br />
<small>An achievement notification popping up in the CX Social interface.</small>
</center></p>

<p>We will provide labeled data and statistics about agent performance. It’s up to you to figure out the best approach, with our help of course.</p>

<h2 id="the-internship">The Internship</h2>

<p>As an intern you are an integral part of the R&amp;D team working on different parts of the application using technologies like PHP, React, MySQL, Redis, memcached, ElasticSearch, RabbitMQ, a.o. The other team members include a designer, front-end developer, data scientist, and several system engineers &amp; full-stack web developers.
We are looking for a student with interest and knowledge of both front-end as back-end technologies.</p>

<p>Want to hear from a previous intern what it’s like to join our team? Read about <a href="https://engagor.github.io/blog/2017/06/01/internship-gheerwijn-cx-social-developer/">Gheerwijn’s experiences</a>.</p>

<h2 id="interested%3F">Interested?</h2>

<p>We are looking for someone to join us in the Gent, Belgium office of Clarabridge, located at Grauwpoort 1, 9000 Gent.</p>

<p>Does this seem like a fun challenge for you? Please reach out to <a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#105;l&#x74;&#x6f;&#58;&#106;&#x75;&#x72;&#114;&#105;a&#x61;&#110;&#46;p&#x65;&#x72;&#115;&#121;&#x6e;&#x40;&#99;&#108;a&#x72;&#x61;&#98;&#114;&#x69;&#x64;&#103;&#101;&#x2e;&#x63;&#111;&#109;">jurriaan.persyn@clarabridge.com</a> with your details, and the requirements for your internship, and we’ll be in touch!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tips For Distraction-Free Programming]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2018/04/09/some-tips-for-distraction-free-programming"/>
            <updated>2018-04-09T17:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2018/04/09/some-tips-for-distraction-free-programming</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm very easily distracted. The slightest movement or conversation in the room takes my focus right away, not to mention the endless stream of information and notifications that e.g. services like Slack (team chat) and e-mail generate. I might be working on something with a colleague or on my own, when a simple notification pops in. My brain glitches for a moment while I process the notification and get back to where I was, but it's enough to completely lose focus. When pair programming with someone that isn't easily distracted, it's mostly fixed in an instant by getting back to the conversation or repeating the last question, but it's a lot more difficult when working on a feature alone. Over time I tried to change a few things to make this kind of interruptions less frequent or pervasive. Let's check some out:</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%8F%9D-environment">🏝 Environment</h2>

<p>The room I'm working in has a huge impact on my concentration levels. People talking or walking around are direct hits, as is any movement in my surroundings, even behind me. This is mostly fixed in our case since we don't have an open floor plan, so we don't share rooms with other teams, and when it's noisy in the room next to ours, we can just close the door. To prevent people talking from disrupting my concentration and the other way around, I'll put on headphones when working alone (mostly to prevent myself from listening in on the conversation), and I'll move to another room when pair programming. I know it sounds antisocial and makes me less approachable for questions or consultation, but I try to only do this when there's noise.</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%93%B1-phone-%26-social-media">📱 Phone &amp; Social Media</h2>

<p>My phone is out of sight. When I get a message I will read it when I find the time. When someone calls me I mostly take the call. It might sound strange because we're a social media company, but I'm not logged in to any of my personal social media accounts during the day. This really helps me concentrate, because my Twitter timeline is a real timesink for me. If I'm looking at that, I'm certainly not concentrating 😏. For testing stuff, I'll aways use test accounts.</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%96%A5-full-screen-applications">🖥 Full Screen Applications</h2>

<p>Although I don't like Full Screen Applications, I started using them more and more. They hide anything that might be happening in other windows, covering unwanted distractions up until you switch to the other application. I still don't like the oversight that is taken away by using an app in Full Screen mode though. The cool thing for me specifically is that iTerm behaves a bit like a tiling window manager for me, since I do most of my development in Vim &amp; the terminal, using iTerm splits. A great tip there is that you can use <code>Cmd + Shift + Enter</code> in an iTerm split to make it appear Full Screen temporarily.</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%9B%8E-osx-notification-center">🛎 OSX Notification center</h2>

<p><img src="/images/2018-04-09-some-tips-for-distraction-free-programming/1.png" alt="do not disturb" /></p>

<p>I already hinted at it earlier on, but notifications of any kind really disturb me. They pop over any fullscreen application that might be open, and I really can't help looking at them. This is why I set the <code>DO NOT DISTURB</code> mode on during workdays. You can configure Mac OSX to enable it by default during work hours, or you can do it manually when you notice being distracted. Notifications I get are mostly from Slack, Calendar and Mail. You can also configure this on a per-application basis in your System Preferences.</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%8E%88-osx-application-badges">🎈 OSX Application Badges</h2>

<p><img src="/images/2018-04-09-some-tips-for-distraction-free-programming/2.png" alt="dock icons with badges" /></p>

<p>What's really annoying me is that Mac OS displays so-called "badges" -the red circle icons with a number in them- on applications that received notifications, and these badges are visible in the Dock and the Application Switcher (<code>Cmd + Tab</code>). When I'm switching to my browser, I don't want to see how many Slack messages I missed. I'll check those later. I just went to Notification Center in System Preferences and disabled these badges for Slack, Calendar and Mail. I believe that I can be more productive when I read these things periodically instead of during other tasks. In the screenshot above, I enabled them temporarily for Calendar to show you what I mean, but what you can't see is that I have 25+ unread messages in Slack. Don't worry, I'll read them after I get this blogpost out! 😉</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%93%A2-slack">📢 Slack</h2>

<p>Some great things to do in Slack are to Leave channels you don't use, and to use the Mute 🔇 functionality on channels that are not urgent but you can't really leave. Of course, I disabled Slack's notification sounds by default.</p>

<p>I hope these tips were helpful, they certainly help me concentrate a bit better. If you think of anything else, comment below, I want to hear it! Happy pair programming!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Our Favorite Content Of 2017]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/12/22/our-favorite-content-of-2017"/>
            <updated>2017-12-22T14:30:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/12/22/our-favorite-content-of-2017</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a team, we consume A LOT of blog posts, YouTube videos, podcasts, and tweets about software development and related topics each year. We asked everyone in the team to share their favorite stuff that they found online, so that you can read it too. Here we go!</p>

<h1 id="people-%26-community">People &amp; Community</h1>

<p><img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/pTY9EtkiakcU/giphy.gif" alt="The Blind" /></p>

<h3 id="in-the-kingdom-of-the-blind"><a href="https://bridgetkromhout.com/blog/in-the-kingdom-of-the-blind/">In The Kingdom Of The Blind</a></h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>As you can imagine, there are plenty of reasons that under-represented people in tech aren't going to jump the second your event's CFP opens. But submissions will pour in nonetheless... from the folks whose (devrel/marketing/field engineer) vendor job includes public speaking (and on-the-job time to fine-tune their abstracts). And spoiler alert, many of them will fall into the majority cis het white male demographic.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Ursula recommends this for the great ideas on how to improve diversity at conferences, and an excellent candid overview of the reasons why underrepresented minorities do not speak at or attend tech conferences as often.</p>

<h3 id="we-fired-our-top-talent.-best-decision-we-ever-made."><a href="https://medium.freecodecamp.org/we-fired-our-top-talent-best-decision-we-ever-made-4c0a99728fde">We fired our top talent. Best decision we ever made.</a></h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>Your team's strength is not a function of the talent of individual members. It's a function of their collaboration, tenacity, and mutual respect.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hans likes this because when there's a smart guy around, you'll find it tempting to just go ask him instead of trying to do the research yourself and learn something new. He doesn't like developers who think that they know everything. They don't. In fact, you'll never know everything. Sharing knowledge and working together as a team is something we should focus on instead. Each person has their own strengths.</p>

<h3 id="the-myth-of-the-%22cool-tech-girl%22"><a href="https://code.likeagirl.io/the-myth-of-the-cool-tech-girl-7868fa63769b">The myth of the "cool tech girl"</a></h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>Don't reward good behaviour with scotch, don't tap kegs at 12pm, and don't host video game or ping pong tournaments. Don't call your employees "rockstars". Shine a harsh light on some of your internal slack channels. If your company doesn't perpetuate the kind of culture that makes women feel like they need to be 'one of the boys', they won't need the coping mechanism of the "cool tech girl".</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Ursula has seen this type of behaviour from women in tech in many countries. "I would almost go as far as to say that if you don't fit into the 'cool tech girl' box, it's difficult to survive. As a woman in tech I think you have a responsibility to speak up for diversity in the industry. It's really hard, and it's great to hear viewpoints that identify that."</p>

<h1 id="engineering">Engineering</h1>

<p><img src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/C3G2KYAWYAEj9km.jpg" alt="Stickies on the wall kind of engineering" /></p>

<h3 id="transactions-redefined"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NqKNqIsB8_k">Transactions Redefined</a></h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>Event Storming is my pizza, you can add your toppings, as long as it's not database tables or pineapple</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Toon recommends this because Alberto Brandolini is a great speaker, and his vision on Domain Driven Design and software development in general is really clear and deep. He goes a long way to understand the business, and the problems associated with the business. He goes out of his way to find out how he can solve them.</p>

<h3 id="modern-software-over-engineering-mistakes"><a href="https://medium.com/@rdsubhas/10-modern-software-engineering-mistakes-bc67fbef4fc8">Modern Software Over-Engineering Mistakes</a></h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>Duplication is better than the wrong abstraction</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Jurriaan likes this because too much of technical literature is about how you should start doing things, and how everything you’ve done in the past is probably wrong. This article captures the essence of trying to architect real-life development projects.</p>

<h3 id="kubernetes-at-github"><a href="https://githubengineering.com/kubernetes-at-github/">Kubernetes at Github</a></h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>With a self-service application provisioning workflow in place, SRE can devote more of our time to delivering infrastructure products to the rest of the engineering organisation in support of our best practices, building toward a faster and more resilient GitHub experience for everyone.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Jeffry liked this because everybody and their dog are rethinking how to do platform now that the technology to do so has matured. This write-up from Github offers a great look into the decision making and preparation that goes into gradually building up confidence. He gives the author additional points for sprinkling snippets of inspiration throughout the post: e.g. chatops-rpc to make our hubot do more than offer drunk commentary, Kelsey Hightower's "Kubernetes the hard way" which he has set his mind to working through over the holidays, flipper and mission control bar and simulating kernel panics with sysrq-trigger.</p>

<h1 id="think-differently">Think Differently</h1>

<p><img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/ximCDHoBlx4UU/giphy.gif" alt="Excel on mobile, epic experience" /></p>

<h3 id="exploring-time"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Zm95cYAtAa8">Exploring Time</a></h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s impossible to know if this talk started on time</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Toon recommends this because Eric Evans uses his own Domain Driven Design to explore better ways to think about time. Very inspiring. He shows how "generic" subdomains of software development are not generally "solved problems", and how you can make a difference there, as a programmer.</p>

<h3 id="clojure-for-the-brave-and-true"><a href="https://www.braveclojure.com/clojure-for-the-brave-and-true/">Clojure for the Brave and True</a></h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>Humor has a certain relationship to seriousness. It is appropriate to joke about serious things, but only after the right amount of time has passed. For example, it took years for me to be able to crack a smile when I remember my favorite uncle’s last words: "Hold my beer".</p>
  
  <p>I'm so proud of you, little teapot. You've run your first Clojure program! Not only that, but you've become acquainted with the REPL, one of the most important tools for developing Clojure software. Amazing!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Niek thinks this book is a hilarious and down-to-earth explanation of yet another programming language to learn. Clojure is a Lisp dialect and will melt your brain with its elegance!</p>

<h3 id="you-suck-at-excel"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0nbkaYsR94c">You Suck At Excel</a></h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>This material is -I guess- kinda like basic to intermediate, but for you all it's going to be stupid hard, so try paying attention and don't slow me down.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Toon enjoyed this because this guy solves real world problems for people using Excel. "I learned a 100 things from seeing him work like this." He knows Excel inside out.</p>

<h3 id="lemme-tell-you-about-the-most-successful-program-i-ever-wrote"><a href="https://twitter.com/revin/status/940700486117634050">Lemme tell you about the most successful program I ever wrote</a></h3>

<h6 id="twitter-thread">(twitter thread)</h6>

<blockquote>
  <p>It was the first time I genuinely understood that users don't care how something is implemented; they care how it makes them feel</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hans thinks we put so much effort in making our application code clean and future-proof while just a tiny poorly written program (that works) can make someone really happy. Software can seem magical for some people.</p>

<h1 id="big-data">Big Data</h1>

<p><img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/xydGi3nSTlkqs/giphy.gif" alt="Ben Stiller as Big Data" /></p>

<h3 id="wat-als-tomorrowland-alles-met-je-data-en-privacy-zou-mogen-doen%3F"><a href="https://medium.com/@ransbottyn/wat-als-tomorrowland-alles-met-je-data-en-privacy-zou-mogen-doen-e25a703668b4">Wat als Tomorrowland alles met je data en privacy zou mogen doen?</a></h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>Zo'n bracelet (gelinkt aan je identiteitsbewijs trouwens) is dus een mes dat aan twee kanten snijdt: handig, maar misschien ook de reden waarom u de volgende keer net iets minder "gewenst" bent.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Jasper likes this because it's incredible how much data a festival organizer track and save about you with just a bracelet, and also, what they (can possibly) do with it.</p>

<h3 id="deep-learning-for-chatbots"><a href="http://www.wildml.com/2016/07/deep-learning-for-chatbots-2-retrieval-based-model-tensorflow/">Deep Learning for Chatbots</a></h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>Generative models are an active area of research, but we’re not quite there yet. If you want to build a conversational agent today your best bet is most likely a retrieval-based model.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Niek checked this out because it was exactly the right content for his reply suggestions adventure, a feature he is working on for CX Social.</p>

<p>Those were our highlights for 2017, let us know if we missed something!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>