<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Clarabridge Engage Dev Blog]]></title>
    <link href="/blog/tags/Performance.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
    <updated>2019-10-02T12:26:43+00:00</updated>
    <id>/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[When too many API calls are breaking your app]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/11/02/javascript-deferred"/>
            <updated>2017-11-02T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/11/02/javascript-deferred</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, I was confronted with a strange issue regarding the "followers" component we have in our inbox.
It's a cool feature that gives you the possibility to check which connected Twitter account is following or followed by another Twitter account. Most accounts or users don't have that many connected Twitter profiles but of course there are always some exceptions. One of our customers had more than 100 connected profiles. The process to check the relationship between the profiles is rather easy. We do a call to the back-end for every profile. In the back-end we do an API call to Twitter to fetch the relationship details. So you can imagine it takes some time if we have to do this for many profiles. In the front-end the component became very slow and it looked like the component crashed.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2017-11-02-javascript-deferred/followers.png" alt="CX Social followers dropdown in inbox" /></p>

<p>After finding out what the problem is, the next step is of course solving it. I started with checking the back-end for some improvements. Instead of calling Twitter's API for every single profile, I checked if we could ask for multiple relations at once. Sadly this wasn't the case. So this trail was a dead end.</p>

<p>If we can't change the API, we could try to avoid using the API as much as possible. By caching the result for some time, we could avoid requesting the same data multiple times as this also improves speed. This wasn't a good option either because the received data was already cached by us in the back-end.</p>

<p>The only thing I could still think of was trying to reduce the calls to the Twitter API or to our own API. Changing the back-end would be a lot of work because the endpoint is used in a lot of places in the front-end. So the only option I wanted to consider was making a change in the one place where we had the problem. In the inbox we loop over the profiles and do a seperate call for every profile. For every call to our API, we wait until we have the response before doing a new call. So instead of doing synchronous calls, we should consider doing the calls asynchronously.</p>

<p>Not knowing if this was possible in Javascript, I started searching and fell upon the <code>Promise</code> object, which does exactly what we need. However, <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/Promise">the documentation for Promise on MDN</a> quickly revealed that it's not supported by some browsers we still have to support. After some more digging around the internet, we stumbled upon the <code>Deferred</code> object in jQuery which does almost the same, and works in most browsers. From its documentation:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It can register multiple callbacks into callback queues, invoke callback queues, and relay the success or failure state of any synchronous or asynchronous function</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So what we actually have to do is start all the calls to the back-end at once. Once we did that we create a new <code>Deferred</code> object. When all the <code>combinedCalls</code> are done, we can start updating our component. It only has to do one big update and it doesn't take that much time because the calls are all fired at the same time instead of one by one.</p>

<pre><code class="js">var profileIds = this.profileIds;

var calls = _.map(services, function (service) {
    var url = '/twitter/relation?accounts='+ service.id +'&amp;users=' + profileIds;

    return $.get(url);
});

var combinedResult = $.Deferred();

var combinedCalls = $.when.apply($, calls);

combinedCalls.done(function() {

    var resultsOfDefferedAjaxCalls = _.toArray(arguments).slice(0, calls.length);

    var relations = _.map(resultsOfDefferedAjaxCalls, function(ajaxResult) {
        return ajaxResult.result.data;
    });

    combinedResult.resolve(relations);
});

combinedCalls.fail(function() {
    // Combine args so that we can pass reason for
    // failure to reject()
    combinedResult.reject();
});

return combinedResult.promise();
</code></pre>

<p>So with some small changes we improved a lot on the loading time of the dropdown. The next problem was that some calls could take some time and if there is one slow call, all the other calls have to wait till the slowest call is finished. So I had to find another solution for this new problem. So instead of just calling the endpoint I added a callback function to the call.</p>

<pre><code class="js">var calls = _.map(services, function (service) {
    var url = '/twitter/relation?accounts='+ service.id +'&amp;users=' + profileIds;

    var onGoingCall = $.get(url);

    onGoingCall.done(callback);

    return onGoingCall;
});
</code></pre>

<p>The moment the call is finished, the callback is triggered and the component will update. You don't have to worry about slow calls because the component will update as soon as possible and the customer can see that data is loading and updating.</p>

<p>That's how we fixed this for now, hopefully we can move to the more modern approach of using <code>Promise</code> in the near future!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[How We Handle Perceived Performance]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/07/10/perceived-performance"/>
            <updated>2017-07-10T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/07/10/perceived-performance</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-is-perceived-performance%3F">What is perceived performance?</h2>

<p>Perceived performance refers to how fast a user thinks your site is, rather than the actual site speed. It's a metric measured by humans rather than a site speed test tool. How fast does the website feel? For example, Facebook appears faster by loading a placeholder for posts in the News Feed. It's useful to know that a site is only loading rather than functioning slowly.</p>

<h2 id="how-cx-social-handles-perceived-performance">How CX Social Handles Perceived Performance</h2>

<p>CX Social is a large application that has a complex interface. The "inbox" part of our system has multiple small features, that all appear to be on a single page. The perceived performance of the inbox is more important than the actual speed, especially because it provides a seamless user experience. The following are a few things we do to portray a speedier performance!</p>

<h2 id="when-a-mention-is-resolved">When a mention is resolved</h2>

<p>In CX Social we process small pieces of information we call "mentions". A mention is any blog post, news article, tweet, etc. that matches any of your specified criteria. All mentions are refined into the CX Social inbox, where support agents can mark them as <em>resolved</em> when they are replied to/labelled as no action needed, etc. When a mention is <em>resolved</em> the support agent is automatically shown the next <em>mention</em> to attend to.
When a mention is resolved we manipulate the DOM and remove the element <em>before</em> the request is completed successfully. This gives you the impression that your action is completed instantly. In the rare case that the request fails, we replace the DOM element and display a relevant error message, so that the user knows what's going on and can resolve the mention again.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-07-10-perceived-performance/mentionresolve.gif" alt="Resolving a mention in CX Social Inbox" /><br />
<small>Resolving a mention in CX Social Inbox</small>
</center></p>

<h2 id="loading-indicators">Loading Indicators</h2>

<p>Loading icons can become a bit annoying on snappy pages because you see a flickering behaviour, and it makes the user feel as though they have to unnecessarily <em>wait</em>. Snappy pages don't require a loading icon, but we'd like a back up plan in case the page takes longer than expected to load. In this case, we use a timeout function for the loading functionality, and only show the loading interface when the request takes over X milliseconds to complete.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-07-10-perceived-performance/delayloading.gif" alt="Delay loading" /><br />
<small>Don't show a loading indicator for quick requests</small>
</center></p>

<p>In this instance, there's a 3000 millisecond delay on the loading behaviour for this page.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-07-10-perceived-performance/delayloadingspinner.gif" alt="Delay loading" /><br />
<small>Do show a loading indicator when a request is taking longer than usual</small>
</center></p>

<h2 id="placeholder-mentions-in-inbox">Placeholder mentions in inbox</h2>

<p>Similar to how Facebook shows a preview of your feed by showing mini placeholders for each post, we show a placeholder when loading a list of mentions in CX Social. 
We immediately show the selected mention, but for other mentions in the thread we automatically show a mention placeholder while they're loading. Then when the user scrolls farther in the thread, we pop in the next mentions. This gives structure to the page, while data is loading and thus makes it easier for the eye/mind to prepare for that data to be there.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-07-10-perceived-performance/inboxloading.gif" alt="Loading of inbox" /><br />
<small>Placeholder sections for mentions in the CX Social inbox</small>
</center></p>

<h2 id="additional-information-in-dropdowns%2Fpopups">Additional information in dropdowns/popups</h2>

<p>When you display a popup or dropdown there's no need to fetch every piece of information immediately. On each Twitter mention we have a "following" dropdown which shows the list of profiles that is following the author of the mention. It also shows whether you are following <em>that</em> profile and if <em>that</em> profile is following <em>you</em>. However we only load the latter information when the dropdown is opened. Sometimes we hit Twitter rate limits, and still try to display relevant following info based on our cache. If we don't have any info, we will still show the dropdown with ability to follow someone (but without displaying who they're already following) since those two endpoints have separate rate limits.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-07-10-perceived-performance/twitterfollowers.gif" alt="Loading of Twitter Followers" /><br />
<small>Dropdown that shows if you are following the author of a mention and vice versa</small>
</center></p>

<h2 id="loading-new-content-without-a-page-reload">Loading new content without a page reload</h2>

<p>We have a large sidebar in CX Social for navigation, as well as a top menu bar. When switching between pages, we just request the content for the main part of the page, and insert the new main content. This saves us doing a full page load.</p>

<h2 id="wrapping-up">Wrapping up</h2>

<p>Have you implemented any features to improve perceived performance? We'd love to hear about it!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>