<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Clarabridge Engage Dev Blog]]></title>
    <link href="/blog/tags/UX.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
    <updated>2020-10-05T12:57:25+00:00</updated>
    <id>/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Async Publishing: Making Clients Feel Like They Don’t Have To Wait]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2018/04/20/async-publishing"/>
            <updated>2018-04-20T10:30:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2018/04/20/async-publishing</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few months ago, we were asked whether it was possible to publish posts to hundreds of Facebook Pages at the same time. This use case is not something we had foreseen, the client just has <em>A LOT</em> of owned profiles; one social profile per physical location that they're in. They wanted to be able to share promotions to those locations (i.e. happy-hour promotions for participating bars).
Of course we can make that happen. It's an important part of our product. Ammm, right?</p>

<h2 id="shaking-the-walls">Shaking the walls</h2>

<p>How can we facilitate this use case, and at the same time make sure this feature is used for genuine, valuable communication?</p>

<p>Posting the exact same message a thousand times will likely trigger spam detection algorithms of certain social networks we support. And e.g. Twitter specifically changed their rules about posting, reposting and retweeting the exact messages on multiple profiles (read <a href="https://blog.twitter.com/developer/en_us/topics/tips/2018/automation-and-the-use-of-multiple-accounts.html">the blogpost</a>). Because Twitter allows you to reach out to others by @mentioning them, this behavior is certainly not desirable on their platform, and we don't allow to post the same content to several profiles at once.
For Facebook however, the re-posting is limited to owned, authorized place pages, so the use case is genuine.</p>

<h2 id="what-we-had-...">What we had ...</h2>

<p>The first thing we were worried about was: "What breaks if we would do this with our current implementation?" After a quick experiment, the answer seemed to be <em>nothing</em>; we just needed patience, a lot of patience. And as a user, the only UI feedback you got while a post got published to your 100 pages was a loading icon, for several minutes.</p>

<p>In fact, we're just looping the list of profiles.
And in that loop, we're doing API calls for each profile.</p>

<p>For 99% of our users, this was good enough and it works like a charm. But with this new use case, our UX had to improve.</p>

<h2 id="life-is-more-than-a-loading-icon">Life is more than a loading icon</h2>

<p>Asking our hamster to run a little faster was not possible. We had to think about another solution in the backend.</p>

<p>We came up with an <code>In progress</code> section in our tool. When a user wants to publish to more than 10 profiles, the post goes into this section.
What changed in the backend? We still loop all the profiles, but we create tasks for each profile and put them on a queue.
That queue will be processed asynchronously, in the background.</p>

<p>Our users can do other tasks in our tool while the post is publishing to all those profiles, and users can follow along in the section <code>In progress</code>.</p>

<p>What I really like about that new section, is that you see the publishing status of every profile.
You have 3 statuses:
- In progress
- Successful
- Failed</p>

<p><code>In progress</code> and <code>Successful</code> are quite obvious. If publishing on a single profile failed, we see the reason why it failed and there's an option to retry posting on that profile.
The <code>Retry</code> button is also a timesaver because you don't have to create the same post with only the failed profiles.</p>

<p>Every time we get a result from the API call, we update the status of the current profile. The user interface is updated in real time so from a user's standpoint, the progress is clearly visible.</p>

<p>The user knows the status of every single profile. This makes the user feel in control of all of the profile actions.
Before we did this change, the user only saw a loading icon. Now, they receive an estimation for when the publishing will be completed.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2018-04-20-async-publishing/async-posting.png" alt="In progress section in publisher" /></p>

<p>The impact that this small improvement has, really makes a big difference. It feels snappy, you can just go on with your work while your 100+ profiles are updated, you don't feel held back by the user interface.</p>

<p>Have you done something like this? Feel free to comment below!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tips on coding a web design close to reality]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/10/16/coding-web-design-tips"/>
            <updated>2017-10-16T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/10/16/coding-web-design-tips</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout my experience as a front end developer I've often heard designers complain about how developers fail to code a design accurately. Many designers ask their developers to make a webpage "pixel perfect". Queue developers rolling their eyes! Here I'll share my tips for bringing your code as close as possible to that psd.</p>

<h2 id="setting-expectations">Setting expectations</h2>

<p>One of the most impactful changes you can do is to make sure to set expectations with your designer. At the start it's a good idea to get your team together and figure out which parts of the design will or will not work in reality. If you're lucky you'll have an amazing product team that has done this for you. In reality the developer usually comes up with a technical pain point in the design. For example, if you find that some of the design won't translate in all browsers, you could come up with a compromise with your designer. For example, our gallery of canned responses uses a masonry layout. This layout doesn't look as perfect in Internet Explorer, but we were willing to put up with this because it meant we could use CSS for the masonry layout and not require to use a heavy JavaScript polyfill plugin. This slight compromise means our website will not have to forsake any page speed for the design.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-10-16-coding-web-design-tips/canned-responses-gallery-modern.png" alt="Canned responses gallery view in a modern browser" /><br />
<small>Clarabrige Engage Inbox canned responses gallery view in a modern browser</small>
</center></p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-10-16-coding-web-design-tips/canned-responses-gallery-ie.png" alt="Canned responses gallery view in a Internet Explorer" /><br />
<small>Clarabrige Engage Inbox canned responses gallery view in Internet Explorer 10</small>
</center></p>

<p>Ideally you only use JavaScript when absolutely nescessary for a design. I've seen it happen before that designers have asked for a <code>&lt;select&gt;</code> dropdown list of <code>&lt;option&gt;</code>'s to be styled, as the default is not as pretty as in other browsers. This requires a JavaScript plugin (I wrote one to do this myself at one point). But it's completely unnecessary when it does not affect the user experience that deeply. Users are used to the style of the default option list and it's not worth adding the extra JavaScript to your website. It's important to weigh up where your JavaScript is <em>really</em> enhancing the user experience. A slower website makes for a less smooth user experience!</p>

<h2 id="useful-plugins">Useful Plugins</h2>

<p>Let's check out some plugins that can come in handy to keep you and your designer happy!</p>

<h3 id="pixel-perfect">Pixel Perfect</h3>

<p>Designers love when I use <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/pixel-perfect/">this plugin</a>! You can pop in your design image and then overlay it on top of your webpage. Then you can use the inspector to adjust margins and padding in between elements.</p>

<p>My main advice when using this plugin is to be careful about fonts. Use the plugin to measure the distance <em>between</em> elements rather than making the entire page a perfect copy of the PSD. This is because the font in a PSD will not look the same in every browser. The most important part is getting the line height, margins and padding correct between the text and the next element. In this example you can see that the "Canned Responses" title is not the exact same in the PSD layover.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-10-16-coding-web-design-tips/canned-responses-pixel-perfect.png" alt="Using the pixel perfect plugin" /><br />
<small>Using the pixel perfect plugin</small>
</center></p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-10-16-coding-web-design-tips/canned-responses-pixel-perfect-inspector.png" alt="Using the pixel perfect plugin with the inspector" /><br />
<small>Using the pixel perfect plugin and adjusting padding to match the overlay mockup</small>
</center></p>

<h3 id="ruler-plugin">Ruler plugin</h3>

<p>A good <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/page-ruler/">ruler plugin</a> is great for when you want to maintain a consistent guttering/spacing between elements in your design. It also prevents arguments with the designer over whether some spacing is 15px or 20px ;)</p>

<p>Usually spacing between elements is consistent in the design - so if you do spot an inconsistency, ask your designer. E.g. If your webpage <code>h1</code> headings are normally 16px, but in the design they are 15px, this could be a slight mistake!</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-10-16-coding-web-design-tips/using-the-ruler-plugin.png" alt="Using the ruler plugin" /><br />
<small>Using a ruler plugin to maintain consistent spacing</small>
</center></p>

<h2 id="useful-software">Useful software</h2>

<h3 id="zeplin">Zeplin</h3>

<p><a href="https://zeplin.io/">Zeplin</a> is a program that acts as a middleman between developers and designers. The designer can input the font sizes, spacing between elements and content for the developer to copy. This prevents the developer having to guess the dimensions of the design. It also generates a little bit of CSS - although in my experience you don't end up using most of that. Some CSS properties like <code>box-shadow</code> are useful. It's also useful for translating hex colours.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-10-16-coding-web-design-tips/spacing-between-elements-in-zeplin.png" alt="Examining the spacing between elements in Zeplin" /><br />
<small>Examining the spacing between elements in Zeplin</small>
</center></p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-10-16-coding-web-design-tips/font-details-in-zeplin.png" alt="Examining font details in Zeplin" /><br />
<small>Examining font details in Zeplin</small>
</center></p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-10-16-coding-web-design-tips/css-rules-in-zeplin.png" alt="Examining CSS rules in Zeplin" /><br />
<small>Examining CSS rules in Zeplin</small>
</center></p>

<h3 id="invision">Invision</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.invisionapp.com/">Invision</a> is an alternative to Zeplin, but it also includes project mockups. The inspector tool is very similar to Zeplin, so it depends on if you need software for your mockups in addition to software for being the "middleman" between developers and designers.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-10-16-coding-web-design-tips/using-invision-inspector.png" alt="Using the inspector in Invision" /><br />
<small>Using the inspector in Invision</small>
</center></p>

<h3 id="using-the-browser-inspector">Using the browser inspector</h3>

<p>This is the most important tool of course! Using the up and down keys in the CSS rules section you can tweak the width of elements until you get it right. Editing the styles in the inspector is where I spend most of my time when coding a design.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-10-16-coding-web-design-tips/using-the-inspector.png" alt="Using the browser inspector" /><br />
<small>Using the browser inspector</small>
</center></p>

<p>Utilize the device toolbar to get a preview of your site in other devices. When you're working on compatibility for Internet Explorer, I recommend utilizing the inspector on IE11 (or the latest IE version) as it will give you a preview back to IE8. The inspector in IE11 for compatibility mode gives you a pretty good idea of what something looks like in older versions. When you've done enough tweaking using the compatibility mode you can double check the <em>real</em> IE browser in a tool like <a href="https://www.browserstack.com/" target="_blank">Browserstack</a>. If you don't have BrowserStack you can <a href="https://developer.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-edge/tools/vms/" target="_blank">download a VM on modern.ie</a>.</p>

<h2 id="always-account-for-responsiveness">Always account for responsiveness</h2>

<p>It's likely your designer will give you a separate spec for the mobile version of your webpage. If they don't, you can ask them if they'd like you to improvise one. But whether you have a mockup for mobile or not, you should always write your code to be responsive. Responsive design is a whole other article, but <a href="https://www.w3schools.com/css/css_rwd_intro.asp" target="_blank">I recommend reading up on it</a>!</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>As a frontend developer you need to work amicably with your designer to find the best technical solutions when implementing a design. Graceful degredation and user experience are the most important, but hopefully these tips also help you to come to a solution that works well for both the designer and the developer!</p>

<p>What developer tools do you use to help you implement designs?</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[How We Handle Perceived Performance]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/07/10/perceived-performance"/>
            <updated>2017-07-10T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/07/10/perceived-performance</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-is-perceived-performance%3F">What is perceived performance?</h2>

<p>Perceived performance refers to how fast a user thinks your site is, rather than the actual site speed. It's a metric measured by humans rather than a site speed test tool. How fast does the website feel? For example, Facebook appears faster by loading a placeholder for posts in the News Feed. It's useful to know that a site is only loading rather than functioning slowly.</p>

<h2 id="how-clarabrige-engage-handles-perceived-performance">How Clarabrige Engage Handles Perceived Performance</h2>

<p>Clarabrige Engage is a large application that has a complex interface. The "inbox" part of our system has multiple small features, that all appear to be on a single page. The perceived performance of the inbox is more important than the actual speed, especially because it provides a seamless user experience. The following are a few things we do to portray a speedier performance!</p>

<h2 id="when-a-mention-is-resolved">When a mention is resolved</h2>

<p>In Clarabrige Engage we process small pieces of information we call "mentions". A mention is any blog post, news article, tweet, etc. that matches any of your specified criteria. All mentions are refined into the Clarabrige Engage inbox, where support agents can mark them as <em>resolved</em> when they are replied to/labelled as no action needed, etc. When a mention is <em>resolved</em> the support agent is automatically shown the next <em>mention</em> to attend to.
When a mention is resolved we manipulate the DOM and remove the element <em>before</em> the request is completed successfully. This gives you the impression that your action is completed instantly. In the rare case that the request fails, we replace the DOM element and display a relevant error message, so that the user knows what's going on and can resolve the mention again.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-07-10-perceived-performance/mentionresolve.gif" alt="Resolving a mention in Clarabrige Engage Inbox" /><br />
<small>Resolving a mention in Clarabrige Engage Inbox</small>
</center></p>

<h2 id="loading-indicators">Loading Indicators</h2>

<p>Loading icons can become a bit annoying on snappy pages because you see a flickering behaviour, and it makes the user feel as though they have to unnecessarily <em>wait</em>. Snappy pages don't require a loading icon, but we'd like a back up plan in case the page takes longer than expected to load. In this case, we use a timeout function for the loading functionality, and only show the loading interface when the request takes over X milliseconds to complete.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-07-10-perceived-performance/delayloading.gif" alt="Delay loading" /><br />
<small>Don't show a loading indicator for quick requests</small>
</center></p>

<p>In this instance, there's a 3000 millisecond delay on the loading behaviour for this page.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-07-10-perceived-performance/delayloadingspinner.gif" alt="Delay loading" /><br />
<small>Do show a loading indicator when a request is taking longer than usual</small>
</center></p>

<h2 id="placeholder-mentions-in-inbox">Placeholder mentions in inbox</h2>

<p>Similar to how Facebook shows a preview of your feed by showing mini placeholders for each post, we show a placeholder when loading a list of mentions in Clarabrige Engage. 
We immediately show the selected mention, but for other mentions in the thread we automatically show a mention placeholder while they're loading. Then when the user scrolls farther in the thread, we pop in the next mentions. This gives structure to the page, while data is loading and thus makes it easier for the eye/mind to prepare for that data to be there.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-07-10-perceived-performance/inboxloading.gif" alt="Loading of inbox" /><br />
<small>Placeholder sections for mentions in the Clarabrige Engage inbox</small>
</center></p>

<h2 id="additional-information-in-dropdowns%2Fpopups">Additional information in dropdowns/popups</h2>

<p>When you display a popup or dropdown there's no need to fetch every piece of information immediately. On each Twitter mention we have a "following" dropdown which shows the list of profiles that is following the author of the mention. It also shows whether you are following <em>that</em> profile and if <em>that</em> profile is following <em>you</em>. However we only load the latter information when the dropdown is opened. Sometimes we hit Twitter rate limits, and still try to display relevant following info based on our cache. If we don't have any info, we will still show the dropdown with ability to follow someone (but without displaying who they're already following) since those two endpoints have separate rate limits.</p>

<p><center>
<img src="/images/2017-07-10-perceived-performance/twitterfollowers.gif" alt="Loading of Twitter Followers" /><br />
<small>Dropdown that shows if you are following the author of a mention and vice versa</small>
</center></p>

<h2 id="loading-new-content-without-a-page-reload">Loading new content without a page reload</h2>

<p>We have a large sidebar in Clarabrige Engage for navigation, as well as a top menu bar. When switching between pages, we just request the content for the main part of the page, and insert the new main content. This saves us doing a full page load.</p>

<h2 id="wrapping-up">Wrapping up</h2>

<p>Have you implemented any features to improve perceived performance? We'd love to hear about it!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>