<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[CX Social Dev Blog]]></title>
    <link href="/blog/tags/Xinetd.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-08T09:12:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[On the fly API&#039;s using Xinetd]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2018/01/08/xinetd-APIs"/>
            <updated>2018-01-08T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2018/01/08/xinetd-APIs</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As developers, we often rely on exposing services in our software as an HTTP
API. Traditionally, our code would be executed from within a webserver
container. For example, PHP apps might run in
<a href="https://httpd.apache.org/">Apache</a>, or Java apps might run in
<a href="https://tomcat.apache.org/">Tomcat</a>.</p>

<p>In modern apps that strive to be self-contained, you might add a webserver
library and handle requests directly in your code instead.
<a href="http://www.tornadoweb.org">Tornado</a> for Python,
<a href="https://golang.org/pkg/net/http/">net/http</a> for Golang,
<a href="http://puma.io/">Puma</a> for Ruby or <a href="https://www.eclipse.org/jetty/">Jetty</a> for
JVM languages are examples of libraries for this.</p>

<p>Any of these options are typically fine, but sometimes you just want something
much, much simpler. Fortunately, it turns out Linux already comes with
everything you need. First, we need a problem to solve though.</p>

<p>At CX Social we deal with a lot of data. We need to do some maintenance work in
order to keep this data relevant and efficient. What we don't want is to
interfere with the processing we do for our users. We'd rather err on the side
of caution and only run these maintenance jobs when we are sure that servers
aren't currently experiencing high loads. One way to know is by looking at load
averages.</p>

<p>Let's build a simple HTTP API that tells us whether a server is currently busy
or not.</p>

<p>The tools we'll use here are <code>xinetd</code> and plain old <code>bash</code>. Xinetd is a
replacement for the original <code>inetd</code>. This is old software. The <a href="https://github.com/xinetd-org/xinetd">GitHub
mirror</a> of Xinetd has a history going 15
years back. It is simple: it lets you write a server program where you only
need to care about the output. All the other details, like networking, logging,
access control, are taken care of.</p>

<p>First, we'll have to install Xinetd which nowadays isn't installed by default:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">$ apt-get install xinetd  # on debian
$ pacman -S xinetd        # on arch
$ yum -y install xinetd   # on those other distros
</code></pre>

<p>Next, we'll need to do some configuration. I added following line to my
<code>/etc/services</code>:</p>

<pre><code>load_avg   9876/tcp
</code></pre>

<p>Then I added a file <code>/etc/xinet.d/load_avg</code> with the following contents:</p>

<pre><code>service load_avg
{
  flags = REUSE
  socket_type = stream
  protocol = tcp
  port = 9876
  wait = no
  user = nobody
  server = /data/load_avg
  log_on_failure += USERID
  disable = no
}
</code></pre>

<p>Some comments here. The <code>service load_avg</code> maps to what I added in
<code>/etc/services</code>, the <code>server = ...</code> will be the script that will be called when
a connection is made.</p>

<p>So, let's write the script itself. We'll be using plain bash. If the load
average is fine we'll return a <code>200 OK response</code>. If not, we'll return a <code>503
Service Unavailable</code> instead.</p>

<pre><code class="bash">#!/bin/bash

http_response() {
  local http_code="$1"
  local message="$2"

  local length=${#message}

  echo -en "${http_code}\r\n"
  echo -en "Content-Type: text/plain\r\n"
  echo -en "Content-Length: ${length}\r\n"
  echo -en "\r\n"
  echo -en "${message}"
  echo -en "\r\n"
}

http_200() {
  http_response "HTTP/1.1 200 OK" "200; $1"
}

http_503() {
  http_response "HTTP/1.1 503 Service Unavailable" "503; $1"
}

load_average=$(uptime | awk '{print $8 * 100}')
acceptable_load=$(nproc | awk '{print $1 * 100}')

if [ ${load_average} -gt ${acceptable_load} ]; then
  http_503 ${load_average}
else
  http_200 ${load_average}
fi
</code></pre>

<p>Let's break it up piece by piece. We start with a couple of functions that help
us construct a valid HTTP response. We can get the length of a value in bash
with <code>${#variable}</code> which is how we set the <code>length</code> variable. For the
rest, nothing particularly interesting is going on.</p>

<p>Next, we get the load average from the <code>uptime</code> command. Bash doesn't have good
support for float values so we get around that by multiplying with <code>100</code> which
lets us compare with <code>-gt</code> later on.</p>

<p>To calculate the acceptable load we cut some corners and simplify things a
little bit: <code>nproc</code> gives us the number of cores in the system so we use that
again multiplying by <code>100</code> so we can compare. So a <code>4</code> core machine would
accept a load of <code>4</code>. I don't love that solution but as an example it's good
enough. In a real setup you would add a little bit of extra margin.</p>

<p>After reloading Xinetd you can use any web client to access
<a href="http://hostname:9876">http://hostname:9876</a>.</p>

<h2 id="improvements">Improvements</h2>

<p>There are a couple of things we can do to improve upon this. We can extract the
<code>http_*</code> functions so we can easily source them as a library in other scripts.
We could render the response as JSON to make parsing the result neater on the
client side.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Often we really do require the capabilities of a full-blown development
environment to implement the features we need. In other situations we can get
away with a simple approach. Xinetd has been around for a very long time and
hides exactly the complexities we'd rather avoid having to deal with.</p>

<p>This technique can be used in interesting combinations. For example, you could
use it with <a href="http://www.haproxy.org/">HAProxy</a> health checks by using a
<code>httpchk</code> rather than a regular <code>tcp-check</code>. Say you have HAProxy in front of
an <a href="https://www.elastic.co/">Elasticsearch</a> cluster to automatically spread
searches. You could use our <code>load_avg</code> script above to exclude busy nodes
automatically.  Or say you have a MySQL setup with a handful of replicas for
reading and you use HAProxy to load balance these. You can write a simple
script that checks the <code>seconds_behind_master</code> value and excludes replicas that
are lagging.</p>

<p>Give it a try, see what you can come up with, and share your experiences in the
comment section below!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>