<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Clarabridge Engage Dev Blog]]></title>
    <link href="/blog/categories/JavaScript.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
    <updated>2020-10-05T12:39:05+00:00</updated>
    <id>/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[A tale of a small JavaScript bug]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2019/10/02/a-tale-of-a-small-javascript-bug"/>
            <updated>2019-10-02T14:30:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2019/10/02/a-tale-of-a-small-javascript-bug</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes it's assumed that the frontend is a relatively harmless place to be programming. We've been proven wrong once again.</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%94%A5%F0%9F%90%B6%E2%98%95%EF%B8%8F%F0%9F%94%A5-this-is-fine">🔥🐶☕️🔥 This is fine</h2>

<p><img src="/images/2019-10-02-a-tale-of-a-small-javascript-bug/this-is-fine.png" alt="This is fine" /></p>

<p>For a few months now, we have been seeing relatively high loads on our web servers. The loads varied from around 90% of the total CPU power available, to a bit over 100% in peak hours. We assumed that this was normal and that our product was just being used more (which it was), and that this was a natural burden on the load on our servers. The approach we were going to take was to continue scaling horizontally.</p>

<p>Two weeks ago however, we noticed huge daily load spikes (up to 1000% of our capacity) during peak hours. We got alert SMS'es of Redis that couldn't handle the amount of requests, and saw Kibana logs of very slow user requests to certain routes, effectively rendering our application unusable at times. It was "all hands on deck" immediately, and we started digging. Before we could find out what was happening it stopped again, and the load dropped to what we assumed was "normal load". We found, also using Kibana, that there was a huge amount of calls to our <code>/find</code> endpoint, and so we decided to implement a <a href="/blog/2017/05/02/sliding-window-rate-limiter-redis/">rate limiter</a> on those, to prevent our app from going down, and buy us some time to look for the actual issue. However, we couldn't see why that endpoint was hit so hard.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2019-10-02-a-tale-of-a-small-javascript-bug/kibana.png" alt="Kibana showing a lot of requests for one user in a short time frame" /></p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%90%9B%F0%9F%95%B5%EF%B8%8F%E2%80%8D%E2%99%82%EF%B8%8F--bug-hunting">🐛🕵️‍♂️  Bug Hunting</h2>

<p>A few days later, when we were hit with a huge amount of calls again (this time, they were ratelimited and not producing those huge loads on our servers, but we could see them in the logs and in Kibana), we noticed that most of them were coming from only a limited number of customers. We tried to work in our app as they would do, but couldn't reproduce it. After some time however, we noticed in the network tab of the browser we were working in, that the same call to the <code>/find</code> endpoint was done multiple times simultaneously! Bingo!</p>

<p>Or not Bingo? The code seemed to be fine: When we mount our inbox's react component, we use <code>Sonora.on(eventname, callback)</code> to bind a callback to a given websocket eventname (Sonora is an abstraction around <a href="https://socket.io/">socket.io</a>). When we unmount the react component again, we call <code>Sonora.off(eventname, callback)</code> to stop listening for those events. When such an event comes in, we would potentially need more info from the backend and a call to the <code>/find</code> endpoint is issued. It definitely looked like we didn't unregister the callbacks when unmounting that component, given how we saw multiple calls being made simultaneously in the console's network tab, whenever a websocket message came in.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2019-10-02-a-tale-of-a-small-javascript-bug/performance-tab.png" alt="Browser's performance tab showing lots of calls to the find endpoint" /></p>

<p>While everything was looking okay in the consuming code of the Sonora <code>.on()</code> and <code>.off()</code> methods, we concluded that something must've been wrong in the wrapper around socket.io itself. When looking inside the <code>.on()</code> method, we found out that there was a debugging statement added like this:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">const Sonora = {
    // ...

    on: (event, callback) =&gt; {
        socket.on(
            event,
            () =&gt; {
                console.log('some debugging here');

                callback.apply(this, arguments);
            }
        );
    }

    // ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, we wrapped the actual callback inside an anonymous function, and passed that on to Socket.io's <code>.on()</code> handler. Now, when calling <code>.off()</code>, we sent along the original callback which didn't match the wrapped one, and nothing was removed. Since it's possible to have multiple callbacks for each incoming event, this resulted in the same callback being added time after time and not being removed. So we had basically made all our clients do <em>loads</em> of unnecessary calls to <code>/find</code> by adding a debugging statement! And believe it or not, this debugging statement was there for a while! (Thanks git blame!)</p>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%94%A8%F0%9F%91%A9%E2%80%8D%F0%9F%94%A7-fixing-it">🔨👩‍🔧 Fixing it</h2>

<p>The fix was easy enough: don't add that anonymous function.</p>

<p>The load on our servers dropped immediately when we put that small change into production, and not only during peak hours. It seemed that we had been on a tipping point. A few more users online at any given time, a few more open tabs with our application running in them. The servers constantly running at semi-high loads. And then we went over it. 🔥</p>

<p><img src="/images/2019-10-02-a-tale-of-a-small-javascript-bug/loads-dropping.png" alt="Graph displaying the huge drop in load on our servers" /></p>

<p>Along the way we did some other optimisations:</p>

<ul>
<li>we implemented a rate limiter on the <code>/find</code> endpoint</li>
<li>we disallowed to register exactly the same callback twice for the same event using <code>Sonora.on()</code></li>
<li>we fixed a second bug in <code>Sonora.off()</code> where we didn't remove the correct callbacks sometimes</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="%F0%9F%98%87%F0%9F%92%AD-and-they-lived-happily-ever-after">😇💭 And they lived happily ever after</h2>

<p>This was the tale of the small JavaScript bug bringing down the huge web application, a modern David and Goliath if you will. Frontend debugging <em>tricks</em> can take down your application! Every change is important, certainly changes that happen in code that's used very frequently. Some changes that look inconspicuous can over time become real bottlenecks. Tools like Kibana and the browser profiler &amp; network tabs really helped us a great deal finding the issue, so don't forget what you have at your disposal.</p>

<p>We hope you enjoyed reading about our failures! Happy debugging! 👋</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[When too many API calls are breaking your app]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2017/11/02/javascript-deferred"/>
            <updated>2017-11-02T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2017/11/02/javascript-deferred</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, I was confronted with a strange issue regarding the "followers" component we have in our inbox.
It's a cool feature that gives you the possibility to check which connected Twitter account is following or followed by another Twitter account. Most accounts or users don't have that many connected Twitter profiles but of course there are always some exceptions. One of our customers had more than 100 connected profiles. The process to check the relationship between the profiles is rather easy. We do a call to the back-end for every profile. In the back-end we do an API call to Twitter to fetch the relationship details. So you can imagine it takes some time if we have to do this for many profiles. In the front-end the component became very slow and it looked like the component crashed.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2017-11-02-javascript-deferred/followers.png" alt="Clarabrige Engage followers dropdown in inbox" /></p>

<p>After finding out what the problem is, the next step is of course solving it. I started with checking the back-end for some improvements. Instead of calling Twitter's API for every single profile, I checked if we could ask for multiple relations at once. Sadly this wasn't the case. So this trail was a dead end.</p>

<p>If we can't change the API, we could try to avoid using the API as much as possible. By caching the result for some time, we could avoid requesting the same data multiple times as this also improves speed. This wasn't a good option either because the received data was already cached by us in the back-end.</p>

<p>The only thing I could still think of was trying to reduce the calls to the Twitter API or to our own API. Changing the back-end would be a lot of work because the endpoint is used in a lot of places in the front-end. So the only option I wanted to consider was making a change in the one place where we had the problem. In the inbox we loop over the profiles and do a seperate call for every profile. For every call to our API, we wait until we have the response before doing a new call. So instead of doing synchronous calls, we should consider doing the calls asynchronously.</p>

<p>Not knowing if this was possible in JavaScript, I started searching and fell upon the <code>Promise</code> object, which does exactly what we need. However, <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/Promise">the documentation for Promise on MDN</a> quickly revealed that it's not supported by some browsers we still have to support. After some more digging around the internet, we stumbled upon the <code>Deferred</code> object in jQuery which does almost the same, and works in most browsers. From its documentation:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It can register multiple callbacks into callback queues, invoke callback queues, and relay the success or failure state of any synchronous or asynchronous function</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So what we actually have to do is start all the calls to the back-end at once. Once we did that we create a new <code>Deferred</code> object. When all the <code>combinedCalls</code> are done, we can start updating our component. It only has to do one big update and it doesn't take that much time because the calls are all fired at the same time instead of one by one.</p>

<pre><code class="js">var profileIds = this.profileIds;

var calls = _.map(services, function (service) {
    var url = '/twitter/relation?accounts='+ service.id +'&amp;users=' + profileIds;

    return $.get(url);
});

var combinedResult = $.Deferred();

var combinedCalls = $.when.apply($, calls);

combinedCalls.done(function() {

    var resultsOfDefferedAjaxCalls = _.toArray(arguments).slice(0, calls.length);

    var relations = _.map(resultsOfDefferedAjaxCalls, function(ajaxResult) {
        return ajaxResult.result.data;
    });

    combinedResult.resolve(relations);
});

combinedCalls.fail(function() {
    // Combine args so that we can pass reason for
    // failure to reject()
    combinedResult.reject();
});

return combinedResult.promise();
</code></pre>

<p>So with some small changes we improved a lot on the loading time of the dropdown. The next problem was that some calls could take some time and if there is one slow call, all the other calls have to wait till the slowest call is finished. So I had to find another solution for this new problem. So instead of just calling the endpoint I added a callback function to the call.</p>

<pre><code class="js">var calls = _.map(services, function (service) {
    var url = '/twitter/relation?accounts='+ service.id +'&amp;users=' + profileIds;

    var onGoingCall = $.get(url);

    onGoingCall.done(callback);

    return onGoingCall;
});
</code></pre>

<p>The moment the call is finished, the callback is triggered and the component will update. You don't have to worry about slow calls because the component will update as soon as possible and the customer can see that data is loading and updating.</p>

<p>That's how we fixed this for now, hopefully we can move to the more modern approach of using <code>Promise</code> in the near future!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>